[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an air-breathing engine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Turbojet",
            "b) Turbofan",
            "c) Rocket",
            "d) Scramjet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Unlike turbojet, turbofan, scramjet, ramjet or turboprop engines, rockets are not air-breathing engines. It carries both fuel and oxidizer along with it, while the other engines suck in air to undergo combustion with the stored fuel."
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a valid classification of rocket engines based on their energy source?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chemical",
            "b) Geothermal",
            "c) Solar",
            "d) Nuclear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Chemical, solar, nuclear, electric are all different types of rocket engines based on their energy sources. But geothermal energy source is limited locally on earth and can’t be harnessed for the whole course of the rocket’s journey."
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "Question": "What is the range of temperature of reaction product gases in a rocket engine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 500 to 1700 °C",
            "b) 1700 to 2500 °C",
            "c) 2500 to 4100 °C",
            "d) 4100 to 6900 °C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The temperature at which product gases of the chemical reaction taking place within the combustion chamber is too high. It is even higher than the melting point of some of the more commonly used materials in aircraft industry like aluminum (660 °C). Appropriate cooling mechanisms are set up to ensure that this high temperature doesn’t transfer over to the rocket components and that it doesn’t lead to the development of thermal stresses."
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "Question": "Which of the following pressure feed systems is mostly used in attitude control of liquid propellant rocket engine with more than one thrust chamber per engine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The Gas pressure feed system",
            "b) Pump-fed system",
            "c) Gravity assisted feed system",
            "d) No feed system is used"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For attitude control of such vehicles, the thrust, as well as the total energy of the propulsion system should be low. Gas pressure feed system is suitable in such circumstances."
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "Question": "What is the typical liquid propellant feed system used in space launch vehicles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The Gas pressure feed system",
            "b) Pump-fed system",
            "c) Gravity assisted feed system",
            "d) No feed system is used"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In vehicles used for space launch, the thrust required and the overall energy of propulsion required is too high. In such cases, the rate of supply of propellants to the combustion chamber will be high. A pump fed system is capable of generating a large mass flow rate of the propellants. Hence it is used here."
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "Question": "For a constant thrust of 6000 N, find the total impulse for the burning time of 3s.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 36000 Ns",
            "b) 18000 Ns",
            "c) 9000 Ns",
            "d) 0 Ns"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Here we assume that the start and stop transients are negligible during the operation of the system. Then, for a constant thrust (F), and for the total burning time of t seconds, the total impulse It = Ft.\nIt = 6000 x 3 = 18000 Ns"
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "Question": "Suppose the thrust force of a rocket varies with time t as F = 250(3t2 + 2t). Then find out the total impulse for a burn duration of 4s.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10000 Ns",
            "b) 20000 Ns",
            "c) 40000 Ns",
            "d) 80000 Ns"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The total impulse can be obtained by integrating the force F with respect to time t from 0 to 3. The total impulse for a varying force F is obtained by It = ∫Fdt.\nIt = 250 x (tb3 + tb2) = 250 x (64 + 16) = 20,000 Ns."
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "Question": "For a rocket, the specific impulse was found to be 250s. Given that the thrust force is constant and assuming gravity-free and drag-free conditions, what will the thrust force be for a mass flow rate of the form (4t2-3t) kg/s and a burn duration of 3s?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 18375 N",
            "b) 12426 N",
            "c) 25234 N",
            "d) 15595 N"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Specific impulse Isp = ∫Fdt/(go∫mdt) where m is mass flow rate, go is standard acceleration due to gravity at sea level.\nThen Isp = Ftb/go(4tb3/3 – 3tb2/2).\nUsing tb = 3s, Isp = 250s, go = 9.8 m/s2,\nF = 250 x 9.8 x 22.5/3 = 18375 N."
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "Question": "Given that the total impulse is 25000 Ns and specific impulse is 300s, find out the effective propellant mass for a burn duration of 8s.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 17 kg",
            "b) 8.5 kg",
            "c) 34 kg",
            "d) 68 kg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Given Isp = 300s and It = 25000 Ns.\nUsing  Isp = It/mpgo, with go = 9.8 m/s2.\nmp = 25000 / (9.8 x 300) = 8.5 kg."
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "Question": "Consider two rocket engines A and B with A having a specific impulse of 242s and B having a specific impulse of 150s. What can be said about their efficiency?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Both A and B are equally efficient",
            "b) A is more efficient than B",
            "c) B is more efficient than A",
            "d) Efficiency doesn’t depend on specific impulse"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Higher specific impulse will result in better efficiency. Rocket A has a higher specific impulse than rocket B. Hence it is more efficient."
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "Question": "If the exit pressure is thrice the atmospheric pressure for a rocket A and if it is twice for rocket B, what will be the ratio of pressure thrust of rocket A to that of B?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pressure thrust is the difference between nozzle exit pressure and ambient pressure multiplied by nozzle exit area.\nPe = 3Pa for rocket A\nPe = 2Pa for rocket B\nPressure thrust Tp = (Pe-Pa)Ae\nSo TpA/TpB = 2Pa/Pa\n= 2."
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "Question": "In the expression of pressure thrust, what does the area (A) represent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The cross-sectional area of the throat",
            "b) The total surface area of the rocket casing",
            "c) The cross-sectional area of the nozzle exit",
            "d) The total surface area of the combustion chamber"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Area (A) represents the nozzle exit cross-sectional area. The expression for pressure thrust is (Pe-Pa)A, where Pe is the exit pressure and Pa is the ambient pressure."
    },
    {
        "id": 13,
        "Question": "If Pe represents exit pressure and Pa represents the atmospheric pressure, what is the condition for a nozzle to be overexpanded?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pe < Pa",
            "b) Pe > Pa",
            "c) Pe = Pa",
            "d) Pe = 0.5*Pa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For the overexpanded nozzle, Pe < Pa is the correct condition. In this case, the exhaust jet pressure is lower than the atmospheric pressure and the flow will be suppressed in its size because of compression resulting from outside pressure. When that happens, our nozzle (which was designed for the optimal condition or correctly expanded flows, where Pe = Pa) will look as if it was bigger than what was required."
    },
    {
        "id": 14,
        "Question": "What will happen to thrust and specific impulse as the rocket is propelled to higher altitudes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thrust decreases, specific impulse increases",
            "b) Thrust increases, specific impulse increases",
            "c) Thrust decreases, specific impulse decreases",
            "d) Thrust increases, specific impulse decreases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Atmospheric pressure decreases with increasing altitude. So the pressure thrust part of the total thrust increases and hence the total thrust increases. Specific impulse is impulse per unit weight of the propellant and proportional to thrust, so it too will increase."
    },
    {
        "id": 15,
        "Question": "The rocket nozzle is usually so designed such that the exhaust pressure is ____ the ambient fluid pressure.",
        "Options": [
            "a) greater than",
            "b) less than",
            "c) equal to",
            "d) equal to or slightly higher than"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Exhaust pressure should be such that it is equal to or slightly greater than the atmospheric pressure. Else the pressure thrust will be negative and lead to low overall thrust."
    },
    {
        "id": 16,
        "Question": "How does the total thrust vary with an extendable nozzle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) First increases, then decrease",
            "b) First decreases, then increase",
            "c) Keeps on increasing",
            "d) Keeps on decreasing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Initially as the nozzle is extended, thrust keeps increasing. This is because of the rate of increase in exhaust velocity being high compared to the decrease in exit pressure. This increase happens until the point where exit pressure equalizes atmospheric pressure. Afterward, the decrease in pressure thrust is more significant and as a result of this, the total thrust also decreases."
    },
    {
        "id": 17,
        "Question": "A rocket has a throat area of 10 mm2 and nozzle exit area of 25 mm2. If the mass flow rate of its propellants is 2 kg/s, exit velocity is 30 m/s, and if exit pressure is twice the standard atmospheric pressure at sea level, what will be the total thrust?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 60 N",
            "b) 62.53 N",
            "c) 61.26 N",
            "d) 65.06 N"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Total thrust = momentum thrust + pressure thrust.\nMomentum thrust = 2*30 = 60 N\nPressure thrust = (Pe-Pa)*Ae = 101325*25/1000000 = 2.53 N\nTotal thrust = 60 + 2.53 = 62.53 N."
    },
    {
        "id": 18,
        "Question": "Rocket A has twice the pressure thrust of rocket B while it has half the momentum thrust as that of B. If the momentum thrust of B is 5 times its pressure thrust, find the ratio of total thrust of A to B.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5",
            "b) 0.75",
            "c) 1",
            "d) 0.25"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Total thrust is the sum of momentum and pressure thrusts for a rocket engine. But for a gas turbine engine, it is the difference between the gross thrust and the ram drag."
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "Question": "Consider a rocket engine A and a jet engine B. Which of them will have higher specific impulse?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A",
            "b) B",
            "c) B doesn’t have a specific impulse",
            "d) A doesn’t have a specific impulse"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: B will have much higher specific impulse because it uses large amounts of outside air for combustion. Since specific impulse is impulse per unit amount of propellant and the stored propellant in jet engines is only the fuel (and not both fuel and oxidizer like in rocket engines), it will have a higher specific impulse."
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "Question": "If exhaust pressure is Pe and surrounding fluid pressure is Pa, what is the condition for the optimum expansion ratio of a rocket nozzle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pe=Pa",
            "b) Pe<Pa",
            "c) Pe>Pa",
            "d) Pe=0.5*Pa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For the optimum expansion of the nozzle, exhaust pressure should be equal to the ambient pressure. When that happens, the size of the rocket exhaust plume matches the size of the nozzle and losses are minimum."
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "Question": "A rocket produces a total thrust of 20,000 N. If the mass flow rate of propellants is 16 kg/s, what will be effective exhaust velocity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1250 m/s",
            "b) 2500 m/s",
            "c) 625 m/s",
            "d) 5000 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Total Thrust = mass flow rate x effective exhaust velocity. Here we assume that the mass flow rate is constant, flow is axially directed and frictional effects are neglected.\nSo, 20,000 = 16 x ueff\nueff = 20,000/16 = 1250 m/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "Question": "What is the characteristic velocity of a rocket if the chamber pressure is 5 MPa, the nozzle throat diameter is 75 mm and the mass flow rate is 25 kg/s?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 884 m/s",
            "b) 1768 m/s",
            "c) 3536 m/s",
            "d) 442 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Characteristic velocity = Chamber pressure x throat area / mass flow rate. It is an important performance parameter of rocket engines.\nSo, Characteristic velocity = [5 x 106 x π x (75 x 10-3)2/4] / 25 = 884 m/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "Question": "Characteristic velocity is a performance parameter that relates to the efficiency of _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) nozzle",
            "b) combustion chamber",
            "c) injector",
            "d) casing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Characteristic velocity can be used to compare the performance of combustion chambers in chemical rocket engines. It can also be used to compare different propellants and propulsion systems."
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "Question": "Which of the following variables is not useful in the determination of rocket effective exhaust velocity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mass flow rate",
            "b) Exhaust velocity",
            "c) Rocket velocity",
            "d) Exit area"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the formulation of effective exhaust velocity, mass flow rate, exhaust velocity, exit area, nozzle exit pressure, ambient pressure are all relevant variables. But the rocket velocity doesn’t come into picture in the final expression."
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "Question": "If C denotes effective exhaust velocity and Isp is specific impulse, then which of them is a better performance parameter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) C",
            "b) Isp",
            "c) Both of them are equal",
            "d) Both of them are equivalent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Isp = C/go, where go is the standard acceleration due to gravity at sea level. Since Isp and c differ only by a constant factor, they are equivalent."
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "Question": "If mo denotes initial mass, mb denotes burnout mass, then what is the expression for mass ratio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) (mo-mb)/mb",
            "b) (mo-mb)/mo",
            "c) mb/(mo-mb)",
            "d) mb/mo"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Correct expression of mass flow rate is mb/mo (according to Sutton). It is a measure of rocket efficiency and it gives us an idea about how massive the rocket is with and without propellants."
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "Question": "For a rocket traveling at 700 m/s having an exhaust velocity of 1.4 km/s, exhaust gas density of 0.3 kg/m3, nozzle throat diameter of 0.14 cm and nozzle exit diameter of 25 cm, find the total mass flow rate of the propellants.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6.46 kg/s",
            "b) 103.1 kg/s",
            "c) 20.62 kg/s",
            "d) 32.33 kg/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Mass flow rate of the propellants is the same as the mass flow rate of the rocket exhaust jet exiting the nozzle. That will be equal to the product of exhaust gas density, nozzle exit area, and exhaust velocity.\nm = ρ Ae ue\n= 0.3 x π/4 x (25 x 10-2)2 x 1400\n= 20.62 kg/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "Question": "What constitutes the exhaust gas at the nozzle exit of a chemical rocket engine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) combustion products of the propellants",
            "b) A mixture of combustion products and surrounding air",
            "c) Surrounding air",
            "d) Propellants"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The exhaust gas at the nozzle exit of a chemical rocket engine consists of combustion products of the propellants. If the combustion were inefficient, it would also contain unburnt propellants. Downstream of the nozzle exit, the exhaust jet entrains the surrounding air and becomes a mixture of both."
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not part of a rocket nozzle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Convergent section",
            "b) Divergent section",
            "c) Throat section",
            "d) Staggering section"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Main elements of a nozzle include convergent, divergent and throat sections. Staggered nozzle sections are uncommon and unfavorable for the smooth flow of exhaust gases."
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "Question": "What is the nozzle throat diameter of a rocket having chamber pressure (Pc) of 3 MPa, mass flow rate (m) of 20 kg/s and characteristic velocity (c*) of 1500 m/s?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 cm",
            "b) 11.3 cm",
            "c) 12.8 cm",
            "d) 25 cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: From the expression c* = Pc At / m, throat area At can be determined.\nAt = 1500 x 20/(3 x 106) = 0.01 m2\nAt = πd2/4\nd = \\(\\sqrt{(\\frac{4A_t}{π})}\\) \n= \\(\\sqrt{(\\frac{4 * 0.01}{π})}\\) \n= 0.112 m or 11.2 cm."
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "Question": "Which form of energy is most useful for propulsion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The kinetic energy of ejected matter",
            "b) The chemical energy of combustion of propellants",
            "c) The potential energy of the rocket at some altitude",
            "d) The electrical energy of the rocket control system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: At the nozzle exit, the exhaust gases are ejected with some kinetic energy. This is the most useful form of energy crucial to propulsion. Chemical energy produced from the combustion of propellants is of no use unless it can be harnessed for propelling the rocket forward by some means."
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "Question": "For a constant gas ejection velocity (v) of 1440 m/s and a mass flow rate (m) of 15 kg/s, find the power of the jet (Pjet).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7.78 MW",
            "b) 15.55 MW",
            "c) 31.10 MW",
            "d) 62.21 MW"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Power of the jet is 1/2mv2. It is the time rate of expenditure of ejected jet’s kinetic energy.\nPjet = 1/2 x 15 x 14402\n= 15.55 MW."
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "Question": "If the power of the jet is given to be 25 MW for a chemical rocket having a weight flow rate of 147 N/s, find out the vehicle’s specific impulse.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 98.2 s",
            "b) 372.6 s",
            "c) 186.3 s",
            "d) 243.5 s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Power of the jet can be expressed in terms of weight flow rate and specific impulse. It is given by 1/2wogoIsp2.\nPjet = 1/2 wo go Isp2\nIsp = \\(\\sqrt{(2Pjet/ ẇ_o g_o)}\\) \n= \\(\\sqrt{(2 * 25 * 10^6 /(147 * 9.8))}\\) \n= 186.3 s."
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "Question": "If a chemical rocket has a jet power of 18 MW, inert mass of 50 kg, a propellant mass of 1000 kg, then what is its specific power?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 34.28 kW/kg",
            "b) 17.14 kW/kg",
            "c) 8.91 kW/kg",
            "d) 25.43 kW/kg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Specific power is jet power divided by the total mass of that the propulsion system prior to its launch. It is lower for electric propulsion system when compared to chemical rockets. This is because of the heavier and relatively inefficient power source that it has to carry.\nPspec = Pjet / mtotal\nmtotal = minert + mprop\n= 50 + 1000 = 1050 kg\n∴ Pspec = 18 x 106 / 1050\n= 17.14 kW/kg."
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "Question": "What is the way of production of energy in a chemical rocket?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ionization of propellants",
            "b) Combustion of propellants",
            "c) Expulsion of propellants",
            "d) Atomization of propellants"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Propellants are mixed together and combusted to create energy for propulsion. Expulsion of propellants after combustion converts this energy into a more useful form (kinetic energy)."
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "Question": "Which of the following Is the maximum energy available per unit mass of chemical propellants?",
        "Options": [
            "a) heat of combustion",
            "b) enthalpy of vaporization",
            "c) enthalpy of atomization",
            "d) enthalpy of fusion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The heat of combustion is the maximum energy per unit mass that can be extracted from chemical propellants. It can be of two types – higher or lower heating value. Higher heating value is determined by taking all the propellants to their pre-combustion temperature and letting all the vapor produced in the reaction to condense."
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "Question": "For a propulsive device, if power available is denoted by P1, power input by P2, combustion efficiency by e, then which of the following expression is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) P1=P2*e",
            "b) P1=P2/e",
            "c) P1=P2/e2",
            "d) P1=P2*e2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: P1=P2*e is the correct expression. Input power will be reduced by a factor of combustion efficiency to become power available."
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "Question": "If a propulsion system produces a thrust of 5 kN, exhaust velocity of 4500 m/s, and vehicle velocity of 3000 m/s, what is the power transmitted to the vehicle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 225 MW",
            "b) 75 MW",
            "c) 10 MW",
            "d) 15 MW"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Power transmitted to the vehicle is the product of vehicle velocity and the thrust produced by the propulsion system. It is not the same as exhaust jet power.\nPtrans = T v\n= 5 x 103 x 3000\n= 15 MW."
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a way of losing energy in a chemical rocket?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Poor mixing",
            "b) Incomplete burning",
            "c) Heat loss to the walls",
            "d) Radial combustion propagation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Axial and radial combustion propagation are two different kinds of burning propagation. Poor mixing and incomplete burning constitute combustion losses."
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "Question": "For a rocket having 95% combustion efficiency, total chemical power of 17MW, a mass flow rate of propellants of 15 kg/s, and effective jet exhaust velocity of 1443 m/s, find the internal efficiency of rocket propulsion.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 97%",
            "b) 95%",
            "c) 93%",
            "d) 91%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Internal efficiency of rocket propulsion is the ratio of kinetic power in the jet to the available chemical power. It is an indicator of how much the system is capable of converting input energy into useful kinetic energy.\nPav chem = ηcomb x Ptot chem\n= 0.95 x 17 x 106 W\nηint = Pkinetic / Pav chem\n= 1/2μe2 / Pchem\n= 0.5 x 15 x 14432 / (0.95 x 17 x 106)\n≅ 0.966."
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about chemical rockets?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Relatively low values of specific impulse",
            "b) Relatively light machinery",
            "c) Very high thrust capability",
            "d) Very low specific power"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Chemical rockets have very high thrust capability. Because of this, chemical rockets have high specific power and high acceleration."
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "Question": "Which of the following vehicles is used where the flight time is long?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrical propulsion unit",
            "b) Solid propulsion system",
            "c) Liquid propulsion system",
            "d) Hybrid propulsion system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Electrical propulsion units have low thrust values. This means that it is a less viable option during take-offs and landing. Because of its very low acceleration potential, it takes a long period of time to accelerate and hence is suited for missions that are time intensive."
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "Question": "What is a sensible specific impulse value for a nuclear fission type rocket engine among the given options?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 300 s",
            "b) 600 s",
            "c) 800 s",
            "d) 2000 s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Chemical rocket engines have relatively lower values of specific impulse. Ion-electrostatic type of rocket engines have very high specific impulses, but they lag in their acceleration potential. Nuclear fission type rocket engines have typical values of the specific impulse around 600 s, while the arc-electro thermal ones have it around 800 s."
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "Question": "What is the typical order of magnitude of mass flow rate (in kg/s) for a chemical rocket engine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10",
            "b) 0.1",
            "c) 0.01",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Typical value of the mass flow rate for a chemical rocket engine is about 0.03. Nuclear fission and arc-electro thermal types of engines have it around the same order of magnitude."
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "Question": "Which of the following engines can achieve the maximum specific impulse of 5000 s?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ion-electrostatic",
            "b) Nuclear fission",
            "c) Hall effect",
            "d) Solar heating"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ion-electrostatic engine has a specific impulse of 1200-5000 s. Nuclear fission type engines have Isp of 500-860 s, while solar heating engines have it around 400-700 s."
    },
    {
        "id": 46,
        "Question": "What is the propulsion duration of resistojets?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Few seconds",
            "b) Few minutes",
            "c) Few days",
            "d) Few weeks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Resistojets have a propulsion duration spanning a few days. The chemical rocket engines have a propulsion duration lasting a few seconds to a few minutes, while for ion-electrostatic engines, it lasts for months."
    },
    {
        "id": 47,
        "Question": "In which of the propulsion systems is the maximum temperature achieved?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chemical",
            "b) Nuclear",
            "c) Arc heating",
            "d) Solar heating"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Arc heating can lead to temperatures of about 20,000 deg C. Chemical propulsion systems have a maximum temperature ranging from 2500-4100 deg C, while nuclear fission leads to temperatures of about 2700 deg C."
    },
    {
        "id": 48,
        "Question": "Which of the following types of engines use Xe as a typical working fluid?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Resistojets",
            "b) Electro thermal",
            "c) Hall effect",
            "d) Nuclear fission"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hall effect type of rocket engines uses Xe as a typical working fluid. Resistojet rockets typically use H2 or N2H4 as working fluid, while nuclear fission uses H2 and electro thermal one uses NH3, N2H4 or H2."
    },
    {
        "id": 49,
        "Question": "Which of the following can typically achieve maximum effective exhaust velocity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrostatic and electromagnetic",
            "b) Arcjet",
            "c) Solar heated H2",
            "d) Nuclear fission"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Electrostatic and electromagnetic type of propulsion system can achieve the maximum exhaust velocity out of the given options. It is typically of the order of 20,000 m/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 50,
        "Question": "A rocket engine moving at 500 m/s produces a total thrust of 9563 N, consuming propellants at the rate of 4.55 kg/s. The energy content of the propellants is 5.35 MJ/kg. Find the effective exhaust velocity.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2100 m/s",
            "b) 3936 m/s",
            "c) 1555 m/s",
            "d) 1400 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rocket thrust is the product of mass flow rate and effective exhaust velocity. Using this,\nue = T/m\n= 9563/4.55\n≈ 2100 m/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 51,
        "Question": "For an ideal rocket, what should be the nature of the working substance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Homogeneous",
            "b) Heterogeneous",
            "c) Anisotropic",
            "d) Amorphous"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The working substance and chemical products should be homogeneous. When we say a substance is homogeneous, we intend to say that its composition and character is uniform throughout the substance."
    },
    {
        "id": 52,
        "Question": "What is the allowable amount of heat (in % of total available energy) that can be transferred across the walls of an ideal rocket?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0%",
            "b) 10%",
            "c) 15%",
            "d) 5%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: An ideal rocket doesn’t allow any heat transfer to take place across its walls. The flow, in this case, would be adiabatic. So, 0% of heat transfer takes place across the walls of an ideal rocket."
    },
    {
        "id": 53,
        "Question": "An ideal rocket has a chamber pressure of 1 MPa and a temperature of 1600 K. Determine the density of the combustion product if its molecular mass is 24 kg/kmol.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.2 kg/m3",
            "b) 2.4 kg/m3",
            "c) 1.8 kg/m3",
            "d) 3.6 kg/m3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Ideal rockets have working substances that follow perfect gas law. Hence using P=ρRT, we can determine the density of the combustion product.\nR = Ru / Mmol = 8314 / 24 = 346.42 J kg-1K-1\nρ = P/RT = 1 x 106 / (346.42 x 1600)\n= 1.8 kg/m3."
    },
    {
        "id": 54,
        "Question": "Which of the following statements is correct for an ideal rocket?",
        "Options": [
            "a) All kinds of frictional effects are not present, but the boundary layer cannot be neglected",
            "b) All discontinuities are not present, but shock waves are allowable",
            "c) Propellant flow is steady but constant",
            "d) The expansion of the working fluid is steady, but need not be uniform"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In an ideal rocket, propellant flow is considered to be steady and constant. In such a vehicle, all kinds of frictional effects and boundary layers are neglected along with the possible discontinuities in flow such as shock waves. The expansion of the working fluid is both steady as well as uniform."
    },
    {
        "id": 55,
        "Question": "Select the correct option for an ideal rocket engine.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The exhaust gases leaving the rocket need not be axially directed",
            "b) Across any cross-section normal to the nozzle axis, gas velocity need not be uniform",
            "c) The gas composition can vary across the nozzle",
            "d) Cryogenic propellants need to be stored at their boiling points"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Exhaust gases leaving the ideal rocket nozzle is axially directed. Gas pressure, temperature, and velocity needs to be uniform across the nozzle axis and the gas composition remains the same along with the nozzle."
    },
    {
        "id": 56,
        "Question": "Which of the following relations won’t hold in an ideal rocket engine’s nozzle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Isentropic expansion relations",
            "b) Conductive heat transfer relations",
            "c) Homogeneous flow relations",
            "d) Ideal gas law relations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The ideal rocket engine has adiabatic walls. Hence heat transfer cannot happen through the walls. At the same time, the nozzle flow obeys isentropic (reversible and adiabatic), homogeneous expansion relations and ideal gas laws."
    },
    {
        "id": 57,
        "Question": "For typical real rocket engines, what is the approximate amount of energy lost (from the available energy pool) due to heat transfer to the walls of the rocket?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1%",
            "b) 10%",
            "c) 5%",
            "d) 15%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The energy loss by heat transfer to the walls is usually less than 1% and occasionally may go up to 2% of the total energy. Because of that, the heat transfer effects can be neglected in real rockets."
    },
    {
        "id": 58,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a reasonable depiction of the mass distribution in practical chemical rockets?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50% propellants, 50% inert mass",
            "b) 10% propellants 90% inert mass",
            "c) 90% propellants 10% inert mass",
            "d) 40% propellants 60% inert mass"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Much of the rocket mass is constituted by the mass of the propellants. Rest of the mass includes the rocket structure, its engines, and its payload."
    },
    {
        "id": 59,
        "Question": "Find the propellant mass fraction for a rocket having a structural mass of 150 kg, a payload mass of 20 kg and propellant mass of 1000 kg.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.65",
            "b) 0.85",
            "c) 0.95",
            "d) 0.45"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The propellant mass fraction is the ratio of propellant mass to the initial mass of the vehicle.\nMinert = Mstruct + Mpayload = 150 + 20 = 170 kg\nMinitial = Minert + Mprop = 170 + 1000 = 1170 kg\nPropellant mass fraction η = Mprop / Minitial = 1000/1170 ≈ 0.85."
    },
    {
        "id": 60,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a feature of the combustion chamber in an ideal chemical rocket engine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High pressure",
            "b) High temperature",
            "c) Low flow velocity",
            "d) Higher transient time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: An ideal chemical rocket engine has high pressure, high temperature and low flow velocity. The transient time is very low to ensure that the flow and associated processes are steady and remains constant at all times."
    },
    {
        "id": 61,
        "Question": "Which of the following comprises of internal thermal energy and flow work?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Entropy",
            "b) Enthalpy",
            "c) Kinetic energy",
            "d) Potential energy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Enthalpy comprises of flow work and internal thermal energy. Flow work arises when a fluid crosses a boundary with some velocity v. Entropy is a measure of the degree of randomness of a system."
    },
    {
        "id": 62,
        "Question": "In which of the following cases can enthalpy be expressed as a function of constant Cp and absolute temperature T?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ideal gas",
            "b) Calorically perfect gas",
            "c) Real gas",
            "d) Thermally perfect gas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A calorically perfect gas obeys ideal gas law and has constant Cp. A thermally perfect gas obeys ideal gas law, but it has a temperature dependent Cp value. A real gas is an imperfect gas that doesn’t follow the ideal gas relations and has Cp values that are temperature and pressure dependent."
    },
    {
        "id": 63,
        "Question": "Find the stagnation enthalpy of a calorically perfect gas having a flow velocity of 94 m/s and static temperature of 315 K. (Cp=1005 J/kg/K)",
        "Options": [
            "a) 321 kJ/kg",
            "b) 234 kJ/kg",
            "c) 456 kJ/kg",
            "d) 543 kJ/kg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Since the gas is calorically perfect, h = Cp T, where h is the static enthalpy and T is the static temperature.\nh = Cp T\n= 1005 x 315\n= 316,575 J/kg\nThen using the relation h0 = h + v2/2,\nh0 = 316,575 + 4324.5\n≅ 321 kJ/kg."
    },
    {
        "id": 64,
        "Question": "For an incompressible subsonic flow over a nozzle, at a typical location A along the nozzle, the diameter of the cross-section was found to be 30 cm. What will be the diameter of the cross section at a point B where the flow velocity was determined to be twice the value at A?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 21.21 cm",
            "b) 42.42 cm",
            "c) 15 cm",
            "d) 60 cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Given flow over the nozzle is subsonic and incompressible. So density doesn’t vary along the nozzle and the flow velocity is less than about 0.3 times the speed of sound. In this case, the product of the nozzle area and flow velocity at any location along the nozzle length remains to be the same.\nA1V1 = A2 V2\nGiven V2 = 2 V1\nd22/4 = (d12/4) V1/V2\n⇒ d2 = d1 √0.5\n= 21.21 cm."
    },
    {
        "id": 65,
        "Question": "For an isentropic flow along a nozzle, at location A, the static temperature and pressure were measured to be 320 K and 5 bar. What will be the static pressure at the location where the static temperature is 500 K? (Given η = 1.4)",
        "Options": [
            "a) 23.8 bar",
            "b) 32.4 bar",
            "c) 12.4 bar",
            "d) 7.4 bar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For the isentropic flow, adiabatic relations can be applied (isentropic means reversible as well as adiabatic).\nThen using P1/P2 = (T1/T2)(η/η-1)\nP2 = 5 x (500/320)1.4/0.4\n≅23.8 bar."
    },
    {
        "id": 66,
        "Question": "An isentropic flow at section x has a velocity of 200 m/s and static enthalpy of 360 kJ/kg. Determine the flow velocity at a location y where the static enthalpy is half the value at x.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 447.2 m/s",
            "b) 385.9 m/s",
            "c) 515.4 m/s",
            "d) 408.2 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For an isentropic flow, stagnation enthalpy remains constant.\nStagnation enthalpy  h0 = h + v2/2 is constant.\nSo h1 + v12/2 = h2 + v22/2\nv2 = √2(360,000 – 180000 + 40000/2)\n= 447.2 m/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 67,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a unit of gas constant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) J/(mol.K)",
            "b) kcal/(K.mol)",
            "c) m3atm/(K.mol)",
            "d) amu.m2s2/K"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The unit amu corresponds to the unified mass unit or atomic mass unit. The correct expression should have been amu.m2/(s2.K)."
    },
    {
        "id": 68,
        "Question": "For an isentropic flow of air through a pipe from a large chamber having a pressure of 5 MPa and temperature of 290 K, determine the temperature at a point along the length of the pipe where the pressure is 3 MPa.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 250 K",
            "b) 277 K",
            "c) 219 K",
            "d) 300 K"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the large chamber, the flow can be assumed to be stagnant. Given that the flow is isentropic, adiabatic relations can be applied to the flow. Using P/P0 = (T/T0)(η/η-1) and taking the value of to be 1.4 (for air),\nT = (3/5)0.4/1.4 x 290\n≅250 K."
    },
    {
        "id": 69,
        "Question": "Which of the following doesn’t happen during a subsonic and isentropic nozzle expansion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase in the specific volume",
            "b) Decrease in absolute fluid static temperature",
            "c) Decrease in static pressure",
            "d) Decrease in stagnation temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Stagnation temperature for an isentropic process remains constant. Static temperature, static pressure, and specific volume may vary."
    },
    {
        "id": 70,
        "Question": "Acoustic velocity in ideal gases is independent of _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) nature of the gas",
            "b) gas temperature",
            "c) gas pressure",
            "d) the molecular mass of the gas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Acoustic velocity (a) is the same as the velocity of sound in the medium under consideration. It is dependent on the nature of the medium, its temperature, and its molar mass. This can be observed from the relation a = \\(\\sqrt{(\\eta RT)}\\), where η is the ratio of specific heats (which depends upon the type of gas), R is the gas constant for the particular gas (R = Ru/M, where Ru is universal gas constant and M is the molar mass of the gas) and the gas temperature (T)."
    },
    {
        "id": 71,
        "Question": "Which of the following will happen if there is a flow obstruction in the nozzle inner wall?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Local conversion of kinetic to thermal energy",
            "b) Local drop in pressure around the region of obstruction",
            "c) Formation of normal shock waves at the point of obstruction",
            "d) Rapid decrease in mass flow rate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the presence of an obstruction, a stagnation zone develops locally, leading to the conversion of useful kinetic energy to thermal energy. It decreases the overall performance of the engine. In the stagnation zone, the local pressure is the stagnation pressure whose value is larger than the static pressure. Point of obstruction may or may not have normal shock waves and it depends on the flow velocity, the shape of the obstruction, nature of the gas flowing through the nozzle, etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 72,
        "Question": "If at a  point along the isentropic rocket nozzle, the temperature of the gas is 718 K, and the flow velocity is 150 m/s, determine the nozzle exit velocity, given the exhaust gas temperature is 460 K (Assume Cp = 1005 J/kg K)",
        "Options": [
            "a) 840.25 m/s",
            "b) 735.58 m/s",
            "c) 913.07 m/s",
            "d) 374.95 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Since the process is isentropic and since no work is done in the nozzle, stagnation enthalpy (ho) is constant.\nho = h + v2/2 = const.\nThen, h1 + v12/2 = he + ve2/2\nWriting h = CpT, we have\nve = \\(\\sqrt{(2C_p(T_1-T_e) +v_1^2)}\\) \n= 735.58 m/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 73,
        "Question": "If the rocket exhaust gases are calorically perfect and have a mean molecular mass of 28 kg/kmol, and a constant specific heat ratio (γ) of 1.33, determine the nozzle exit velocity. Assume the nozzle inlet conditions to be the following: P1 = 5 MPa, V1 = 240 m/s, T1 = 750 K and exit pressure (Pe) to be 1 MPa.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 204 m/s",
            "b) 699.21 m/s",
            "c) 712.32 m/s",
            "d) 805.56 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Using the adiabatic relation, Pe / P1 = (Te / T1)γ/γ-1,\nTe = T1(Pe / P1)γ/γ-1\nTe = 750 x (1/5)0.33/1.33 = 503 K\nR = Ru / Mmol = 8314/28 = 297 J / kg K.\nCp = γR/(γ-1) = 1.33 x 297 / 0.33 = 1197 J / kg K.\nho is constant. So, h1 + v12/2 = he + ve2/2.\nUsing this, ve = \\(\\sqrt{(2C_p(T_1-T_e) +v_1^2)}\\) \n= \\(\\sqrt{(2*1197*( 750 – 503) + 240^2)}\\) \n= 805.56 m/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 74,
        "Question": "What is the correct definition of the nozzle area expansion ratio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The ratio of nozzle exit area to the throat area",
            "b) The ratio of the nozzle area at the inflection point to the throat area",
            "c) The ratio of throat area to the nozzle inlet area",
            "d) The ratio of throat area to the area at the point of inflection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For a de Laval Nozzle, the area is inversely proportional to the ratio v/V. This follows from the continuity equation."
    },
    {
        "id": 75,
        "Question": "Which of the following will improve the performance of a rocket engine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decrease in gas temperature",
            "b) Increase in the molecular mass of the propellant",
            "c) Decrease in the pressure ratio",
            "d) Increase in the chamber pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Nozzle area expansion ratio is the ratio of the nozzle exit area to the nozzle’s throat area. The throat area is the smallest area and lies in between the convergent and divergent portions of a de Laval nozzle."
    },
    {
        "id": 76,
        "Question": "What are the standardized chamber pressure and exit pressure values used for comparing the specific impulse values or various design parameters of different rocket engines?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1000 psia, 1 atm",
            "b)1000 atm, 1 psia",
            "c) 100 psia, 1 atm",
            "d)100 atm, 1 psia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Increase of chamber pressure P1 will help in performance improvement of the rocket engine. With the increase in pressure ratio Prc = P1/P2, performance increases (here P2 denotes the exit pressure). From the expression for exhaust velocity v2 = \\(\\sqrt{(2\\gamma R_uT_0(1-P_{rc}^{1-\\gamma/\\gamma})/(\\gamma-1)M_{mol})}\\), it can be seen that decrease in propellant molecular mass will aid in increased exhaust jet velocity and hence enhanced performance."
    },
    {
        "id": 77,
        "Question": "What is the expression for the maximum theoretical value of the nozzle outlet velocity (ve) with an infinite expansion, if γ represents the ratio of specific heats, To represents the chamber temperature, R is the gas constant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ve = \\(\\sqrt{(2\\gamma RT_o(\\gamma-1))}\\) ",
            "b) ve = \\(\\sqrt{(2\\gamma RT_o/(\\gamma-1))}\\) ",
            "c) ve = \\(\\sqrt{(2(\\gamma+1)RT_o/(\\gamma-1))}\\) ",
            "d) ve = \\(\\sqrt{(2(\\gamma-1)RT_o(\\gamma+1))}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Specific impulse and other design parameters of various rocket engines are compared with one another while assuming some general standard values for the chamber pressure and exit pressure. A chamber pressure of 1000 psia and an exit pressure of 1 atm are typically in use today. (1 psia = 6894.76 Pa and 1 atm = 101.325 Pa)."
    },
    {
        "id": 78,
        "Question": "What is the pressure ratio for the maximum theoretical value of nozzle outlet velocity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Infinite",
            "b) Zero",
            "c) Finite value < 1",
            "d) Finite value > 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: ve = \\(\\sqrt{(2R\\gamma T_o/(\\gamma-1))}\\) is the correct expression. It is obtained from the bigger expression v2 = \\(\\sqrt{(2\\gamma R_uT_0(1-P_{rc}^{1-\\gamma/\\gamma})/(\\gamma-1)M_{mol})}\\). Here Prc = P1/P2, where P2 is the exit pressure and P1 is the chamber pressure. The maximum theoretical value is possible when P2/P1 = 0, i.e. when the jet is exhausted to vacuum."
    },
    {
        "id": 79,
        "Question": "What will happen if the maximum theoretical nozzle exhaust velocity tends to a very large value?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Working fluid ceases to be a gas",
            "b) The temperature of the working fluid increases exponentially",
            "c) The thermal energy content of the fluid becomes infinite",
            "d) The flow undergoes rapid compression"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pressure ratio Prc = P1 / P2, where P2 is the jet exit pressure and P1 is the chamber pressure. For the maximum theoretical value of nozzle outlet velocity, the flow has to be exhausted to vacuum. So P2 = 0 or in other words, Prc → ∞."
    },
    {
        "id": 80,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a reason why the wall surface throughout the nozzle is smooth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Minimize friction",
            "b) Minimize radiation absorption",
            "c) Minimize convective heat transfer",
            "d) Minimize flow velocity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Smooth wall surface allows smooth passage of flow through the nozzle. It won’t minimize the flow velocity. Since friction is dependent on surface roughness, it will be less for a smoother nozzle. Smoother surfaces will also increase the reflectivity of the material. Since reflectivity + transmissivity + absorptivity = 1, increasing reflectivity reduces the absorptivity of the material."
    },
    {
        "id": 81,
        "Question": "Which of the following is permissible in a rocket nozzle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gaps",
            "b) Smooth edges",
            "c) Holes",
            "d) Protrusions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Gaps, holes, and protrusions obstruct the flow passage through the nozzle. An ideal rocket requires the flow to be uniform at any cross-section throughout the length of the nozzle."
    },
    {
        "id": 82,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an objective of a good nozzle configuration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decrease nozzle inert mass",
            "b) Increase nozzle length",
            "c) Obtain the highest practical specific impulse",
            "d) Decrease nozzle diameter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Increase in nozzle length would lead to more material consumption, which means an increase in inert mass. It will also mean a larger exposed surface area of the rocket and while operating under atmospheric conditions will lead to higher drag."
    },
    {
        "id": 83,
        "Question": "What is the nozzle correction factor for a conical nozzle angle of 200?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.992",
            "b) 0.969",
            "c) 1.939",
            "d) 0.939"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: λ = 1/2 (1 + cosα), where α is the semi-divergence angle for a conical nozzle.\nHere, α = 20/2 = 10°\n∴ λ = 0.5 x ( 1 + 0.985)\n= 0.992."
    },
    {
        "id": 84,
        "Question": "What happens to the theoretical nozzle correction factor as the nozzle angle decreases?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) Increases first and then decreases",
            "d) Decreases first and then increases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: λ = 1/2 (1 + cosα). As nozzle angle 2α decreases, cosα decreases, and λ also keeps decreasing. If the divergence angle is small for a conical nozzle, it causes most of the momentum to be axially directed and will lead to an increase in specific impulse."
    },
    {
        "id": 85,
        "Question": "To which of the following terms can we multiply the nozzle correction factor with?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Total thrust",
            "b) Momentum thrust",
            "c) Pressure thrust",
            "d) Pressure ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Nozzle correction factor needs to be multiplied with momentum thrust term only. The flow momentum is affected by the change in divergence angle of a conical nozzle."
    },
    {
        "id": 86,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a typical optimum divergence angle for a conical nozzle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10°",
            "b) 30°",
            "c) 40°",
            "d) 60°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Typical half-angle of a conical nozzle lies in between 12° to 18°. So the conical nozzle divergence angle should be between 24° to 36°, so 30° angle is a plausible option."
    },
    {
        "id": 87,
        "Question": "How does the divergence angle vary along a bell-shaped nozzle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sharply increases, then decrease",
            "b) Sharply decreases, then increase",
            "c) Remains constant for a while and then increases",
            "d) Remains constant for a while and then decreases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For a bell-shaped nozzle, immediately after the throat section, the nozzle divergence angle increases rapidly and then it gradually decreases. It allows the flow to smoothly follow the contour without separation and leave the nozzle with more axially directed flow momentum (for eg. relative to conical nozzles)."
    },
    {
        "id": 88,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a reason why large divergence angles are allowed in bell-shaped nozzles immediately behind the throat?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High relative pressure",
            "b) Large pressure gradient",
            "c) Rapid expansion of the working fluid",
            "d) Supersonic flow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Large divergence angles are allowed in bell-shaped nozzles because flow separation is suppressed by high relative pressure and large pressure gradient in the divergent portion. The working fluid rapidly expands in this region. But the flow need not be supersonic at all times."
    },
    {
        "id": 89,
        "Question": "What is the difference between the angle at the nozzle inflection point and the angle at the exit called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Contour angle",
            "b) Divergence angle",
            "c) Semi-divergence angle",
            "d) Turn-back angle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Turn-back angle is the difference between the nozzle angle at the exit and the angle at the inflection point. Between inflection point and the exit, when the gas flow is turned in the opposite direction, it leads to the formation of oblique compression waves."
    },
    {
        "id": 90,
        "Question": "If the divergence angle for a conical nozzle is 30°, nozzle exit diameter is 30 cm, exit pressure is 10% more than the ambient pressure, mass flow rate is 14 kg/s and the jet exhaust velocity is 700 m/s, determine the total thrust of the engine under standard sea level operating conditions.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 11.2 kN",
            "b) 12.9 kN",
            "c) 10.3 kN",
            "d) 9.8 kN"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Total thrust = Corrected momentum thrust + Pressure thrust\nTtot = λTmom + Tpres\nλ = 1/2 (1 + cosα)\nα = 1/2 x 30° = 15°\nSo, λ = 1/2 (1 + 0.966)\n= 0.983\nTpres = (Pe – Pa)Ae\nSince the operation is under standard sea level conditions, Pa = 101325 Pa.\nPe = 110% of Pa.\nSo Pe – Pa = 10% of Pa = 10132.5 Pa\nAe = π de2/4 = 0.071\n∴ Tpres = 10132.5 x 0.071 = 719.075 N\nTmom = μe\n= 14 x 700 = 9800 N\nSo Ttot = (0.983 x 9800) + 719.075 ≅ 10.3 kN."
    },
    {
        "id": 91,
        "Question": "If for a bell-shaped nozzle, the divergence angle immediately after the throat is 40°, contour angle at the inflection point is 32° and the nozzle full-angle at its exit is 10°, determine the turn-back angle.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8°",
            "b) 35°",
            "c) 27°",
            "d) 22°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Divergence angle is the difference between the angle at the inflection point and the angle at the nozzle exit.\nθi = contour angle at the inflection point = 32°\nθe = 1/2 x full-angle at the exit = 5°\nθturn-back = θi – θe\n= 32° – 5° = 27°."
    },
    {
        "id": 92,
        "Question": "For an asymmetric nozzle section of diameter 12 cm, determine the average value of flow velocity if the velocity distribution is of the form v2 = (2r – 3r2) x 104 m/s, where r denotes the radial location in the cross-section plane.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1104.4 m/s",
            "b) 765.4 m/s",
            "c) 891.4 m/s",
            "d) 404 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: V2av = (2π/A2)∫v2rdr integrating over 0 to r2.\nA2 = πd22/4\n= 0.011 m2\n∫v2rdr = ∫ (2r2 – 3r3)x 104 dr\n= {(2/3)r23 – (3/4)r24} x 104\nr2 = d2/2 = 0.06 m\nso V2av = (2π/0.011) x 1.34\n= 765.4 m/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 93,
        "Question": "In a boundary layer flow along with the nozzle, why is the layer closest to the wall cooler?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flow velocity is minimum; Low energy flow leads to less temperature",
            "b) Heat transfer to the walls",
            "c) Radial heat propagation from the nozzle axis is a very slow process",
            "d) Mass flow rate closer to the nozzle axis is maximum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Because of heat transfer to the wall, the fluid layer closer to the wall will be cooler. But the boundary layer as a whole will have a higher temperature than the free stream flow because as the flow is slowed down in a boundary layer, it will lead to the conversion of flow kinetic energy to heat energy by viscous friction."
    },
    {
        "id": 94,
        "Question": "In which of the following cases is the effect of the boundary layer more pronounced?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Longer nozzles with high area ratios",
            "b) Shorter nozzles with high area ratios",
            "c) Longer nozzles with low area ratios",
            "d) Shorter nozzles with low area ratios"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In longer nozzles with high area ratios, a relatively higher proportion of mass flow is found to be lying within the low-velocity region of the boundary layer. When that happens, the boundary layer plays a significant role in reducing the performance of the rocket engine."
    },
    {
        "id": 95,
        "Question": "What happens to the solid particles in multiphase flow at the nozzle exit when the size of the particles increases?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lower momentum and lower thermal energy",
            "b) Higher momentum and lower thermal energy",
            "c) Lower momentum and higher thermal energy",
            "d) Higher momentum and higher thermal energy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As the particle size increases, its mass increases as a function of the cube of the diameter, but the drag force on them increases only as a function of the square of its diameter. So larger particles do not move as fast as smaller ones and when they reach the nozzle exit, their temperature is higher because they give away less thermal energy."
    },
    {
        "id": 96,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct expression for particle fraction β? Given: Total mass = mT, mass of the particles = mp.",
        "Options": [
            "a) mT/mp + mT",
            "b) mp/mp + mT",
            "c) mp/mT",
            "d) mT/mp"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Particle fraction is defined as the ratio of the mass of the particle to the total mass. Enthalpy (h), gas constant (R), specific volume (V), etc can be specified as a function of particle fraction in a multiphase flow."
    },
    {
        "id": 97,
        "Question": "How do the characteristic velocity (c) and the specific impulse (Isp) vary as particle fraction β is increased?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Both Isp and c decreases",
            "b) Both Isp and c increases",
            "c) Isp decreases, c increases",
            "d) Isp increases, c decreases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Both specific impulse and characteristic velocity decrease as the particle fraction is increased. The loss of specific impulse is about 2% if the particle fraction is small (less than 6%). For larger values of particle fraction, the theory is not helpful and the losses can be as high as 10 to 20%."
    },
    {
        "id": 98,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not correct for transient periods when compared to steady periods of rocket operation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lower average thrust",
            "b) Higher chamber pressure",
            "c) Lower specific impulse",
            "d) Higher velocity variations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Transient period happens during the start or end of the operation, i.e. when the process hasn’t achieved a steady state yet. In that period, the chamber pressure, average thrust and specific impulse values are lower than its steady-state values and the velocity variations are significant."
    },
    {
        "id": 99,
        "Question": "Which of the following terms denote the ratio of kinetic energy per unit flow of the actual jet leaving the nozzle to that of a hypothetical ideal one with the same working substance, initial state and exit pressure as that of the actual exhaust jet?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Velocity correction factor (ζv)",
            "b) Discharge correction factor (ζd)",
            "c) Thrust correlation factor (ζF)",
            "d) Energy efficiency factor (e)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Energy efficiency factor (e) compares the kinetic energy of actual jet leaving the nozzle to that of a jet leaving an ideal nozzle while assuming the same working fluids, initial states, and exit pressure. e = v2a2/v2i2 = v2a2/{v1a2 + Cp(T1-T2)}."
    },
    {
        "id": 100,
        "Question": "Determine the velocity correction factor (ζv) if the energy conversion efficiency is 0.94.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.97",
            "b) 0.85",
            "c) 0.92",
            "d) 0.99"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: ζv = \\(\\sqrt{e}\\), where e is the energy conversion efficiency.\nSo ζv = \\(\\sqrt{0.94}\\) = 0.97 is the final answer."
    },
    {
        "id": 101,
        "Question": "Find the actual mass flow rate for a discharge correction factor (ζd) of 1.15. For an ideal nozzle of same design and initial state, the following information is given: Volume flow rate (Q) = 0.53 m3/s; static temperature (T) = 590 K; static pressure (P) = 0.15 MPa; R = 287 J/kg/K.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.47",
            "b) 0.88",
            "c) 0.28",
            "d) 0.54"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: ζd = actual mass flow rate / ideal mass flow rate = ma / mi.\nFor ideal conditions, ρ = P / RT = 0.15 x 106 / (287 x 590) = 0.886 kg/m3.\nmi = ρAV = ρQ = 0.886 x 0.53 = 0.47 kg/s.\n∴ ma = 1.15 x 0.47 = 0.54 kg/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 102,
        "Question": "How are delivered performance values estimated for a propulsion system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Static tests or flight tests of full-scale models",
            "b) Dimensional analysis and similitude of models",
            "c) A theoretical analysis using the known relations",
            "d) Using computational simulation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Theoretical and actual (or delivered) performance values of a propulsion system may not be equal at all times. For evaluating delivered performance parameter values, static tests or flight test of full-scale models are used."
    },
    {
        "id": 103,
        "Question": "What is another name for the nozzle area ratio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nozzle expansion ratio",
            "b) Nozzle contraction ratio",
            "c) Nozzle convergence ratio",
            "d) Nozzle divergence ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Nozzle area ratio is defined as Ae/A*, where Ae denotes exit area and A* denotes throat area. Nozzle contraction area ratio is Ai/A*, where Ai is the inlet area of the nozzle."
    },
    {
        "id": 104,
        "Question": "If isentropic efficiency for expansion in a nozzle having a mass flow rate of 90 kg/s is 0.95, find the exit area. Given the low speed entrance pressure is 250 kPa, temperature is 375 °C and outside atmospheric pressure is 101 kPa. Assume Cp = 1005 J/(kgK) and γ = 1.33.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.133 m2",
            "b) 0.210 m2",
            "c) 0.295 m2",
            "d) 0.225 m2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Choking occurs if Pe/Po < {2/(γ+1)}γ/γ-1\n{2/(γ+1)}γ/γ-1 = (2/2.33)(1.33/0.33) = 0.54\nHere Pe/Po = 0.4. Hence its a C-D nozzle.\nTe = To(Pe/Po)γ-1/γ = 648 x (101/250)0.33/1.33 = 517.5 K\nve = \\(\\sqrt{(2C_p(T_t-T_e))} = \\sqrt{(2 * 1005 * (648 – 517.5))}\\) = 512.16 m/s\nρe = Pe/RTe = 0.78 kg/m3 (Take Cp = γR/(γ-1) to get approximate value of R)\nUsing m = ρeAeve,\nAe = m/ρeve = 90/(0.78×512.16) = 0.225 m2."
    },
    {
        "id": 105,
        "Question": "Find the critical pressure ratio for a nozzle flow from a chamber of pressure 300 kPa to the atmospheric pressure of 100 kPa. Assume γ = 1.4.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.637",
            "b) 0.528",
            "c) 0.981",
            "d) 0.243"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Critical pressure ratio = {2/(γ+1)}γ/γ-1\nUsing γ=1.4, we have the value equal to (2/2.4)1.4/0.4 = 0.528."
    },
    {
        "id": 106,
        "Question": "Determine the acoustic speed in chamber conditions if the chamber pressure is 500 kPa, density is 0.8 kg/m3 and γ=1.4.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 900.2 m/s",
            "b) 879.5 m/s",
            "c) 935.4 m/s",
            "d) 1014.2 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: a = \\(\\sqrt{(\\gamma RT)}\\). Assuming the gas to be ideal, P/ρ = RT. So, a = \\(\\sqrt{(\\gamma P_o/\\rho_o)} = \\sqrt{(1.4 * 500 * 1000/0.8)}\\) = 935.4 m/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 107,
        "Question": "For a slightly over-expanded supersonic exhaust from a nozzle with exit area of 0.110 m2, flow pressure of 180 kPa and an atmospheric pressure of 100 kPa, determine the approximate distance between the nozzle and the first shock diamond.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30.2 cm",
            "b) 25.9 cm",
            "c) 28.5 cm",
            "d) 33.6 cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A thermally isolated gas tank discharges slowly than an isothermal one. This is because in the isothermal gas tank, in order to maintain the temperature constant, any kind of heat addition will result in an increase of tank pressure thereby resulting in a faster ejection."
    },
    {
        "id": 108,
        "Question": "If a nozzle has an optimum expansion ratio of 9, determine the nozzle cone exit diameter for a throat diameter of 15 mm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30 mm",
            "b) 135 mm",
            "c) 45 mm",
            "d) 90 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The required distance x = 0.67Do√(P0/P1), where Do is the nozzle diameter, Po is the flow pressure and P1 is the atmospheric pressure.\nDo = \\(\\sqrt{(4A_e/\\pi)} = \\sqrt{(4 * 0.110/\\pi)}\\) = 0.374 m.\nx = 0.67 * 0.374 * \\(\\sqrt{(180/100)}\\) = 0.336 m or 33.6 cm."
    },
    {
        "id": 109,
        "Question": "Determine the rocket thrust coefficient for a total thrust of 20 kN, chamber pressure of 500 kPa and a throat diameter of 10 cm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.39",
            "b) 6.51",
            "c) 4.97",
            "d) 5.09"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Ae/A* = 9.\nSo de2/d*2 = 9 (Since A = πd2/4).\nWhich means de = d* x 3 = 45 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 110,
        "Question": "Determine the jet exhaust velocity, if the flow has an exit Mach number of 3 and temperature of 700 K. (Assume γ= 1.4 and Cp = 1005 J/kgK)",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1591 m/s",
            "b) 2041 m/s",
            "c) 991 m/s",
            "d) 781 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Thrust coefficient CF = T/PoA*.\nA* = πd2/4 = 78.53 cm2.\n∴ CF = 20,000/(500 x 1000 x 78.53 x 10-4)\n= 5.09."
    },
    {
        "id": 111,
        "Question": "What will happen when the thrust line doesn’t intersect the center of mass of a flying vehicle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The vehicle experiences a centripetal acceleration",
            "b) The vehicle drops in altitude",
            "c) The vehicle trajectory becomes zigzag",
            "d) The vehicle tries to rotate in flight"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When the thrust line doesn’t intersect the flying vehicle’s center of mass, turning moments are generated about the COM and it tends to rotate the vehicle in flight. Moment M = r x F, where F is the thrust force and r is the position vector measure from center of mass to any point on the force vector."
    },
    {
        "id": 112,
        "Question": "Which among the following is the most necessary for controlled turning and attitude control?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Turning moments",
            "b) High exhaust velocity",
            "c) Vortex generators",
            "d) Dorsal fins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: By varying the direction of the thrust line, turning moments can be generated. Controlling the turning moments will help in attaining the desired vehicle attitude."
    },
    {
        "id": 113,
        "Question": "What will not help in generating a turning moment in a flying vehicle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thrust vector deflection",
            "b) Aerodynamic fins",
            "c) Using separate engines for attitude control",
            "d) Altering the nozzle exit area by using nozzle extensions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Altering the nozzle exit area will not produce a thrust component not passing through the center of mass of the rocket. In that case, turning moment will not be generated."
    },
    {
        "id": 114,
        "Question": "In general, the rocket nozzle exits surface’s geometric axis is taken to be the __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) gimbal axis",
            "b) roll axis",
            "c) thrust axis",
            "d) lift axis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Both the thrust axis and the geometric axis of the rocket nozzle exit surface are taken to be the same. For the high-thrust booster system, even a small misalignment can lead to the rocket deviating from its path during the vehicle operation period."
    },
    {
        "id": 115,
        "Question": "Which of the following doesn’t belong to misalignment due to irregularities in nozzle geometry?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Out of round",
            "b) Unsymmetrical roughness",
            "c) Protuberances",
            "d) Nozzle extensions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Nozzle extensions are a means of improving the efficiency of rocket engines by increasing nozzle expansion ratio. It is not an irregularity in nozzle geometry. Protuberances refer to obstructions or protrusions from the nozzle wall. Out-of-round means having an unbalanced spherical or circular form or density."
    },
    {
        "id": 116,
        "Question": "Conventional axisymmetric conical nozzle with a cylindrical extension is called as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) cant nozzle",
            "b) bell-shaped nozzle",
            "c) scarfed nozzle",
            "d) aerospike nozzle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In surface mounting, the device is fixed to the outer surface while in flush mounting, the attached device won’t extend out of the outer surface. Cant angle is the angle between the longitudinal axis of the rocket motor grain and the nozzle center-line."
    },
    {
        "id": 117,
        "Question": "Motor axial specific impulse _____ with the scarf angle.",
        "Options": [
            "a) increases",
            "b) decreases",
            "c) increases and then decreases",
            "d) decreases and then increases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Scarfed nozzle is a passive way of thrust vector adjustment. Even though the flow Mach number of scarfed nozzles is lower compared to conical nozzles, it is more preferable because unwanted turning moments due to vehicle configuration can be avoided using it."
    },
    {
        "id": 118,
        "Question": "If the motor axial specific impulse of a given nozzle is 340s for propellant ‘A’ and its characteristic velocity is 1400 m/s, determine the specific impulse for the same nozzle using a propellant ‘B’ with a characteristic velocity of 980 m/s. Assume both propellants ‘A’ and ‘B’  have the same specific heat ratio.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 259 s",
            "b) 286 s",
            "c) 277 s",
            "d) 238 s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: With the increase in scarf angle, the motor axial specific impulse will decrease. This is because the component of exhaust velocity directed along the vehicle’s longitudinal axis decreases with the scarf angle increase."
    },
    {
        "id": 119,
        "Question": "Thrust is a weak function of ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) throat area",
            "b) chamber pressure",
            "c) mass flow rate",
            "d) thrust coefficient"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Thrust is a weak function of thrust coefficient CF. It is in turn dependent on specific heat ratio, pressure ratio, expansion ratio, and altitude."
    },
    {
        "id": 120,
        "Question": "A two-to-one thrust decrease can be achieved using _________ in a liquid propellant rocket engine.",
        "Options": [
            "a) throttle valves",
            "b) gas pressure feed system",
            "c) spark ignitor",
            "d) using BATES grain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Throttle valve helps in controlling the mass flow rate thereby reducing the thrust. It usually consists of a flow controlling unit and an electro-mechanical-actuator."
    },
    {
        "id": 121,
        "Question": "Attitude and maneuvering corrections require impulses with _________ pulse width.",
        "Options": [
            "a) extremely short",
            "b) extremely large",
            "c) moderately short",
            "d) moderately large"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Some methods of changing the area involves using a tapered plug or movable contoured pintle into the nozzle. Pintle has a pin or bolt shaped structure with a rod inside the nozzle and a tip outside of it."
    },
    {
        "id": 122,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a way for thrust modulation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Controlling the propellant flow rate to the injector",
            "b) Controlling injection orifices",
            "c) Varying chamber pressure",
            "d) Deploying control surfaces like fins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The engine might be operating at very high thrust levels. In order to bring changes to the vehicle orientation and for maneuvering purposes, time constraints might be tight and required impulses should be delivered with an extremely short pulse width."
    },
    {
        "id": 123,
        "Question": "Which of the following thrust modulation technique makes use of symmetric injection for jet area control?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Throat Shifting Thrust Modulation",
            "b) Shock Thrust Modulation",
            "c) Shock Vectoring Control",
            "d) Scarfed Nozzle Thrust Modulation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Thrust modulation can be achieved by varying mass flow rate or axial component of gas flow velocity or both. Deploying control surfaces may help in controlling the attitude of the vehicle in flight within the atmosphere, but it doesn’t help in varying thrust manually."
    },
    {
        "id": 124,
        "Question": "Which of the following thrust modulation techniques uses a normal shock to reduce total thrust?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Throat Shifting Thrust Modulation",
            "b) Scarfed Nozzle Thrust Modulation",
            "c) Shock Thrust Modulation",
            "d) Fluidic Thrust modulation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Usually solid propellant combustion gases are fuel rich and addition of oxygen into this control flow results in a secondary combustion. It increases both stagnation temperature and pressure of the flow. Because of pressure sensitivity on burning rate, higher stagnation pressure results in a higher mass flow rate, while the increase in stagnation temperature results in an increase in the characteristic velocity of the exit jet."
    },
    {
        "id": 125,
        "Question": "For a conical nozzle of throat diameter 0.007 m, exit cross-section diameter 0.02 m, and divergent section length of 0.038 m, determine the nozzle semi-divergence angle.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10.5°",
            "b) 12.6°",
            "c) 7.3°",
            "d) 9.7°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Throat Shifting Thrust Modulation (TSTM), by shifting the throat of the nozzle, thrust is controlled. For modulation of thrust, the jet area is controlled using symmetric injection near the throat."
    },
    {
        "id": 126,
        "Question": "Which of the following cannot be the nature of the actuation system for thrust vector control?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mechanical",
            "b) Fluidic",
            "c) Either mechanical or fluidic",
            "d) Neither mechanical and fluidic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Shock Thrust Modulation (STM) involves an axisymmetric injection of secondary flow into the diverging section of the supersonic nozzle and the creation of a normal shock by the interaction of oblique shocks. Across a normal shock, a supersonic flow becomes subsonic, thereby reducing exhaust velocity and total thrust. Fluidic Thrust Modulation is divided into STM and TSTM."
    },
    {
        "id": 127,
        "Question": "What is the nature of the trajectory of rockets in gravity-free, drag-free environment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Two-dimensional, curved path",
            "b) One dimensional, curved path",
            "c) Two-dimensional, straight line path",
            "d) One dimensional, straight line path"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: One dimensional, straight-line acceleration path is followed in such an environment as the only force acting on the rocket is its thrust and it acts in the flight direction. Under the influence of gravity, the flight path will become curved."
    },
    {
        "id": 128,
        "Question": "How will propellant mass flow and thrust change with burn duration in a gravity-free, drag-free environment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mass flow and thrust remains constant",
            "b) Mass flow increases, thrust decreases",
            "c) Mass flow decreases, thrust increases",
            "d) Mass flow decreases, thrust decreases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Both mass flow and thrust remain constant in such an environment. Then for a given burning time tb, total mass expelled from the rocket can be determined from mass flow rate m = m/tb equation."
    },
    {
        "id": 129,
        "Question": "Where do we account for residual propellant mass in a rocket engine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Propellant mass",
            "b) Inert mass",
            "c) Payload mass",
            "d) Structural mass"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: We account for residual propellant mass in inert mass section. Inert mass includes the masses of the engine system, like that of the nozzles, tanks, cases or unused, residual propellants. It doesn’t come under the useful propellant mass consumed for propulsion."
    },
    {
        "id": 130,
        "Question": "What is the nature of the effect of the propellant mass fraction on the vehicle velocity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Exponential",
            "b) Logarithmic",
            "c) Linear",
            "d) Parabolic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Propellant mass fraction has a logarithmic effect on the vehicle velocity.\nup = ∆u = -c ln(1-ζ)."
    },
    {
        "id": 131,
        "Question": "Keeping the system inert mass constant, which of the following changes will not result in flight velocity increment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Use of better propellants",
            "b) A more favorable nozzle area ratio",
            "c) Higher chamber pressure",
            "d) Better nozzle cooling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Because doing any of these except better nozzle cooling will result in better Isp. Velocity increment is directly proportional to Isp, so more Isp means more velocity increment."
    },
    {
        "id": 132,
        "Question": "For given average effective exhaust velocity(c), which of the following values of propellant mass fractions(ζ) gives maximum vehicle velocity (up)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.6",
            "b) 0.7",
            "c) 0.8",
            "d) 0.9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: 0.9 is the correct answer. Because of the relation up = ∆u = -c ln(1-ζ), we can see that higher ζ gives higher up."
    },
    {
        "id": 133,
        "Question": "What is the effect of increasing mass ratio (mo/mb, where mo is the initial mass and mb is the burnout mass) on Isp?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) No effect",
            "d) Increases only after a limit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Isp increases because of the relation up = c ln(mo/mb). Here c is the exhaust velocity of the vehicle and ln denotes natural logarithm."
    },
    {
        "id": 134,
        "Question": "Which of the following will decrease the effective propellant fraction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Higher system inert mass",
            "b) More favorable nozzle area ratio",
            "c) Higher chamber pressure",
            "d) Higher temperature at the inlet of the nozzle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is because the effective propellant fraction is the ratio of the mass of propellants to the initial mass of the system. If inert mass(mf) increases, then the total initial mass(mo) will also increase as mo = mp + mf."
    },
    {
        "id": 135,
        "Question": "Which of these is a reasonable value of the mass ratio (Initial mass/inert mass) for single-stage vehicles for gravitation free drag-free space flight?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100",
            "b) 1000",
            "c) 200",
            "d) 20"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Single-stage rocket vehicles can have mass ratio up to about 20. To minimize weights and lateral loads, spherical shape of the rocket is desirable, although it may not be the easiest to manufacture."
    },
    {
        "id": 136,
        "Question": "Which of these is a reasonable value of the mass ratio (Initial mass/inert mass) for multistage vehicles for gravitation free drag-free space flight?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100",
            "b) 1000",
            "c) 200",
            "d) 20"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Multistage vehicles can have mass ratios that exceed 200. In this case, the rocket is segmented into multiple segments in which each of the segment is a separate propulsive system."
    },
    {
        "id": 137,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an external force acting on a vehicle flying in the earth’s atmosphere?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thrust",
            "b) Aerodynamic forces",
            "c) Gravitational forces",
            "d) Forces due to thermal stress"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For a vehicle flying in the earth’s atmosphere, thrust, aerodynamic (lift and drag) and gravitational forces are the major external forces. Thermal stress inside an engine leads to internal forces only."
    },
    {
        "id": 138,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a reasonable factor of increase for effective exhaust velocity (c) as altitude is increased?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.5",
            "b) 2.1",
            "c) 3.2",
            "d) 4.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of c can increase by a small factor between 1.2 to 1.6 as altitude is increased. Rocket motors produce greater thrust at higher altitudes due to the lower atmospheric pressure."
    },
    {
        "id": 139,
        "Question": "If L denotes the lift and ∅ denotes flight path angle, then what is the aerodynamic force acting normal to the flight path?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lcos ∅",
            "b) Lsin ∅",
            "c) Lsec ∅",
            "d) L"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Lift (L) is the aerodynamic force acting normal to the flight path. Flight path angle is the angle between the local horizon (perpendicular to r) and the flight path."
    },
    {
        "id": 140,
        "Question": "In writing the expressions for CL and CD for missiles and rockets, what does area A denote?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sum of all the fin areas",
            "b) The total surface area of the missile/rocket including the fins",
            "c) Maximum cross-sectional area normal to the missile axis",
            "d) Minimum cross-sectional area normal to the missile axis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Area A denotes the maximum cross-sectional area perpendicular to the longitudinal axis of the missile. So for a cylindrical missile body having a radius r, A = πr2."
    },
    {
        "id": 141,
        "Question": "What is the angle of attack for a missile?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The angle between the local horizon and the missile axis",
            "b) The angle between the local horizon and the missile flight path",
            "c) The angle between the missile axis and its flight path",
            "d) The angle between the relative wind and the missile longitudinal axis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Angle of attack for a missile is the angle between its flight path and the missile axis. For the pitching movement of a cruise missile, a range of angle of attack of 15° to 24°  is found to be effective."
    },
    {
        "id": 142,
        "Question": "The lift and drag coefficients are not primarily a function of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) vehicle configuration",
            "b) flight Mach number",
            "c) angle of attack",
            "d) vehicle mass"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: lift and drag coefficients are primarily a function of vehicle configuration, flight Mach number, and angle of attack. CL depends on lift force and not vehicle mass."
    },
    {
        "id": 143,
        "Question": "What is the loss of velocity increment experienced by a rocket as a result of drag in the atmosphere?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5-10%",
            "b) 15-20%",
            "c) 25-30%",
            "d) 35-40%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For space launch vehicles and ballistic missiles, the drag loss is about 5 to 10% of the final vehicle velocity increment. It will be lesser for space vehicles than atmospheric vehicles like fighter aircraft because the time spent in the atmosphere is lesser for the space vehicles."
    },
    {
        "id": 144,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct expression for gravitational acceleration (g) at a height h, given go refers to gravitational acceleration on the earth’s surface and Ro refers to effective radius of earth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) g=go[Ro/(Ro+h)]2",
            "b) g=go[Ro/(Ro-h)]2",
            "c) g=go[(Ro+h)/2Ro]2",
            "d) g=go[(Ro-h)/2Ro]2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: g=go[Ro/(Ro+h)]2 is the required formula.\ngo = GM/Ro2\ng = GM/(Ro + h)2\n⇒ g/go = Ro/(Ro+h)2."
    },
    {
        "id": 145,
        "Question": "Dynamic pressure experienced by the rocket in the lower atmosphere is ______ compared to that experienced at higher altitudes.",
        "Options": [
            "a) more",
            "b) less",
            "c) equal",
            "d) any random value"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: At lower atmospheric altitudes, the dynamic pressure experienced will be low because of the lower velocity of the rocket even though the air density is high. Dynamic pressure Pdyn is proportional to ρV2."
    },
    {
        "id": 146,
        "Question": "Which of the following can be non-zero for an airborne vehicle moving in rectilinear equilibrium flight?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Control forces",
            "b) Lateral forces",
            "c) Moments",
            "d) Thrust"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Control forces, Lateral forces and moments are taken to be zero to ensure that the vehicle doesn’t turn or slip in flight. However, the vehicle may need thrust to propel forward."
    },
    {
        "id": 147,
        "Question": "What is the trajectory of an airborne vehicle in rectilinear equilibrium flight?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One-dimensional",
            "b) Two-dimensional",
            "c) Three-dimensional",
            "d) Four-dimensional"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The trajectory for such a vehicle is considered to be two-dimensional and contained within a plane. In real cases, the flight is much more complex and three-dimensional and requires computational usage for the trajectory analysis."
    },
    {
        "id": 148,
        "Question": "The angle at which the wings of the vehicle are inclined to the flight path is called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) angle of attack",
            "b) flight path angle",
            "c) pitch angle",
            "d) roll angle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The vehicle wings are at some angle with the flight path. This angle is called the angle of attack. It plays a significant role in determining the lift generated under atmospheric conditions in the vehicle."
    },
    {
        "id": 149,
        "Question": "Lift is generated __________ to the flight path for an airborne vehicle in rectilinear equilibrium flight.",
        "Options": [
            "a) parallel",
            "b) perpendicular",
            "c) at an acute angle",
            "d) at an obtuse angle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Lift generation is normal to the direction of the flight path for such a vehicle. Lift is normal to the relative wind, while drag acts parallel to it and in the opposite direction."
    },
    {
        "id": 150,
        "Question": "In the direction of the flight path, the product of mass and acceleration of the vehicle is not the sum of which of the following forces?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Propulsive",
            "b) Aerodynamic",
            "c) Gravitational",
            "d) Electromagnetic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Propulsive, aerodynamic and gravitational forces are the major forces that contribute to the flight of an airborne vehicle. Propulsive forces include the thrust produced by the vehicle’s engine, while the aerodynamic forces include lift and drag forces."
    },
    {
        "id": 151,
        "Question": "Which of the following is acceleration perpendicular to the flight path?",
        "Options": [
            "a) udθ/dt",
            "b) θdu/dt",
            "c) d(uθ)/dt",
            "d) d(u/θ)/dt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: udθ/dt is the correct representation of the acceleration perpendicular to the flight path. du/dt is the acceleration in the direction of the flight path. It has a contribution from the lift, propulsive forces, and the gravitational forces."
    },
    {
        "id": 152,
        "Question": "Determine the acceleration perpendicular to flight path for constant value of flight speed u = 100 m/s and instantaneous radius R = 200 m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 m/s2",
            "b) 50 m/s2",
            "c) 200 m/s2",
            "d) 125 m/s2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Required acceleration perpendicular to flight path is atan = u2/R.\natan = 1002/200 = 50 m/s2."
    },
    {
        "id": 153,
        "Question": "Determine the component of gravitational force in the direction of the flight path if the angle of the flight path with the horizontal is 30°, angle of direction of thrust with the horizontal is 20° and mass of the vehicle is 300 kg. Assume the acceleration due to gravity to be 9.8 m/s2.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2250 N",
            "b) 2980 N",
            "c) 1470 N",
            "d) 3343 N"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Required component of gravitational force = mgsinθ.\nFgrav comp = 300 x 9.8 x sin(30) = 1470 N."
    },
    {
        "id": 154,
        "Question": "For a propulsive force of 1500 N, determine the magnitude of its component in a direction normal to the flight velocity if the angle of flight path with the horizontal is 30° and the angle of direction of thrust with the horizontal is 10°. Assume g=9.8 m/s2.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 513 N",
            "b) 1026 N",
            "c) 279 N",
            "d) 813 N"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The required propulsive force component is Tprop = F x sin(ψ-θ), where F is the total propulsive force, ψ is the angle of direction of thrust with the horizontal and θ is the angle of the flight path with the horizontal.\nTprop = 1500 x sin(10-30) = 513 N in magnitude."
    },
    {
        "id": 155,
        "Question": "Vehicle’s final velocity increment can be increased by using a _________ propellant.",
        "Options": [
            "a) more energetic",
            "b) less energetic",
            "c) highly unstable",
            "d) highly stable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Using a more energetic propellant increases the specific impulse of the vehicle. Higher specific impulse results in higher final velocity increment."
    },
    {
        "id": 156,
        "Question": "The mass ratio has a/an ____________ effect on the final velocity increment of a rocket vehicle.",
        "Options": [
            "a) logarithmic",
            "b) exponential",
            "c) linear",
            "d) parabolic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: R = m0/mf is the mass ratio, where m0 is the initial mass and mf is the burnout mass.\n&#8710u; is proportional to c ln(R) where c is the exhaust velocity."
    },
    {
        "id": 157,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a way of reducing final mass mf of a rocket?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Using a lesser portion of propellant for flight",
            "b) Using lighter structures",
            "c) Having smaller payloads",
            "d) Using lighter guidance/ control devices"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If a lesser portion of propellant is used for the flight of the vehicle, then the residual propellant mass will be more. This means that the final mass mf will be more than usual."
    },
    {
        "id": 158,
        "Question": "Which of the following is minimum for increasing the initial mass of the rocket?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increasing the thrust",
            "b) Adding more propellant",
            "c) Increase in structure",
            "d) Increase in specific impulse"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The increase in structure or propulsion system masses is kept minimum for increasing the initial mass of the rocket. The effective mass ratio will be more if the structural mass is not kept minimum."
    },
    {
        "id": 159,
        "Question": "The form drag depends on ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) aeroelastic stresses",
            "b) solid structures far downstream",
            "c) solid structures far upstream",
            "d) aerodynamic shape of the body"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Reducing the burning time will only reduce the gravitational losses. Keeping the flight path normal to the local horizon will also help in reducing gravitational losses"
    },
    {
        "id": 160,
        "Question": "The rocket frontal area can be reduced by choosing a propellant with __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) higher propellant density",
            "b) lower propellant density",
            "c) higher propellant flammability",
            "d) lower propellant flammability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Form drag depends on the aerodynamic shape of the body in the flow field. A streamlined body like a slender body with a pointed nose has lesser drag compared to a blunt object."
    },
    {
        "id": 161,
        "Question": "Which drag is specifically caused by the friction of air flowing over the vehicle’s outer surface?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Form drag",
            "b) Skin drag",
            "c) Shock drag",
            "d) Base drag"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Higher propellant density will allow lesser tank volume for the storage of the same mass of the propellant. Hence the frontal area requirement will be less. Flammability has no role in controlling rocket frontal area."
    },
    {
        "id": 162,
        "Question": "A shorter rocket length will help in _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) more vehicle structural mass",
            "b) lighter vehicle structure",
            "c) greater vehicle mass ratio",
            "d) greater complexity of the vehicle design"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Skin friction drag is the drag caused by the friction of flowing air over the vehicle outer surface. A polished and smooth outer surface will help in its reduction."
    },
    {
        "id": 163,
        "Question": "If flight velocity is u and the vehicle exhaust velocity is c, when is the propulsive efficiency maximum?",
        "Options": [
            "a) u ≅ c",
            "b) u ≫ c",
            "c) u ≪ c",
            "d) c → ∞"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A shorter rocket length means that the overall vehicle’s structural mass will be lesser. This is because of the reduction in the amount of material required in the construction of the vehicle. It will also mean more mass ratio compared to longer rockets because of lesser inert mass in shorter vehicles."
    },
    {
        "id": 164,
        "Question": "Determine the velocity of a satellite in a circular orbit around the earth at a height of 112 km.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3219.28 m/s",
            "b) 2472.76 m/s",
            "c) 1591.98 m/s",
            "d) 7834.95 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Satellite velocity us can be obtained from mus2 = mg. Here g = gox(Ro/Ro+h)2\n⇒ us = Ro√(go/Ro+h)\n⇒ us = 6374 x 103 x √(9.8/6486000) = 7834.95 m/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 165,
        "Question": "Determine the time period of revolution of a satellite in a circular orbit around a planet of radius 6374 m at a height of 600 m. Assume the acceleration due to gravity at sea level to be 9.8 m/s2.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30 mins",
            "b) 25 mins",
            "c) 35 mins",
            "d) 40 mins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Time period τ = 2π(Ro+h)/us = 2π(Ro+h)3/2/(Ro/√go)\n⇒ τ = 2 x 3.14 x 69743/2/(6374/√9.8) = 1797.2 s or ∼ 30 mins."
    },
    {
        "id": 166,
        "Question": "Determine the energy necessary to bring a unit mass into a circular orbit around the earth having a height of 170 km. Neglect the effects of drag.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25 MJ",
            "b) 16 MJ",
            "c) 32 MJ",
            "d) 19 MJ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The required energy E = 1/2 Rogo x (Ro + 2h)/(Ro + h)\n⇒ E = 0.5 x 6374 x 103 x 9.8 x (6714/6544) ≅ 32 MJ."
    },
    {
        "id": 167,
        "Question": "What is the typical altitude of LEO?",
        "Options": [
            "a) more than 500 km",
            "b) Less than 800 km",
            "c) Less than 500 km",
            "d) More than 800 km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: LEO stands for Low Earth Orbits. They are typically less than 500 km in altitude."
    },
    {
        "id": 168,
        "Question": "Why are the orbits of satellites outside of the earth’s atmosphere?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The orbit needs to be elliptical",
            "b) The orbit needs to be circular",
            "c) Within the atmosphere, the satellite spirals down to the earth",
            "d) Drag losses are absent outside the atmosphere"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Outside the atmosphere, due to the absence of air, aerodynamic effects like lift and drag are non-existent. Within the atmosphere, additional energy is required to make up for the drag losses."
    },
    {
        "id": 169,
        "Question": "For a circular trajectory of a satellite around the earth, the centrifugal forces must balance the ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) propulsive forces",
            "b) gravitational forces",
            "c) lift forces",
            "d) drag forces"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The centrifugal forces should be equal to the gravitational forces for a satellite revolving around the earth in a circular orbit. If m denotes the satellite mass, us denotes the satellite velocity, and R represents the radius of the orbit, then mus2/R = mg."
    },
    {
        "id": 170,
        "Question": "Find the altitude of a satellite in a circular orbit around earth with a velocity of 7000 m/s.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1751.6 km",
            "b) 2134.3 km",
            "c) 9053.1 km",
            "d) 899.5 km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: From the relation us = Ro√(go/Ro+h), using us = 7000 m/s, Ro = 6374 x 103 m, we have\nh = [go/us2/Ro2] – Ro\nh = 1751.6 km."
    },
    {
        "id": 171,
        "Question": "At an instant of time, a satellite in an elliptical orbit is at a distance of 500 km from the surface of the earth. If the semi major axis of the orbit is 8500 km in length, determine the magnitude of the satellite velocity. Take μ = 3.986 x 1014 m3/sec2.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8118.33 m/s",
            "b) 8813.38 m/s",
            "c) 8311.38 m/s",
            "d) 8181.38 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: u = [μ(2/R – 1/a)]1/2\nu = [3.986 x 1014 x(2/6874000 – 1/8500000)]1/2\n= 8311.38 m/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 172,
        "Question": "Satellite velocity is maximum at __________ for an elliptical orbit.",
        "Options": [
            "a) apogee",
            "b) perigee",
            "c) focal point",
            "d) infinity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The point on the elliptical orbit closest to the focal point (where the planet is situated) is the perigee. At perigee, the satellite will have its maximum velocity and at apogee it will have its minimum velocity. It is evident from the principles of angular momentum conservation."
    },
    {
        "id": 173,
        "Question": "For an eccentricity of 0.92 and semi major axis length of 9500 km, determine the apogee velocity for a satellite in elliptical orbit. Take μ = 3.986 x 1014 m3/sec2.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1349.54 m/s",
            "b) 1439.45 m/s",
            "c) 1233.33 m/s",
            "d) 1322.21 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Apogee velocity ua = √(μ(1-e)/a(1+e))\nua = √(3.986 x 1014 x (0.08/1.92)/(9500 x 103)) = 1322.21 m/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 174,
        "Question": "Rocket propulsion thrust vector passes through the ___________ of the vehicle.",
        "Options": [
            "a) center of gravity",
            "b) center of pressure",
            "c) neutral point",
            "d) maneuvering point"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The thrust vector passes through the center of gravity for a rocket propulsion system. Because of that, no residual moments will be generated about the center of gravity."
    },
    {
        "id": 175,
        "Question": "An example for an unpowered maneuvering is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) coasting",
            "b) translational maneuver",
            "c) cruising",
            "d) freefall"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Coasting is an example for an unpowered maneuver. Cruising involves maintaining a steady level horizontal flight at a constant altitude. Several powered and unpowered segments of the flight trajectory can be grouped together under translational maneuvers."
    },
    {
        "id": 176,
        "Question": "What is the thrust required for a truly rotational maneuver?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Infinite",
            "b) Zero",
            "c) In the order of mega-Newtons",
            "d) In the order of milli-Newtons"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: No thrust is required for a truly rotational maneuver. Only torque is generated in this case using couples."
    },
    {
        "id": 177,
        "Question": "What kind of maneuvers are typically provided by the reaction control systems?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Misaligned thrust maneuvers",
            "b) Translational maneuvers",
            "c) Truly rotational maneuvers",
            "d) Circular maneuvers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Reaction control systems typically help in rotational maneuvers. It requires a set of 4 thrusters for to rotate the vehicle about any one axis in either of the two directions."
    },
    {
        "id": 178,
        "Question": "Which of the following processes requires accurately predetermined impulses for a rocket engine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Launching",
            "b) Re-entry",
            "c) Orbit Injection",
            "d) Coasting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Orbital injection or transferring the rocket vehicle from one orbit to another requires a predetermined, accurate amount of specific impulse. Here the thrust levels are lower in comparison to the launch stage."
    },
    {
        "id": 179,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a property of inflight correction maneuver?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low thrust",
            "b) Pulsing",
            "c) Long duration",
            "d) Uses reaction control systems"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The thrust in this case needs to be applied in the same direction as the flight velocity vector. If the new orbit is lower, then the thrust direction is opposite to the flight velocity vector. Transfer orbits are typically achieved using an electric propulsion system if the flight duration is supposed to be longer."
    },
    {
        "id": 180,
        "Question": "Station keeping maneuvers are ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) orbit maintenance maneuvers",
            "b) velocity adjustment maneuvers",
            "c) first stage propulsion control",
            "d) orbit transfer maneuvers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Inflight correction maneuvers are typically short duration maneuvers. They are intermittent (pulsing) operations performed with low thrust."
    },
    {
        "id": 181,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the most effective way of slowing a rocket during reentry and landing maneuver into the moon?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The atmospheric drag",
            "b) Deploying landing parachutes",
            "c) Reverse thrust",
            "d) Deploying heat shields"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Station keeping maneuvers are orbit maintenance maneuvers. It keeps the spacecraft in its intended orbit and orbital position."
    },
    {
        "id": 182,
        "Question": "Which of the following terms doesn’t relate to docking?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lock-on",
            "b) Rendezvous maneuver",
            "c) Spacecrafts",
            "d) Heat shield"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In those locations where there is little to no atmosphere (like moon or Mercury), drag is not a reliable factor for slowing down the rocket. Reverse thrust is usually employed in such cases for the same purpose during the descent and the touchdown."
    },
    {
        "id": 183,
        "Question": "Depending on the mission profile, the most economical number of steps / expended stages for a multistage rocket is between _____ and ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2, 10",
            "b) 4, 9",
            "c) 2, 6",
            "d) 4, 7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Generally, the number of stages for a multistage rocket is between two and six stages. Using more than one stage permits higher vehicle velocities, higher payload fractions and better performance of long ranged ballistic missiles. But having too many stages will limit the initial take-off mass and the mechanisms and machinery involved become too complex."
    },
    {
        "id": 184,
        "Question": "If the velocity increments of the first, second, and third stages are 1000 m/s, 500 m/s and 250 m/s respectively, determine the total velocity increment.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2750 m/s",
            "b) 1375 m/s",
            "c) 1750 m/s",
            "d) 3500 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For an n-staged vehicle, the total velocity increment is the sum of the velocity increments of all the stages. So the final velocity increment is δuf = δu1 + δu2 + δu3 + …… ."
    },
    {
        "id": 185,
        "Question": "Determine the mass ratio (Initial mass/Burnout mass) for each stage for a 3-stage rocket, given the total velocity increment is 2000 m/s, mass ratio is constant for all stages and the exhaust velocity is constant for all stages with a value of 3000 m/s.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.51",
            "b) 1.52",
            "c) 2.15",
            "d) 1.25"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: δuf = c1ln(R1) + c2ln(R2) + c3ln(R3)\n= 3 c ln (R), since c1 = c2 = c3 = c and R1 = R2 = R3 = R\n⇒ R = exp (δuf/3c)\n= exp(2000 / 9000) = 1.25."
    },
    {
        "id": 186,
        "Question": "Strap-on booster stages are an example of ______ staging.",
        "Options": [
            "a) parallel",
            "b) tandem",
            "c) partial",
            "d) piggyback"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When two or more booster stages are attached to the lower stage of the vertical configuration of a rocket vehicle, such a configuration is called as parallel staging. In this case, the booster stages are “strapped” on to the lower stage and this allows an increase in the vehicle performance."
    },
    {
        "id": 187,
        "Question": "If the theoretical payload increases by the use of a third stage for an initially two stage rockets is 8-10%, which of the following values is a logical value for theoretical payload increase for the use of an additional fourth stage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) -4 to -6%",
            "b) 3 to 5%",
            "c) 8 to 10%",
            "d) 12 to 14%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An increase in the number of stages will help in the increase payload mass the vehicle can carry. But with the increase in the number of stages, the amount of additional payload mass the vehicle can carry will decrease. So, if 8-10% additional payload mass can be carried by the rocket using a third stage, then a fourth stage will have a payload increase of only about 3 to 5%."
    },
    {
        "id": 188,
        "Question": "Usually, the thrusts required by a rocket system __________ from upper to lower stages.",
        "Options": [
            "a) increases",
            "b) decreases",
            "c) first increases and then decreases",
            "d) first decreases and then increases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The initial stage of the rocket is usually the stage that requires the largest thrust and largest total impulse. The lower stage is often called as the booster stage. The thrust required becomes smaller for the upper stages or the sustainer stages."
    },
    {
        "id": 189,
        "Question": "Which of the following terms are not related to a strap-on stage of a rocket engine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Booster stage",
            "b) Half stage",
            "c) Zero stage",
            "d) Sustainer stage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The upper stages are usually called as the sustainer stages. Booster stages usually include the strap-on motors which after their use drop off from the attached lower stage. They are also called as half or zero stages. Typically, there are 2 to 6 strap-on motors used in a rocket engine."
    },
    {
        "id": 190,
        "Question": "Which of the following operations does the small reaction control thrusters in Space Shuttle doesn’t serve?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Attitude control",
            "b) Small trajectory corrections",
            "c) Docking",
            "d) Take-off"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Same engines can be used for different purposes. An example for one such engine is the small reaction control thruster for the Space Shuttle which serves the main purpose of attitude control, but in addition to it plays a role in docking and small trajectory corrections as well. It is however not used for take-off as it is a low thrust, high specific impulse delivering device."
    },
    {
        "id": 191,
        "Question": "__________ is that part of a launch vehicle that carries the payload.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spacecraft",
            "b) Booster stage",
            "c) Sustainer stage",
            "d) Control and guidance system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Of the total launch vehicle, the only part that goes into the orbit or deep space is the spacecraft. It is that part which carries the payload. Some of the spacecraft are designed to return back to the earth."
    },
    {
        "id": 192,
        "Question": "In which of these following altitudes does a rocket exhibit narrow pencil shaped exhaust plume?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low altitude",
            "b) Above atmosphere",
            "c) Outer space",
            "d) During launch"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In general, rocket exhaust plumes are pencil shaped when they are at low altitudes. This is because the exhaust gases are restricted from expanding against ambient air pressure."
    },
    {
        "id": 193,
        "Question": "What are the primary sources of radiation in a chemical rocket engine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Excitation of molecules in the combustion chamber",
            "b) De-excitation of internal modes of gas molecules",
            "c) Rapid combustion of injector fuel",
            "d) Shock layer at the nozzle exit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The molecules are excited in the combustion chamber. But these excited molecules de-excite in their internal modes causing radiation to be emitted."
    },
    {
        "id": 194,
        "Question": "Determine the chamber pressure for a rocket engine if the thrust coefficient is 1.8, the throat area is 0.2 m2 and the total thrust is 20000 N.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 61.33 kPa",
            "b) 67.98 kPa",
            "c) 45.67 kPa",
            "d) 55.56 kPa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Thrust force F = Pc At Cf, where Pc is the chamber pressure, At is the throat area and Cf is the thrust coefficient.\nThen, Pc = F/(At Cf) = 20000/(0.2×1.8) = 55.56 kPa."
    },
    {
        "id": 195,
        "Question": "Determine the mass ratio (Burnout mass/ Initial mass) of a vehicle in a gravitation less space if its velocity is boosted from 800 m/s to 1600 m/s and the effective rocket exhaust velocity is 2000 m/s.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.85",
            "b) 0.33",
            "c) 0.67",
            "d) 0.25"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: δu = ueq ln (Mo/Mb)\nwhere δu = uf – ui = 1600 – 800 = 800 m/s.\nThen Mb/Mo = 1/exp(800/2000) = 0.67."
    },
    {
        "id": 196,
        "Question": "Which of the following correspond to the spectral bands of CO2 and H2O respectively in the IR signature of rocket exhaust plumes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.7μm and 4.3μm",
            "b) 7.2 μm and 3.4μm",
            "c) 4.3 μm and 2.7 μm",
            "d) 3.4 μm and 7.2μm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  Spectral band of H2O is in the 2.7 μm region, while for CO2, it is 4.3 μm. In missile launches, these are the two principal bands observed in the atmospheric absorption."
    },
    {
        "id": 197,
        "Question": "If A is the pre-exponential factor, n is the temperature exponent, Ea is the activation energy, then the expression for forward rate constant according to Arrhenius law is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) kf = ATn exp(-Ea/RT)",
            "b) kf = T exp(-EaA/RTn)",
            "c) kf = ATn exp(-Ea/RTn)",
            "d) kf = AT exp(-Ea/nRT)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Exhaust plumes with strong emission signatures easily detectable. Afterburning will enhance such an emission. For stealth aircraft, this isn’t an ideal mode of operation, unless the emission signature can be well suppressed."
    },
    {
        "id": 198,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the mixing layer of a nozzle core flow?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inviscid inner core flow",
            "b) Viscous outer core flow",
            "c) Inviscid outer core flow",
            "d) Viscous inner core flow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The expression for the forward reaction is given by kf = ATn exp(-Ea/RT). This is given by the Arrhenius law, which plays an important role in the calculation of the rate of chemical reactions and activation energy."
    },
    {
        "id": 199,
        "Question": "At which of the following altitudes does the infrared emissions from the mixing zone of the rocket exhaust higher?",
        "Options": [
            "a) near sea level",
            "b) Stratospheric region",
            "c) Just outside the atmosphere",
            "d) Outer space"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Nozzle core flow can be divided into inviscid inner core flow and viscous outer core flow. The viscous outer core flow is also called the mixing layer. No chemical reactions are assumed to take place in the nozzle inner core flow."
    },
    {
        "id": 200,
        "Question": "Stability of a flying vehicle cannot be ensured by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) control surfaces",
            "b) reaction control system",
            "c) anti-sloshing setup",
            "d) hinged multiple rocket nozzles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Sloshing of liquid propellants in the tank can be prevented by anti-sloshing setup. But when the vehicle moves into an unstable state, it cannot control the vehicle and help it return back to the stable regime."
    },
    {
        "id": 201,
        "Question": "Suppose an aircraft trimmed at a 10° angle of attack faces a gust that changes the angle of attack to 15°. What is the nature of the moment required to bring it back to the trimmed condition?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Positive pitching moment",
            "b) Positive yawing moment",
            "c) Negative pitching moment",
            "d) Negative yawing moment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Negative pitching moment is a nose-down pitching moment which will act as the restoring moment in this situation. Yawing moment happens about the vehicle’s z-axis."
    },
    {
        "id": 202,
        "Question": "Which of the following statements is true for the center of gravity (cog) and the center of pressure (cop) location along the axis of a fuel powered aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) cog and cop both changes",
            "b) cog remains fixed but cop changes",
            "c) cog and cop both remain fixed",
            "d) cog changes but cop remains fixed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Center of gravity changes due to fuel consumption of the aircraft. Since aerodynamics moments vary with Mach number, center of pressure location is also not fixed."
    },
    {
        "id": 203,
        "Question": "Which of the following can be spin-stabilized?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Unguided rocket projectiles",
            "b) Commercial aircrafts",
            "c) Artificial satellites",
            "d) Bullet trains"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Unguided rocket projectiles can be given a rotation about its longitudinal axis by means of inclined fins or smaller rocket nozzles to stabilize it. This is an example of spin stabilization."
    },
    {
        "id": 204,
        "Question": "Determine the period of revolution of an artificial satellite in a circular orbit of altitude 350 km.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.738 hrs",
            "b) 1.266 hrs",
            "c) 1.395 hrs",
            "d) 1.525 hrs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: T=2π(R0+h)3/2/√μ\n= 2×3.14x(6728000)3/2/(3.986×1014)\n= 1.525 hrs."
    },
    {
        "id": 205,
        "Question": "For a satellite revolving around the earth in a circular orbit at an altitude of 350 km, determine the orbital velocity.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7691.3 m/s",
            "b) 7606.9 m/s",
            "c) 7532.3 m/s",
            "d) 7797.2 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: V = \\(\\sqrt{(\\mu/R)}\\), where R = Ro + h.\nV = \\(\\sqrt{(3.98 * 10^{14}/6728000)}\\) \n= 7691.3 m/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 206,
        "Question": "For an airplane undergoing a steady pull-up maneuver along a curved flight path of the constant angle of attack, constant pitch rate of 20°/s, and having a radius of curvature of 150 m, determine the flight velocity.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 47.66 m/s",
            "b) 52.36 m/s",
            "c) 38.33 m/s",
            "d) 69.42 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In some cases, a low-speed roll is applied on the rocket to minimize or cancel out the thrust vector deviations due to aerodynamic shape misalignment or due to some other reason. This roll is different from the roll used for spin stability."
    },
    {
        "id": 207,
        "Question": "The point on the rocket where all the aerodynamic forces balance is called as the ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) center of pressure",
            "b) neutral point",
            "c) maneuvering point",
            "d) center of gravity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pitch rate q = V/R\nThen, V = qR = 20 x π/180 x 150 = 52.36 m/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 208,
        "Question": "Determine the normal force coefficient of a rocket having a maximum frontal area of 0.2 m2, flying at sea level with a velocity of 100 m/s. Consider the center of gravity to be ahead of the center of pressure by 0.5 m and the corrective moment coefficient to be 2.5.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.016",
            "b) 0.012",
            "c) 0.008",
            "d) 0.004"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Center of pressure is the point where all the aerodynamic forces balance. Lift and drag are the two aerodynamic forces acting on the rocket."
    },
    {
        "id": 209,
        "Question": "Consider a mixture of three gases a, b and c at equilibrium. If the individual gas components have pressures equal to Pa, Pb and Pc, determine the total pressure P of the mixture of gases.",
        "Options": [
            "a) P = Pa + Pb + Pc",
            "b) P = Pa x Pb x Pc /(Pa + Pb + Pc)",
            "c) P = [(Pa x Pb) + (Pb x Pc) + (Pc x Pa)] / (Pa + Pb + Pc)",
            "d) P = (Pa x Pb / Pc) + (Pb x Pc / Pa) + (Pc x Pa / Pb)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dalton’s law of partial pressures states that the total pressure exerted by a mixture of gases is the sum of partial pressures of individual gas components. Hence the answer is P = Pa + Pb + Pc."
    },
    {
        "id": 210,
        "Question": "Perfect gas equation applies very closely to ________ gases.",
        "Options": [
            "a) low temperature, low pressure",
            "b) high temperature, high pressure",
            "c) high temperature, low pressure",
            "d) low temperature, high pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Perfect gas equations are valid for high temperature and low-pressure gases. In such a case, the inter-molecular forces are negligibly small. PV=RT is the perfect gas equation, with V as the specific volume, P as the pressure, T as the temperature and R as the gas constant for the mixture of gases."
    },
    {
        "id": 211,
        "Question": "Consider two sets of mixture of gases A and B having the same specific volume of the mixture and having total pressures PA and PB respectively. If TA = 3TB and molecular mass of A MA = 1/2 MB, determine the ratio of PA/PB.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.75",
            "b) 12",
            "c) 1.5",
            "d) 6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Assume that the gases follow the perfect gas equation. P = R’T/MVmix where Vmix is the specific volume of the mixture and R’ is the universal gas constant.\nSo PA/PB = (TA/TB) x (MB/MA)\n= 3 x 2 = 6."
    },
    {
        "id": 212,
        "Question": "Consider two sets of mixture of gases X and Y having the same total temperature of the mixture and having total pressures PX and PY respectively. If PX = 1.4 PY and molecular mass of A MX = 2.3 x MY, determine the ratio of Vmix_X/Vmix_Y.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.26",
            "b) 0.52",
            "c) 0.62",
            "d) 0.31"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Assuming the mixture of gases to be ideal, we have P = R’T/MVmix where Vmix is the specific volume of the mixture and R’ is the universal gas constant.\nPX/PY = (TX/TY) x (MYVmix_Y/MXVmix_X)\nVmix_X/Vmix_Y = (MY/MX) x (TX/TY) x (PY/PX)\n= (1/2.3) x 1 x (1/1.4) = 0.31."
    },
    {
        "id": 213,
        "Question": "In a gaseous mixture, the number of moles and the molecular mass (in their respective units) of each component is given as follows: nA = 1, MA = 23; nB = 2, MB = 48; nC = 3, MC = 19. Find the average molecular mass of the mixture.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 28.67",
            "b) 29.33",
            "c) 31.25",
            "d) 25.47"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Mavg = (nAMA + nBMB + nCMC) / (nA + nB + nC)\n= (23 + 96 + 57) / 6 = 29.33."
    },
    {
        "id": 214,
        "Question": "What is the number of condensed species in a gaseous mixture, if there are 8 possible species which enter into a relationship and out of these, only 5 are gases?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 9",
            "d) 6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If there are n species that enter into a relationship and if there are only m species out of these, then the total number of condensed species is n-m."
    },
    {
        "id": 215,
        "Question": "Determine the stoichiometric mixture mass ratio for the complete reaction: H2 + 1/2 O2 → H2O.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2:1",
            "b) 16:1",
            "c) 4:1",
            "d) 8:1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: On mass basis, stoichiometric mixture requires half of 32 kg of O2 with 2 kg of H2. So the mixture mass ratio would be 1/2 x 32 / 2 = 8."
    },
    {
        "id": 216,
        "Question": "Rocket propulsion usually operates in ___________ mixture ratio.",
        "Options": [
            "a) fuel rich",
            "b) oxidizer rich",
            "c) stoichiometric",
            "d) any"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rocket propulsion systems typically operate in fuel rich mixture ratio. This allows a portion of lightweight molecules such as hydrogen to be unreacted and contributes to the decrease in the average molecular mass of the combustion products."
    },
    {
        "id": 217,
        "Question": "The decomposition of solid propellants to reaction mixture is a(n) ______________ chemical reaction.",
        "Options": [
            "a) reversible",
            "b) irreversible",
            "c) stoichiometric",
            "d) ideal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The whole process of combustion of solid propellants to derive a reaction mixture is an irreversible chemical reaction. It means that the reverse process is not possible."
    },
    {
        "id": 218,
        "Question": "What is the energy released (or absorbed), or the enthalpy change when one mole of a chemical compound is formed from its constituent atoms or elements at one bar and isothermally at 25°C?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heat of formation",
            "b) Heat of reaction",
            "c) Gibbs free energy",
            "d) Latent heat of vaporization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is the definition of heat of formation. In this reaction, each of the reactants and products are in its thermodynamic standard state and at the reference pressure and temperature."
    },
    {
        "id": 219,
        "Question": "If the energy balance in the chemical reaction within the thrust chamber is thought of as a two-step process, what is the initial step in the process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Isothermal chemical reaction at the reference temperature",
            "b) Isentropic chemical reaction at the reference temperature",
            "c) Adiabatic chemical reaction at the reference temperature",
            "d) Heating of gases with the energy release from the chemical reaction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The heat generated during combustion of the propellants is the heat that is necessary to raise the resulting gases to their final temperature adiabatically. This follows from the conservation of energy."
    },
    {
        "id": 220,
        "Question": "Out of the following products of the reaction of hydrogen and oxygen, which of them is unstable?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydrogen",
            "b) Hydrogen peroxide",
            "c) Hydroxyl",
            "d) Water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The energy balance can be thought of as a two-step process. The first step involved in the isothermal chemical reaction of the propellants at the reference temperature. The second step involves the resultant gases having their temperature raised by the heat released from the previous chemical reaction."
    },
    {
        "id": 221,
        "Question": "Energy release efficiency is also called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) isentropic efficiency",
            "b) polytropic efficiency",
            "c) propulsive efficiency",
            "d) combustion efficiency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Theoretically, the reaction between hydrogen and oxygen can give rise to H2O2 and O3 too. But these are unstable materials and they do not readily exist at high temperatures."
    },
    {
        "id": 222,
        "Question": "Combustion efficiency in liquid propellant rocket engines __________ with an increase in combustion temperature.",
        "Options": [
            "a) increases",
            "b) decreases",
            "c) doesn’t change",
            "d) oscillates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Energy release efficiency is also called as combustion efficiency. It is the ratio of actual change in enthalpy of the unit propellant mixture to the theoretical change in enthalpy necessary to transform the propellants from the initial conditions to the products at the chamber pressure and temperature."
    },
    {
        "id": 223,
        "Question": "What is the approximate number of species or compounds present in the exhaust for a solid propellant rocket engine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10",
            "b) 50",
            "c) 100",
            "d) 200"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Combustion efficiency increases with increased combustion temperature. It is also depended on the method of injection and mixing."
    },
    {
        "id": 224,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for an ideal expansion in the nozzle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adiabatic, reversible expansion",
            "b) Drop in static temperature and pressure",
            "c) Drop in stagnation temperature and pressure",
            "d) Conversion of thermal to kinetic energy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Stagnation temperature remains constant for ideal expansion in the nozzle. Ideal expansion is isentropic and involves conversion of thermal to kinetic energy."
    },
    {
        "id": 225,
        "Question": "Which of the following effects are neglected for simple cases of nozzle expansion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heat exchange",
            "b) Frictional effects",
            "c) Divergence angle",
            "d) Reversibility"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For simple cases of nozzle expansion, the effects of friction, heat transfer, shock waves, non-equilibrium and divergence angle are neglected. But the process is considered to be reversible none the less."
    },
    {
        "id": 226,
        "Question": "What is the typical value of penalty incurred by assuming a frozen equilibrium rocket performance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1-4%",
            "b) 0%",
            "c) 12-15%",
            "d) 25-30%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The condensed phases are assumed to have zero volume. It implies that the droplets or particles are very small in size and have the same temperature as the gas at all the nozzle locations."
    },
    {
        "id": 227,
        "Question": "In which of the following cases is the chemical equilibrium maintained instantaneously, even though the gas composition varies through the nozzle due to temperature and pressure variations along the nozzle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frozen equilibrium",
            "b) Non-equilibrium",
            "c) Shifting equilibrium",
            "d) Isothermal equilibrium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: By assuming frozen equilibrium, we assume that the composition of the chemical products remains constant throughout the nozzle and is the same as that under the chamber conditions. In such a case, there are no phase changes or chemical reactions within the nozzle. The typical penalty on the rocket performance by assuming frozen equilibrium is about 1-4%."
    },
    {
        "id": 228,
        "Question": "In which of the following modes of analysis does the temperature, velocity or pressure at any normal cross-section of an axisymmetric nozzle remain to be the same?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One dimensional",
            "b) Two dimensional",
            "c) Three dimensional",
            "d) N-dimensional, where N can be 1,2,3,…"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In shifting equilibrium, even though there is an instantaneous chemical equilibrium between all molecular species, under the variation of pressure and temperature along the nozzle, the chemical composition varies. The gas composition at the chamber and at the exhaust in such a case would be different."
    },
    {
        "id": 229,
        "Question": "What is the average diameter of a solid particle in a nozzle flow above which there is a chance of occurrence of thermal lag?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 μm",
            "b) 10 μm",
            "c) 100 μm",
            "d) 1 μm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The simplest nozzle analysis is one-dimensional. In this case, for an axisymmetric nozzle, the flow properties across any normal cross-section will remain to be the same, or the flow properties are said to be uniform."
    },
    {
        "id": 230,
        "Options": [
            "a) I, II and III",
            "b) Only II and III",
            "c) Only I and III",
            "d) Only III"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the average diameter of the solid particles or the liquid droplets in a nozzle flow exceeds 0.1μm, it may lead to thermal and velocity lag. The thermal lag depends upon the convection and radiation means of losing energy and the velocity lag depends upon the drag experienced by the particles."
    },
    {
        "id": 231,
        "Question": "Dissociation of the reaction products __________ with the rise in the chamber temperature and _________ with the rise in chamber pressure of a chemical rocket engine.",
        "Options": [
            "a) increases, increases",
            "b) decreases, increases",
            "c) decreases, decreases",
            "d) increases, decreases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Higher chamber temperature results in higher dissociation of the reaction products. But the dissociation can be suppressed by an increase in the chamber pressure."
    },
    {
        "id": 232,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a highly refined form of kerosene used as rocket fuel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RP-1",
            "b) HMX",
            "c) RDX",
            "d) C-4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: RP-1 is a highly refined form of kerosene. It is short for Rocket Propellant-1 or Refined Petroleum-1. A part of RP-1 includes toxic and carcinogenic hydrazine."
    },
    {
        "id": 233,
        "Question": "Which of the following fuels were used in the first stage of Titan I?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RP-1",
            "b) RDX",
            "c) HMX",
            "d) LH2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: RP-1 fuel is used in the first stage of Titan 1. Other than that, it was also used in the first stages of Saturn V, Energeia, Saturn I and IB etc. It is a cheaper and less explosive alternative to LH2."
    },
    {
        "id": 234,
        "Question": "The fuel which releases the most energy per unit mass of combustion is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) LH2",
            "b) RP-1",
            "c) Kerosene",
            "d) Methane"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Compared to hydrocarbon fuels, liquid hydrogen delivers most energy per unit mass of combustion. Any hydrocarbon fuel, when subjected to combustion produces more pollution than LH2."
    },
    {
        "id": 235,
        "Question": "1-methyl-1, 2-dicyclopropyl cyclopropane is also called as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Syntin",
            "b) Kerosene",
            "c) RP-1",
            "d) Jet fuel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Syntin is a high-energy formulation briefly used in the upper stages of rockets developed by the Soviet Union. Its molecular formula is C10H16 and it is a mixture of 4 stereoisomers."
    },
    {
        "id": 236,
        "Question": "____________ is not a metallic additive in rocket propellants.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Beryllium",
            "b) Aluminum",
            "c) Nitroglycerine",
            "d) Boron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Nitroglycerine is a dense, colorless, explosive liquid. Its chemical formula is C3H5N3O9. It is neither metallic nor an additive."
    },
    {
        "id": 237,
        "Question": "Knocking in spark-ignition internal combustion engines is not the same as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) detonation",
            "b) pinging",
            "c) pinking",
            "d) pre-ignition"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Knocking and pre-ignition are two separate events. Knocking happens when the combustion of some of the air-fuel mixture doesn’t occur because of the propagation of flame front due to spark-plug ignition, but when one or more air-fuel mixture pockets explode outside the normal combustion front. Pre-ignition refers to the case in which combustion happens even before the spark-plug fires."
    },
    {
        "id": 238,
        "Question": "What kind of propulsion is used for trajectory adjustments and attitude corrections?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Boosting propulsion",
            "b) Auxiliary propulsion",
            "c) Sustaining propulsion",
            "d) Cryogenic propulsion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Auxiliary propulsion helps in trajectory adjustments and attitude corrections. Boosting propulsion imparts a high velocity to the payload. Boosting and auxiliary propulsion are one way of classifying liquid rocket engines."
    },
    {
        "id": 239,
        "Question": "How are liquid rocket engines classified on the basis of their feed system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pressurized or turbopump",
            "b) Restartable or single fired",
            "c) Single flight or reusable",
            "d) Boosting or auxiliary"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Feed system is used for the transfer of the liquid propellants from their storage tank to the thrust chamber of the rocket engine. They can be a gas-pressurized feed system or turbo pump feed system."
    },
    {
        "id": 240,
        "Question": "The thruster is also called as _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) combustion chamber",
            "b) thrust chamber",
            "c) nozzle",
            "d) injector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Thruster is the same as the thrust chamber of a rocket engine. It is the combination of the injector, combustion chamber and the nozzle."
    },
    {
        "id": 241,
        "Question": "Which of the following ways of thrust chamber cooling may use niobium metal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Film cooling",
            "b) Cooling jacket",
            "c) Radiation cooling",
            "d) Ablative cooling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Niobium is a special high temperature material that can radiate excess heat. So it is used as part of the radiation cooling of the thrust chamber."
    },
    {
        "id": 242,
        "Question": "At what temperature are the liquid oxygen and the liquid hydrogen kept in their storage tanks of the cryogenic rocket engine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) -253°C and -183°C",
            "b) -183°C and -253°C",
            "c) -253°C for both",
            "d) -183°C for both"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Liquid oxygen is stored at -183°C and liquid hydrogen is stored at -253°C. Extensive care is taken to ensure that the vaporization losses are minimized for the cryogenic propellants."
    },
    {
        "id": 243,
        "Question": "Determine the mixture ratio if mass flow rate of the oxidizer is 3/4 times the total mass flow rate of the combustion products.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.5",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Assuming the combustion gases are purely a result of the propellants and using mass conservation, mcomb = mo + mf.\nmo = 3/4 mcomb\nSo, mf = 1/4 mcomb\nMixture ratio r = mo / mf = 3."
    },
    {
        "id": 244,
        "Question": "If the total propellant flow rate is 24 kg/s and the mixture ratio is 2.3, determine the mass flow rate of the oxidizer.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 19.67 kg/s",
            "b) 15.33 kg/s",
            "c) 12.94 kg/s",
            "d) 16.73 kg/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: mo = r m/(r+1)\n= 2.3 x 24/(3.3) = 16.73 kg/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 245,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a part of a simple pressurized feed system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High pressure tank",
            "b) Gas starting valve",
            "c) Pressure regulator",
            "d) Ignitor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A simple pressurized feed system has feed lines, gas starting valve, pressure ignitor, high-pressure tank, propellant valves, and propellant tanks. Ignitors are not part of the feed system but are an important part of the thrust chamber."
    },
    {
        "id": 246,
        "Question": "_____ is used for separating liquids from the pressurizing gas.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Filters",
            "b) Elastic bladder",
            "c) Check valves",
            "d) Draining provisions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Filters retain contaminants from proceeding to the combustion chamber. Elastic bladder separates liquids from the pressurizing gas. Check valves are one-way valves that allow the flow to happen only in a single direction."
    },
    {
        "id": 247,
        "Question": "To enhance reliability on the feed system, the number of components/ subassemblies should be ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) higher",
            "b) lower",
            "c) non-existent",
            "d) more than 100"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Lower number of subassemblies will allow better reliability on the system. But it doesn’t mean that the system should be devoid of subassemblies as using them judiciously can achieve better results with ease."
    },
    {
        "id": 248,
        "Question": "When a section of the system has a leak or malfunction ____________ are used to shut it off.",
        "Options": [
            "a) isolation valves",
            "b) auxiliary power unit",
            "c) control valves",
            "d) filters"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Isolation valves help in shutting off the system if a leak or malfunction occurs within the system. Control valve varies the size of the passage and controls the flow. Filters does its job by retaining the contaminants from passing to the next level of the system."
    },
    {
        "id": 249,
        "Question": "____________ are used for preventing the propellant flow back into the tanks and avoiding inadvertent mixing of propellants in the flow passage.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Check valves",
            "b) Isolation valves",
            "c) Drainage valves",
            "d) Filters"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Check valves allow flow to pass only in one direction. Using them will prevent the flow from going back to the tank or inadvertent mixing."
    },
    {
        "id": 250,
        "Question": "For effective propellant utilization, the rate at which tank can expulse the propellants should be ____________ and the amount of residual propellants should be ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) high, Low",
            "b) low, High",
            "c) high, High",
            "d) low, Low"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Higher tank expulsion efficiency coupled with minimal residual propellants in the tank will enable effective propellant utilization for the rocket engine."
    },
    {
        "id": 251,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the function of an OMS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Deorbit",
            "b) Attitude control",
            "c) Rendezvous",
            "d) Orbit circularization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: OMS stands for Orbital Maneuver System. It provides thrust for orbital insertion, orbital transfer, orbital circularization, deorbit, abort and rendezvous. RCS (Reaction Control System) deals with attitude control."
    },
    {
        "id": 252,
        "Question": "Which of the following statements is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RCS operates only simultaneously with OMS",
            "b) RCS operates separately from OMS",
            "c) RCS can operate both simultaneously with and separate from OMS.",
            "d) Both RCS and OMS both cannot operate together when one of them is under operation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: RCS is the Reaction Control System while OMS is the Orbital Maneuvering System. RCS can alongside OMS as well as in separate mode. Both systems perform different operations for the same rocket engine and don’t depend on one another for its functionality."
    },
    {
        "id": 253,
        "Question": "Which of the following materials of the propellant tank requires a thin inner liner of metal to avoid leakage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Titanium",
            "b) Aluminum",
            "c) Stainless steel",
            "d) Fiber-reinforced plastics"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Fiber reinforced plastics can have tiny pores through which the propellant can escape easily. In order to prevent that, it is coated with a thin layer of some impervious metal."
    },
    {
        "id": 254,
        "Question": "What is ullage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The volume of propellant stored inside a tank neglecting its empty volume",
            "b) The extra volume of gas above the propellant in a tank",
            "c) The ratio of the volume of extra gas to that of the propellant after 50% of the propellant has been consumed",
            "d) The ratio of the volume of the propellant to that of the extra gas after 50% of the propellant has been consumed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Ullage is the extra volume of gas that lies above the propellant in a sealed tank. It is necessary for this extra volume to exist as it takes into account the thermal expansion of the propellant fluid."
    },
    {
        "id": 255,
        "Question": "Determine the amount of propellant trapped in pipe, fittings, and valve corners and lost by other means, if the initial mass of the propellant was M and it had an expulsion efficiency of 97%.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.97M",
            "b) 0.03M",
            "c) 0.06M",
            "d) 0.48M"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  Expulsion efficiency is the ratio of the amount of propellant available or expelled to the amount of propellant initially present in the tank.\nSo, 0.97 = mexpel/M\nThen mtrapped = M – Mexpel = 0.03M."
    },
    {
        "id": 256,
        "Question": "What happens to the vehicle mass ratio (Initial mass / Burnout mass) when the residual propellant is not available for combustion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decreases slightly",
            "b) Increases slightly",
            "c) Increases rapidly",
            "d) Decreases rapidly"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Residual propellant when not available for combustion is treated as inert mass. Since the inert mass increases, the burnout mass will also increase. The residual fuel amount is typically small. So the vehicle mass ratio (Initial mass / Burnout mass) will slightly decrease."
    },
    {
        "id": 257,
        "Question": "A good propellant tank must ensure that sloshing is ___________ and vortexing is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) minimized; maximized",
            "b) maximized; minimized",
            "c) maximized; maximized",
            "d) minimized; minimized"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Both sloshing and vortexing need to be minimized. This becomes significant when the tanks are near empty. Sloshing refers to the movement of a liquid inside another body. Vortexing is also similar to sloshing, but the movement is circular in nature."
    },
    {
        "id": 258,
        "Question": "When does the slosh-dynamics problem become useful?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When the liquid has a free surface",
            "b) When the liquid has no free surface",
            "c) When the liquid is non-Newtonian",
            "d) When the material stored inside the tank is thixotropic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The liquid stored inside the tank needs to have a free surface for slosh-dynamics to be applied. Propellant slosh in aircraft and rocket tanks are some examples of slosh dynamics problems."
    },
    {
        "id": 259,
        "Question": "Who is the innovative rocket designer who created Atlas ICBM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stewart Powell",
            "b) Karel Bossart",
            "c) John von Neumann",
            "d) Bernard A. Schriever"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Karel Bossart was the mind behind Atlas ICBM. It was first launched in June 1957. Atlas later was used for the first stage of satellite launch vehicles and served for about 5 decades."
    },
    {
        "id": 260,
        "Question": "Which component of the external tank of Space Shuttle served the main purpose of distributing thrust loads from SRBs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) LOX tank",
            "b) LH2 tank",
            "c) Intertank",
            "d) Contractor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In addition to the distribution of thrust loads from SRBs of the Space Shuttle, intertank also transferred the loads between other tanks. It is a structural connection between both the LOX and LH2 tanks. It also acts as a protective cover for accommodating some operational instruments."
    },
    {
        "id": 261,
        "Question": "Tank pressure for the pressure feed system is between ___________ and __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 psi; 2000 psi",
            "b) 200 psi; 1800 psi",
            "c) 300 psi; 2400 psi",
            "d) 800 psi; 3000 psi"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Tank pressure for the pressure feed system lies between 200 and 1800 psi. 1 psi is about 6894.76 Pa. For pump fed systems, the tank pressure lies between 10 and 50 psi."
    },
    {
        "id": 262,
        "Question": "Which of the following gases cannot be used for gas pressure feed systems?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Helium",
            "b) Nitrogen",
            "c) Argon",
            "d) Ozone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Inert gases are used in gas pressure feed systems. Ozone is not an inert gas. Hence it cannot be used in this case."
    },
    {
        "id": 263,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about the pressurizing gas?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It shouldn’t be soluble in the liquid propellant",
            "b) It shouldn’t condense in the presence of the liquid propellant",
            "c) It should be inert",
            "d) It should have at least 10% moisture content"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pump feed systems require a small positive pressure in the tanks to suppress pump cavitation. When it happens, it will lead to the formation of small vapor bubbles in the pump and subsequent collapse or implosion of it, damaging the pump."
    },
    {
        "id": 264,
        "Question": "Propellant tanks containing oxygen and nitrogen tetroxide can be pressurized using _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) helium and nitrogen respectively",
            "b) nitrogen and helium respectively",
            "c) helium alone",
            "d) nitrogen alone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The pressurizing gas should be dry and shouldn’t contain any moisture. Else the moisture might react with the propellant or might dilute it."
    },
    {
        "id": 265,
        "Question": "For pressurizing cryogenic propellant tanks, the amount of gas required is _________ compared to an equivalent tank containing a non-cryogenic propellant.",
        "Options": [
            "a) more",
            "b) less",
            "c) equal",
            "d) not related in any way"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Nitrogen will react with oxygen and nitrogen tetroxide and decrease the density and concentration of the oxidizer. In order to avoid that, helium is used instead of nitrogen for pressurizing the tanks containing oxygen or nitrogen tetroxide."
    },
    {
        "id": 266,
        "Question": "Which of the following pressurization techniques involves combustion inside the propellant tank?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chemical pressurization",
            "b) Gas fed pressurization",
            "c) This is not possible",
            "d) Dynamic pressurization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A larger mass of the gas will be required in the cryogenic case. This is because the gas will be warmer compared to the cryogenic propellant and it will cool down increasing its density."
    },
    {
        "id": 267,
        "Question": "Pressurizing gas cannot perform ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) operation of valves",
            "b) operation of controls",
            "c) admission of propellants into the tank",
            "d) expulsion of propellants away from the tank"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Chemical pressurization involves the injection of fuel or other suitable igniting material to cause combustion inside the propellant tank to produce gases to pressurize the tank. This is a small and light pressurization technique, but it doesn’t often produce reproducible tank pressures."
    },
    {
        "id": 268,
        "Question": "In turbopump feed systems, the pressurization of the propellants is done by ____________ and they are driven by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) turbines; pumps",
            "b) pumps; turbines",
            "c) pumps; pumps",
            "d) turbines; turbines"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pumps pressurize the propellants while they are driven by turbines. The turbines are run by propellants fed from the main propellant tank, separate propellant tank or by some other means."
    },
    {
        "id": 269,
        "Question": "In turbopump feed systems, the turbines derive their power from _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) expansion of hot gases",
            "b) expansion of cold gases",
            "c) compression of hot gases",
            "d) compression of cold gases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The power derived by the turbines come from the expansion of hot gases. This power is in turn used to run the turbopumps."
    },
    {
        "id": 270,
        "Question": "Closed cycles in turbopump feed systems are also called as  ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) open cycle",
            "b) engine cycle",
            "c) topping cycle",
            "d) bottoming cycle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Closed and open cycles are both engine cycles. Closed cycle is also called topping cycle. In this cycle, the working fluid from the turbine is injected into the combustion chamber so that the energy of this working fluid is also utilized in the engine cycle."
    },
    {
        "id": 271,
        "Question": "Which of the following cycles is used in RL10 hydrogen/oxygen rocket engine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Expander cycle",
            "b) Gas generator cycle",
            "c) Staged-combustion cycle",
            "d) Combustion tap-off cycle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Closed cycle tends to perform a little better than closed cycles. This is mainly because the exhaust gas from the turbine expands through the thrust chamber nozzle in its full pressure ratio. For open cycles, this expansion process happens across a smaller pressure ratio."
    },
    {
        "id": 272,
        "Question": "Which of the following engines uses a staged combustion cycle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vinci",
            "b) Pratt & Whitney RL10",
            "c) Ariane 6",
            "d) SpaceX Raptor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For gas generator cycles, the turbine inlet gas is obtained from a separate gas generator. The propellants used to generate the gas may be stored in separate tanks or it may be fed from the main propellant tank."
    },
    {
        "id": 273,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a characteristic of staged combustion cycle compared to other cycles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High fuel efficiency",
            "b) High engine specific impulse",
            "c) Engineering simplicity",
            "d) Use of preburners"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Expander cycle was used in RL-10 hydrogen/oxygen rocket engine. In this cycle, fuel used for cooling the thrust chamber is used as the working fluid in the turbine used to power the turbopumps. The exhaust from the turbine is fed to the combustion chamber and burned."
    },
    {
        "id": 274,
        "Question": "The oxidiser flow (mo) through the gas generator is ____________ if its flow rate through the pump is 10 kg/s and through the thrust chamber is 5 kg/s.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 kg/s",
            "b) 15 kg/s",
            "c) 20 kg/s",
            "d) 25 kg/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: mo = (mo)gg + (mo)c\nSo, (mo)gg = 10 – 5 = 5 kg/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 275,
        "Question": "The fuel flow (mf) through the gas generator is ____________ if its flow rate through the pump is 18 kg/s and through the thrust chamber is 10 kg/s.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 18 kg/s",
            "b) 10 kg/s",
            "c) 8 kg/s",
            "d) 28 kg/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: mf = (mf)gg + (mf)c\nSo, (mf)gg = 18 – 10 = 8 kg/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 276,
        "Question": "What is the total mass flow rate through the gas generator if the oxidizer flow through it is 15 kg/s and fuel flow is 18 kg/s?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3 kg/s",
            "b) 48 kg/s",
            "c) 53 kg/s",
            "d) 33 kg/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation:  Total mass flow rate through the gas generator mgg = (mgg)o + (mgg)f\nmgg = 15 + 18 = 33 kg/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 277,
        "Question": "In a turbopump, what are are the gear ratios for ao and af (for oxidizer pump and fuel pump respectively) if no gears are used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0 for both",
            "b) 1 for both",
            "c) 0 for ao and 1 for af",
            "d) 0 for af and 1 for ao"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If no gears are used, ao = af = 1. For shaft speed N, aoNo = afNf, where the subscript o and f denote oxidizer and fuel respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 278,
        "Question": "If the gear ratio for fuel pump is thrice that of the oxidizer pump, the shaft speed of fuel pump is ____________ the oxidizer pump.",
        "Options": [
            "a) half",
            "b) twice",
            "c) thrice",
            "d) one-third"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: One-third because it follows from the relation, aoNo = afNf.\nGiven, af=3 x ao.\nUsing this, Nf = 1/3 x No."
    },
    {
        "id": 279,
        "Question": "If power of turbines equals PT, power consumed by pumps is PP and the power consumed by auxiliaries is PA, what is the expression for auxiliary power?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PA = PP – PT",
            "b) PA = PP + PT",
            "c) PA = PT – PP",
            "d) PA = PT x PP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Turbine power produced is consumed by pumps as well as the auxiliaries. This is called as the power balance for turbopumps."
    },
    {
        "id": 280,
        "Question": "The power is expressed as the product of torque and ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) vehicle speed",
            "b) shaft speed",
            "c) exhaust velocity",
            "d) volume flow rate per unit cross-sectional area"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Torque L x Shaft speed N is a form of representation of the power P. Part of the power produced goes to waste by bearing, seal, transmission, and friction losses."
    },
    {
        "id": 281,
        "Question": "Which of the following expressions is true when there are no gears in a particular turbopump?",
        "Options": [
            "a) NT = No ≠ Nf",
            "b) NT ≠ No = Nf",
            "c) NT ≠ No ≠ Nf",
            "d) NT = No = Nf"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If there are no gears in a particular turbopump, then all the shaft speeds are same. So NT = No = Nf is the correct expression."
    },
    {
        "id": 282,
        "Question": "If L represents torque, and the subscripts T, o, f, b denotes the turbopump, oxidizer pump, fuel pump and bearings respectively, then which of the following expressions is true when there are no gears in a particular turbopump?",
        "Options": [
            "a) LT = Lo + Lf + Lb",
            "b) LT = Lo x Lf x Lb",
            "c) LT = Lo = Lf = Lb",
            "d) LT = Lo = Lf ≠ Lb"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The torque of the turbopump will then be the sum of all the other torques. This is evident from the expression, PT = LTNT = LoNo + LfNf + Pb. When there are no gears, all the N terms will be equal and the expression simplifies to LT = Lo + Lf + Lb."
    },
    {
        "id": 283,
        "Question": "If the pressure rise ΔP across a pump is half the discharge pressure, then which of the following relates the suction pressure Ps to discharge pressure pd?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ps = pd",
            "b) Ps = 2 x Pd",
            "c) 2 x Ps = Pd",
            "d) Ps = 4 x Pd"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  c\nExplanation: pd = Ps +ΔP.\nSince ΔP = 1/2 Pd, Pd = 2Ps."
    },
    {
        "id": 284,
        "Question": "What is the nature of thrusters and feed system for attitude control rocket engines?",
        "Options": [
            "a) small; common pressurized feed system",
            "b) large; separate turbopump feed system",
            "c) small; separate pressurized feed system",
            "d) large; common turbopump feed system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Thrusters used in rocket engines for attitude control, maneuvering and orbital adjustments are usually small. They are located at different spots on the rocket engine but have a common pressurized feed system."
    },
    {
        "id": 285,
        "Question": "Rocket engines used for orbital adjustments are also called as _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) boost propulsion system",
            "b) primary propulsion system",
            "c) auxiliary rockets",
            "d) strap-on motors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In addition to orbital adjustments, auxiliary rockets also serve the purpose of maneuvering and attitude control. They are also called as reaction control systems."
    },
    {
        "id": 286,
        "Question": "For the application of pure torques in three directions, it requires ______ thrusters.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 12",
            "d) 9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Reaction control systems are the same as auxiliary propulsion systems. So, the thrust is the same. But reaction control systems produce lesser thrust compared to the main propulsion system."
    },
    {
        "id": 287,
        "Question": "Which of the following modes of firing thrusters leads to pure modulation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pulsing mode",
            "b) Step input mode",
            "c) Ramp input mode",
            "d) Sinusoidal mode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It requires 12 thrusters for the purpose of creating pure torques in the three orthogonal directions. Some of them include roll, pitch and yaw thrusters with control valves."
    },
    {
        "id": 288,
        "Question": "A thruster firing repeatedly for 0.010 seconds each time followed by a pause of 0.020 seconds or 0.150 seconds is an example for __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) step input mode",
            "b) pulsing mode",
            "c) sinusoidal mode",
            "d) ramp input mode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In pure modulation, some of the thrusters are fired in pulsing mode. This is a good method for achieving accurate velocity corrections."
    },
    {
        "id": 289,
        "Question": "___________ system determines the maneuver to be performed and _________ system sends command signals to specific thrusters for number of signals required.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Control; control",
            "b) Guidance; guidance",
            "c) Control; guidance",
            "d) Guidance; control"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This kind of mode in which the thrusters are fired for a very brief period of time and then a brief pause is maintained just to repeat the whole process again is an example for pulsing mode of operation of the thrusters."
    },
    {
        "id": 290,
        "Question": "What is range of side force required by a ballistic missile during its final closing maneuver just before nearing in on the target?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100-4500 N",
            "b) 200-6000 N",
            "c) 800-8000 N",
            "d) 1000-18000 N"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Guidance system identifies the maneuver to be performed and the control system sends the signals to specific thrusters. The signals specify the number of pulses needed to complete the maneuver without fail."
    },
    {
        "id": 291,
        "Question": "For very short pulse duration of the thruster firing, the specific impulse is degraded by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1-5%",
            "b) 0.5-1%",
            "c) 5-25%",
            "d) 1-5%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The range of side force required is from 200 N to 6000 N. Upper stages of ballistic missiles are highly maneuverable owing to these high side forces that they require."
    },
    {
        "id": 292,
        "Question": "Reaction control of the Space Shuttle is achieved using ________ thrusters.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 24",
            "b) 48",
            "c) 38",
            "d) 34"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The specific impulse degradation can be from 5% to 25%. This is because the performance during thrust build up and thrust decay are inferior compared to that at the rated operating conditions (without any transience)."
    },
    {
        "id": 293,
        "Question": "When these valves are shut, it shuts off a portion of the propulsion system _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) burst diaphragm",
            "b) isolation valves",
            "c) control valves",
            "d) drainage valves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Isolation valves are shut to negate the contribution from a portion of the propulsion system that it controls. Drainage valves help in draining propellants, while control valves help in controlling the amount of flow passing through the adjacent to the valve."
    },
    {
        "id": 294,
        "Question": "Two valves commonly used in pressurized feed systems are _________ and _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) burst diaphragm and latch valves",
            "b) latch valves and drainage valves",
            "c) burst diaphragm and drainage valves",
            "d) latch valves and Isolation valves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Isolation and latch valves are commonly used for pressurized feed systems. For opening and shutting them down, they require power, but when latched on to some position they don’t require any power."
    },
    {
        "id": 295,
        "Question": "Which of these is a very simple and light valve?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Isolation valves",
            "b) Latch valves",
            "c) Drainage valves",
            "d) Burst diaphragm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Burst diaphragm is a very simple and light valve. It is a circular disc like material which is designed so as to burst when it faces more than a particular pressure differential."
    },
    {
        "id": 296,
        "Question": "German antiaircraft missile Wasserfall used four of which of the following valves?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Burst diaphragm",
            "b) Latch valves",
            "c) Isolation valves",
            "d) Drainage valves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Burst diaphragm is used in the German missile Wasserfall. It actually used 4 of such burst disks."
    },
    {
        "id": 297,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a property of the main liquid oxygen valve?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low pressure",
            "b) High pressure",
            "c) Reusable ball valve",
            "d) Cryogenic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Main liquid oxygen valves are under high pressure. Since liquid oxygen easily evaporates under normal atmospheric conditions, they are kept in cryogenic tanks. These valves also make use of reusable ball valves."
    },
    {
        "id": 298,
        "Question": "Which of the following valves help in controlling gas pressures?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pressure regulator",
            "b) Burst diaphragm",
            "c) Latch valves",
            "d) Isolation valves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pressure regulator, as the name mentions, helps in regulating or controlling gas pressure. Other valves serve different purposes, like maintaining the flow until a pressure differential (burst diaphragm) or for isolation of a particular flow region."
    },
    {
        "id": 299,
        "Question": "Fluids in a rocket engine are conveyed through __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) pipes",
            "b) channels",
            "c) ducts",
            "d) contractions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pipelines are used in conveying fluids in a rocket engine. The complexity of the pipeline network in rocket engines will increase with its size and capabilities."
    },
    {
        "id": 300,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct function of pipes and lines in a rocket engine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Allow thermal expansion and maximize vibrational effects",
            "b) Minimize thermal expansion and minimize vibrational effects",
            "c) Allow thermal expansion and minimize vibrational effects",
            "d) Minimize thermal expansion and maximize vibrational effects"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Pipes and lines in a rocket engine should allow thermal expansion and it should minimize vibrational effects. Irregular fluid flow due to inadequate pipe design may lead to performance issues in the rocket engine."
    },
    {
        "id": 301,
        "Question": "Maximum pressure in pipelines is reduced by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) friction and branching of the pipe",
            "b) friction of the pipe but not its branching",
            "c) branching of the pipe but not its friction",
            "d) neither friction nor branching of the pipe"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Analysis of a particular hammer phenomenon in the pipelines will aid in determining the maximum pressure. This maximum pressure can reduce because of frictional losses and due to branching in the pipe."
    },
    {
        "id": 302,
        "Question": "Water hammer phenomenon in pipelines can help in the determination of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) maximum pressure",
            "b) minimum pressure",
            "c) maximum temperature",
            "d) minimum temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Maximum pressure can be determined using the water hammer phenomenon. It is usually caused by the sudden closing of valves."
    },
    {
        "id": 303,
        "Question": "Which of the following propellants were used in the Titan mission?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50% UDMH + 50% hydrazine",
            "b) RP1",
            "c) RDX",
            "d) Aviation gasoline"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: UDMH is often used in mixed form with 30-50% of hydrazine. Titan missile and launch vehicle make use of this fuel combination."
    },
    {
        "id": 304,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a factor considered in the selection of liquid propellant for a rocket engine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Economic",
            "b) Performance",
            "c) Safety",
            "d) Injector pattern"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Injector pattern is not considered for the selection of liquid propellant. Economic, performance and safety reasons for choosing a propellant are perfectly reasonable."
    },
    {
        "id": 305,
        "Question": "Which of the following chemical particles cannot be suspended in liquid fuel to increase specific impulse?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Boron",
            "b) Beryllium",
            "c) Aluminium",
            "d) Fluorine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Fluorine is highly toxic and corrosive. It may react with propellants as well. So it cannot be used."
    },
    {
        "id": 306,
        "Question": "Which among the following propellants is not corrosive?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Liquid oxygen",
            "b) Nitric acid",
            "c) Nitrogen tetroxide",
            "d) Liquid Fluorine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Liquid oxygen is a non-corrosive propellant. Nitric acid and nitrogen tetroxide are corrosive to some materials, but their extremely low temperature makes their storage and pumping a difficult task. Liquid fluorine is highly corrosive and toxic."
    },
    {
        "id": 307,
        "Question": "What is O-ring in a chemical rocket engine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A kind of seal",
            "b) A type of injector",
            "c) A type of pipe network",
            "d) A kind of control system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: O-ring is a kind of seal technology used in the pressure vessel industry. Liquid rocket engines might use O-ring for the purpose of sealing the propellant tanks."
    },
    {
        "id": 308,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a desirable property of a liquid propellant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low freezing point",
            "b) Low specific gravity",
            "c) Stability",
            "d) High specific heat"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: One of the desirable properties of a liquid propellant is that it should have high specific gravity. Specific gravity is the ratio of density of a substance to the density of a reference substance."
    },
    {
        "id": 309,
        "Question": "What is the average specific gravity(δav) if the specific gravity of the fuel (δf) is 0.792, the specific gravity of the oxidizer is (δo) is 1.02 and the mixture ratio (r) is 4?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.96",
            "b) 0.94",
            "c) 1.01",
            "d) 0.98"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: δav = δoδf(1+r)/(rδf + δo)\nδav = 1.02 x 0.792 x 5/(4×0.792 + 1.02)\n= 0.96."
    },
    {
        "id": 310,
        "Question": "Determine the density specific impulse (Id) if the specific impulse is 315 s and the average density of the propellants is 840 kg/m3. Take the reference density to be the maximum density of water.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 264.6 s",
            "b) 251.3 s",
            "c) 279.5 s",
            "d) 304.4 s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Id = δavIs, where Is is the specific impulse and δ is the average specific gravity.\n∆av = 840/1000 = 0.84, in which consider the density of water to be 1000 kg/m3.\nId = 0.84x 315 = 264.6 s."
    },
    {
        "id": 311,
        "Question": "A good liquid propellant will have ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) easy deterioration",
            "b) resistance to deterioration",
            "c) absorption of moisture",
            "d) small amount of impurities"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A good liquid propellant should have no appreciable absorption of moisture. It should also be resistant to deterioration as it may be required to be kept intact for a long period of mission journey."
    },
    {
        "id": 312,
        "Question": "Evaporation is a major concern for __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) cryogenic propellants",
            "b) monopropellants",
            "c) bipropellants",
            "d) solid propellants"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cryogenic propellants are stored at very low temperatures in their storage/propellant tanks. Even though they have significant performance, their maintenance is a complex and elaborate procedure. Because of their low boiling point vale, they evaporate quickly."
    },
    {
        "id": 313,
        "Question": "__________ are not liquid oxidizers.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nitrogen-fluorine formulations",
            "b) Oxygen-fluorine compounds",
            "c) Fluorinated hydrocarbons",
            "d) Borohydrides"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Borohydrides are not liquid oxidizers. Rest of the options are storable, cryogenic liquid oxidizer propellants with high specific impulse values."
    },
    {
        "id": 314,
        "Question": "___________ is a commonly used liquid oxidizer.",
        "Options": [
            "a) ClF3",
            "b) OF2",
            "c) ClF5",
            "d) H2O2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Hydrogen peroxide (H2O2) is a commonly used liquid oxidizer. But ClF2, OF2, ClF5, etc. are experimental liquid oxidizers."
    },
    {
        "id": 315,
        "Question": "LOX boils at _______ atmospheric pressure.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 909C",
            "b) 90 K",
            "c) 90 F",
            "d) 90 R"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: LOX refers to liquid oxygen. It boils at 90 K. Since their boiling point is very low, a cryogenic setup is required for the storage and transport of this oxidizer."
    },
    {
        "id": 316,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the specific gravity and heat of vaporization of LOX at atmospheric pressure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.14; 213 kJ/kg",
            "b) 1.08; 253 kJ/kg",
            "c) 1.80; 235 kJ/kg",
            "d) 1.41; 231 kJ/kg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: LOX refers to liquid oxygen. It has a specific gravity of 1.14. That means it is 1.14 times denser than water having a density of about 1000 kg/m3. It has a heat of vaporization of 213 kJ/kg."
    },
    {
        "id": 317,
        "Question": "What is the decrease in specific gravity of LOX if the tank pressure is increased from atmospheric pressure to 8 atm? (At 8 atm, specific gravity of LOX is 0.88)",
        "Options": [
            "a) 32.3%",
            "b) 28.2 %",
            "c) 22.8%",
            "d) 25.3%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The increase can be calculated using δinc = (δnew – δold) / δold x 100.\nδinc=(0.88-1.14)/1.14 x 100 = -22.8. Hence the decrease is 22.8%."
    },
    {
        "id": 318,
        "Question": "When are the tanks with cryogenic propellants pressurized?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Just before the engine start",
            "b) After the engine start",
            "c) 10 sec after the engine start",
            "d) 10 sec before the engine start"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is done to ensure that the propellants are at its lowest possible temperature. Else they might evaporate within the tank and may lead to devastating results under wrong circumstances."
    },
    {
        "id": 319,
        "Question": "Which of the following percentages of concentration of hydrogen peroxide is used for rocket applications?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 80 %",
            "b) 60 %",
            "c) 30 %",
            "d) 10 %"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: H2O2 used for rocket applications has a concentration of 80%. It is said to be in its highly concentrated form from 70% to 99%. For commercial uses, hydrogen peroxide is available at 30% concentration."
    },
    {
        "id": 320,
        "Question": "In the combustion chamber, hydrogen peroxide decomposes to give __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) hydrogen and oxygen",
            "b) hydrogen and water",
            "c) oxygen and water",
            "d) water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Decomposition of hydrogen peroxide gives oxygen and water.\nThe reaction is represented as H2O2 → H2O + 1/2O2 + heat."
    },
    {
        "id": 321,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a catalyst used for H2O2 decomposition?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Platinum",
            "b) Iron oxide",
            "c) Manganese dioxide",
            "d) Aluminium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Aluminium tanks are generally used for storing H2O2 for this reason. Whereas hydrazine is not compatible with iron, copper, its alloys, monel, magnesium, zine or some types of aluminium alloys."
    },
    {
        "id": 322,
        "Question": "Theoretical specific impulse of 90% H2O2 is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 204 s",
            "b) 154 s",
            "c) 321 s",
            "d) 114 s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: 90% H2O2 has a specific impulse of 204s. Because of this good specific impulse, countries like USA, Russia and Germany used concentrated hydrogen peroxide for monopropellant gas generation before 1955."
    },
    {
        "id": 323,
        "Question": "__________ is not liquid fuel.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Xylidine",
            "b) Furfuryl alcohol",
            "c) Hydrazine hydrate",
            "d) Nitric acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Nitric acid is not a fuel, but and oxidizer. HNO3 is also used as a very strong oxidizing agent in chemical reactions."
    },
    {
        "id": 324,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a liquid fuel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ammonia",
            "b) Ethyl alcohol",
            "c) Borohydrides",
            "d) Hydrogen peroxide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Hydrogen peroxide (H2O2) acts as an oxidizer. Ammonia (NH3), ethyl alcohol (C2H5OH), and Borohydrides (containing BH4–) are liquid fuels."
    },
    {
        "id": 325,
        "Question": "Petroleum derivatives are mainly ___________ chemicals.",
        "Options": [
            "a) hydrocarbon",
            "b) gasoline",
            "c) alcoholic",
            "d) aldehydic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Petroleum derivatives are hydrocarbon chemicals. This means that it is a compound made up of hydrogen and carbon."
    },
    {
        "id": 326,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a hydrocarbon fuel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kerosene",
            "b) Diesel",
            "c) Turbojet fuel",
            "d) Ethyl alcohol"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Ethyl alcohol is not a hydrocarbon fuel. Kerosene and diesel are petroleum derivatives."
    },
    {
        "id": 327,
        "Question": "Petroleum fuels form ________ radiating flames.",
        "Options": [
            "a) blue-green",
            "b) orange-red",
            "c) yellow-white",
            "d) orange-yellow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The bright brilliant radiating flames of petroleum fuels are yellow-white in color. Main examples of petroleum fuels include kerosene, gasoline, gaseous fuels like methane, propane, butane etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 328,
        "Question": "Carbon deposits on the inside of cooling passage can lead to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) decrease in heat transfer and decrease in wall temperature",
            "b) increase in heat transfer and decrease in wall temperature",
            "c) decrease in heat transfer and increase in wall temperature",
            "d) increase in heat transfer and increase in wall temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cooling passages by some means may have carbon deposits on its inside. This can lead to a decrease in heat transfer and an increase in the wall temperature. It happens because the operation of cooling passages is inhibited by the carbon deposits and as a result the cooling is ineffective."
    },
    {
        "id": 329,
        "Question": "Atlas, Delta and Thor rocket engines use __________ fuel along with liquid oxygen.",
        "Options": [
            "a) RP-1",
            "b) RDX",
            "c) HMX",
            "d) H2O2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: RP-1 is used in Thor, Delta and Atlas rocket engines as a fuel. Oxidizer for this fuel is usually liquid oxygen. RP-1 is a highly refined form of kerosene."
    },
    {
        "id": 330,
        "Question": "Methane is a __________ fuel.",
        "Options": [
            "a) cryogenic hydrocarbon",
            "b) monopropellant",
            "c) bipropellant",
            "d) hypergolic hydrocarbon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Methane falls under the category of cryogenic hydrocarbon fuels. Using methane or RP-1 have shown to give a small advantage in the performance of initial stages of space launch vehicles."
    },
    {
        "id": 331,
        "Question": "RP-1 specific gravity at 15°C is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.80",
            "b) 0.75",
            "c) 0.70",
            "d) 0.65"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: RP-1 is a highly refined form of kerosene. It is alternatively called as Rocket Propellant-1 or Refined Petroleum-1. It has a specific gravity of 0.80 at a temperature of 15°C."
    },
    {
        "id": 332,
        "Question": "H2 burns with oxygen with a ________ flame.",
        "Options": [
            "a) yellow-orange",
            "b) yellow-white",
            "c) colorless",
            "d) blue-yellow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When H2  burns with oxygen, it produces a colorless flame. In reality, the flame is a pale blue that appears to be invisible in daylight."
    },
    {
        "id": 333,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a monopropellant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) H2",
            "b) Diluted H2O2",
            "c) Hydrazine",
            "d) Monomethyl hydrazine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hydrazine can be used as a monopropellant. It can also be used as a storable fuel. Concentrated H2O2 is another example for a monopropellant."
    },
    {
        "id": 334,
        "Question": "___________ is not a method of monopropellant ignition.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flame heat",
            "b) Electrical",
            "c) Catalytic material",
            "d) Pulverization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pulverization for the sake of monopropellant ignition is not a possible method. Pulverization is the act of grinding a substance to powder or dust form."
    },
    {
        "id": 335,
        "Question": "___________ is an excellent catalyst for hydrazine at room temperature.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zeolite",
            "b) Iridium",
            "c) Antimony trioxide",
            "d) Cobalt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Iridium is an excellent catalyst for hydrogen decomposition reaction at room temperature. For faster startup, the catalyst can be reheated."
    },
    {
        "id": 336,
        "Question": "Iron, nickel and cobalt can decompose hydrazine at ________ temperature.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 273 K",
            "b) 289 K",
            "c) 400 K",
            "d) 450 K"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Hydrazine will be decomposed in the presence of iron, nickel or cobalt at elevated temperatures (about 450K). Here the temperature act as an agent for improving catalytic decomposition. Some of the other catalysts can do the same at room temperature."
    },
    {
        "id": 337,
        "Question": "In catalytic decomposition of hydrazine, it decomposes into ________ and _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) ammonia; nitrogen",
            "b) hydrogen; nitrogen",
            "c) ammonium; nitrogen",
            "d) ammonia; hydrogen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hydrazine has a chemical formula of N2H4. It undergoes catalytic decomposition to give ammonia (NH3) and nitrogen (N2). Some forms of hydrazine include monomethyl hydrazine (MMH) and unsymmetrical dimethyl hydrazine (UDMH)."
    },
    {
        "id": 338,
        "Question": "The catalytic decomposition of hydrazine is an __________ reaction.",
        "Options": [
            "a) endothermic",
            "b) exothermic",
            "c) endergonic",
            "d) exergonic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Exothermic reactions involve the release of heat to the surroundings. Hydrazine undergoing catalytic decomposition is an example of exothermic reaction."
    },
    {
        "id": 339,
        "Question": "Ammonia decomposition into nitrogen and hydrogen gases is an _________ reaction.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Endothermic",
            "b) Exothermic",
            "c) Endergonic",
            "d) Exergonic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The decomposition reaction in which nitrogen and hydrogen forms from ammonia is an endothermic reaction. In endothermic reactions, heat is absorbed from the surroundings for the reaction to take place."
    },
    {
        "id": 340,
        "Question": "Hydroxylammonium nitrate has a specific impulse of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 300-365s",
            "b) 10-65s",
            "c) 200-265s",
            "d) 100-165s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Hydroxylammonium nitrate is an example of a synthetic monopropellant. It is abbreviated as HAN. It has a specific impulse in between 200 and 265s."
    },
    {
        "id": 341,
        "Question": "Standard commercial hydrazine has less than ________% aniline.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5",
            "b) 1.0",
            "c) 0.8",
            "d) 0.6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Commercially available hydrazine has less than 1% aniline in it. It also has about 1.5% maximum weight of water and less than 10 mg/l of particulates, including carbon."
    },
    {
        "id": 342,
        "Question": "UDMH stands for _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Unsymmetrical Dimethyl Hydrazine",
            "b) Unsaturated Dimethyl Hydrazine",
            "c) Unsymmetrical Diethyl Hydrazine",
            "d) Unsaturated Diethyl Hydrazine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: UDMH is the short form of Unsymmetrical Dimethyl Hydrazine. Its chemical formula is (CH3)2NNH2. UDMH is often used instead of hydrazine because forms a more stable liquid at larger temperatures."
    },
    {
        "id": 343,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a gold gas propellant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nitrogen",
            "b) Argon",
            "c) Freon 14",
            "d) Hydrazine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Some of the cold gas propellants are Argon, Krypton, Freon 14 and Nitrogen. Reaction control systems typically use cold gas propellants. Hydrazine is a monopropellant."
    },
    {
        "id": 344,
        "Question": "For cold gas propellants, tank pressure is typically between __________ and __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 300 Mpa; 1000 Mpa",
            "b) 100 Mpa; 500 Mpa",
            "c) 200 Mpa; 1000 Mpa",
            "d) 300 Mpa; 500 Mpa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The tank used for the storage of cold gas propellants typically have a pressure between 300 Mpa and 1000 Mpa. Cold gas propulsion is used typically for low thrust space propulsion purposes. Nitrogen is the most preferred cold gas propellant due to its lack of contamination, storage density and performance characteristics. "
    },
    {
        "id": 345,
        "Question": "Selection of propellant, storage tank, and RCS design depends on?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mass and volume of storage tanks, maximum thrust and total impulse",
            "b) Maximum thrust and total impulse but not the storage tank mass or volume",
            "c) Maximum thrust and storage tank mass and volume but not total impulse",
            "d) None of maximum thrust, total impulse or storage tank properties"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It depends upon all the three properties. In addition, it also depends upon the gas density, required maneuvers, flight duration and duty cycle."
    },
    {
        "id": 346,
        "Question": "Total impulses of cold gas systems are about _______ N-sec.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 400",
            "b) 800",
            "c) 1200",
            "d) 1600"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cold gas systems can deliver total impulse having a magnitude of 1200 N-sec or 5000 lbf-sec. For higher total impulse values, liquid propellants are used."
    },
    {
        "id": 347,
        "Question": "For a short period of operation (lasting few minutes), the gas expansion in cold gas systems is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) isothermal",
            "b) adiabatic",
            "c) homogenous",
            "d) heterogeneous"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Since the operation lasts only a short period of time, the expansion can be taken as adiabatic. It means that there is no heat absorption or release by the gas."
    },
    {
        "id": 348,
        "Question": "Thrust in RCS is produced by the momentum exchange between exhaust and the ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) payload",
            "b) injector",
            "c) spacecraft",
            "d) pump"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  Thrust generation is due to the exchange of momentum between exhaust and the spacecraft. The thrust is given by Newton’s second law F = mVe."
    },
    {
        "id": 349,
        "Question": "Which of the following gives a rough estimate of specific impulse provided by cold gas systems?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30-70 s",
            "b) 80-150 s",
            "c) 10-50 s",
            "d) 200-300 s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In order to decrease power consumption, one can use solenoid valves. It requires an electric pulse to open and close and hence can be easily controlled with lesser power expended."
    },
    {
        "id": 350,
        "Question": "How are forces from a cold gas thruster measured in a testing environment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Using strain gage",
            "b) Using load cells",
            "c) Using force balance",
            "d) Using accelerometers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Depending upon the propellant used, the specific impulse of the system will vary. For attitude control or orbital corrections, specific impulse required is lesser compared to other rocket engines. Hence the cold gas system provides less specific impulse."
    },
    {
        "id": 351,
        "Question": "Use of stainless steel thruster helps in _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) elimination of reaction between propellants and thrusters",
            "b) increase in specific impulse",
            "c) reduction of total power consumption",
            "d) providing better orbital correction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Load cells aid in measuring the thrust produced by the cold gas thrusters. For example, PRSS (Pakistan’s first Remote Sensing Satellite) thrusters use FUTEK load cells for this purpose."
    },
    {
        "id": 352,
        "Question": "Burning of the propellants take place in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) nozzle",
            "b) injector",
            "c) combustion chamber",
            "d) engine casing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Propellants burn in the combustion chamber for both solid and liquid rocket engines. This burning can produce temperatures higher than melting points of many of the chamber wall materials. So, an effective cooling system is used to mitigate this issue."
    },
    {
        "id": 353,
        "Question": "The volume of the combustion chamber is selected on the basis of which of these factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mixing, evaporation and complete combustion of the propellants",
            "b) Mixing and complete combustion of the propellants, but not its evaporation",
            "c) Evaporation and complete combustion of the propellants, but not mixing",
            "d) Mixing and evaporation but not the complete combustion of the propellants"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: All the three factors – mixing, complete combustion and evaporation of the propellants are considered for the choice of the volume of combustion chamber. It is chosen such that the mixing is good, evaporation is less and the complete combustion is ensured at all times."
    },
    {
        "id": 354,
        "Question": "Which of the following will aid in the selection of smaller combustion chamber volume during its design?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slightly reactive propellants",
            "b) Low chamber pressure",
            "c) Injectors with moderate mixing",
            "d) Possibility for complete combustion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If there are means of achieving complete combustion, then the size of the combustion chamber may be reduced. Other than that, using highly reactive propellants (with adequate safety measures), having high chamber pressure and using injectors with good mixing will also act as factors for the selection of a smaller combustion chamber."
    },
    {
        "id": 355,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true for combustion chambers with large volume and diameter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High heat transfer rates to the walls",
            "b) Smaller total area exposed to the heat",
            "c) Thinner walls",
            "d) Lower wall temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Heat transfer to the chamber wall will be less if the diameter and volume of the chamber is large. This is due to the large area exposed to heat and due to thicker walls of the chamber."
    },
    {
        "id": 356,
        "Question": "The combustion chamber mass is not a function of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) payload mass",
            "b) method of cooling",
            "c) chamber pressure",
            "d) nozzle area ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The combustion chamber mass is not a function of payload mass. But it will depend upon the method of cooling, area ratio of the nozzle and the chamber pressure."
    },
    {
        "id": 357,
        "Question": "For increased operating chamber pressure, the length of the combustion chamber ________ and the nozzle throat area _________ if the diameter of the combustion chamber (assume the shape to be cylindrical) is fixed and the thrust remains constant.",
        "Options": [
            "a) increases; decreases",
            "b) decreases; increases",
            "c) decreases; decreases",
            "d) increases; increases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The combustion chamber length will decrease because the combustion chamber volume decreases with the chamber pressure for the same thrust. It will also lead to a decrease in the nozzle throat area."
    },
    {
        "id": 358,
        "Question": "What is characteristic chamber length?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thrust chamber length without the length of the nozzle",
            "b) Length of the thrust chamber as if it were a straight tube with no converging section",
            "c) Total length of the nozzle",
            "d) Total length of the rocket engine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Characteristic length is the length of the thrust chamber assuming that it was a straight tube with no converging section.\nL* = Vc/At, where Vc is the chamber volume and At is the throat area."
    },
    {
        "id": 359,
        "Question": "Determine the chamber volume if the characteristic length of a thrust chamber is 150 cm and nozzle throat area is 0.25m2.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.573 m3",
            "b) 0.735 m3",
            "c) 0.375 m3",
            "d) 0.753 m3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Characteristic length L* = Vc/At, where Vc is the chamber volume At is the nozzle throat area.\nSo, Vc = 150 x 10-2 x 0.25 = 0.375 m3."
    },
    {
        "id": 360,
        "Question": "Typical values of L* for several bipropellants lie between __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.8 and 3 m",
            "b) 1 and 2 m",
            "c) 1.5 and 5.5 m",
            "d) 3.2 and 6.4 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: L* typically has a range of 0.8 to 3 m. This is the case for bipropellants. For monopropellants, it may lie even higher."
    },
    {
        "id": 361,
        "Question": "What is stay time?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Average time spent by each molecule or atom within the combustion chamber volume",
            "b) Average time spent by each molecule or atom within the thrust chamber volume",
            "c) Average time spent by each molecule or atom within the propellant tank after rocket take off",
            "d) Average time spent by each molecule or atom within the injector manifold"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Stay time is the average time that each molecule or atom of the propellant stays within the volume of the combustion chamber.\nIt is defined by ts = Vc/mVi, where Vc is the chamber volume, m is the mass flow rate, and Vi is the average specific volume."
    },
    {
        "id": 362,
        "Question": "The carburetor of an internal combustion engine has a similar function as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) injector",
            "b) thrust chamber",
            "c) nozzle",
            "d) propellant tank"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Injector in rocket engine and carburetor in an internal combustion engine functions in a similar manner. Injector meters, injects and atomizes the liquid propellants into the combustion chamber."
    },
    {
        "id": 363,
        "Question": "The process by which liquids are broken into small droplets is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) atomization",
            "b) vaporization",
            "c) disintegrator",
            "d) pulverization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Atomization is the process through which the liquid is broken into tiny droplets. One of the functions of injector is atomization."
    },
    {
        "id": 364,
        "Question": "_________ helps in the distribution of propellant from the injector inlet.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Injector hole pattern",
            "b) Turbopump",
            "c) Preburner",
            "d) Gas generator cycle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: By varying the injector hole pattern, it is possible to get different types of propellant distribution from the injector inlet. It is related to feed passages and internal manifolds within the injector."
    },
    {
        "id": 365,
        "Question": "A large complex manifold of an injector allows ________ and ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) high flow velocities; good distribution of flow over the chamber cross-section",
            "b) low flow velocities; good distribution of flow over the chamber cross-section",
            "c) high flow velocities; poor distribution of flow over the chamber cross-section",
            "d) low flow velocities; poor distribution of flow over the chamber cross-section"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For larger manifolds, the injector flow will be lesser and the distribution of flow over the chamber cross-section will be uniform. This can be seen by considering two passages of varying cross-sections and constant mass flow rate of propellants through it."
    },
    {
        "id": 366,
        "Question": "A small manifold volume of an injector results in ________ and ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) less dribble; heavier injector",
            "b) more dribble; heavier injector",
            "c) less dribble; lighter injector",
            "d) more dribble; lighter injector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Dribble flow is remaining flow after the valve closes. For a smaller manifold volume of an injector, the amount of dribble flow will be lesser. Since the injector is small, only a small mass of material is used for injector manufacturing and hence it leads to a lighter injector."
    },
    {
        "id": 367,
        "Question": "The flow through injector manifold after the main valves are shut is called as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) dribble flow",
            "b) main flow",
            "c) bleed flow",
            "d) pipe flow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dribble or dripping flow is the flow after the main valves are shut. This uneven flow is undesirable and needs to minimize."
    },
    {
        "id": 368,
        "Question": "To make a sharp, abrupt start to fuel injection _________ is used.",
        "Options": [
            "a) pop valve",
            "b) check valve",
            "c) safety valve",
            "d) anti-dribble valve"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pop valve is used for that purpose. It sharply opens to allow full flow. This type of valve opens only when a certain pressure has been attained."
    },
    {
        "id": 369,
        "Question": "Which of the following can cause afterburning?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Complete combustion",
            "b) Dribbling flow",
            "c) Sloshing in propellant tank",
            "d) Use of cold gas propellant system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Dribbling flow can cause afterburning. The dribble flow may lead to an excess in fuel and this might end up in secondary reactions after passing the combustion chamber and result in afterburning."
    },
    {
        "id": 370,
        "Question": "Non-impinging injector is also called as _________ injector.",
        "Options": [
            "a) showerhead",
            "b) multiple-hole",
            "c) doublet",
            "d) like-on-like"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A showerhead injector is also called as a non-impinging injector. The propellant usually comes out normal to the face cross-section of the injector."
    },
    {
        "id": 371,
        "Question": "Which of the following injectors requires large chamber volume for good combustion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sheet injector",
            "b) Showerhead injector",
            "c) Impinging-stream-type injector",
            "d) Multiple-hole injector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sheet injector requires large chamber volume for good combustion. It is a spray-type injector that can give cylindrical, conical and many other kinds of spray sheets."
    },
    {
        "id": 372,
        "Question": "If dT/dL denotes temperature gradient with respect to thickness L at the surface A, k denotes the thermal conductivity, then the heat transferred per unit area is given by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Q/A = -k dT/dL",
            "b) Q/A = -(1/k) dT/dL",
            "c) Q/A = k dT/dL",
            "d) Q/A = (1/k) kdT/dL"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Q/A = -k dT/dL is the expression for heat transferred per unit area. This is called as Fourier’s law of heat transfer. By negative symbol in the equation, we can see that the direction of heat transfer is in the direction of negative gradient (larger temperature to smaller temperature) of temperature along the length of the material."
    },
    {
        "id": 373,
        "Question": "Steady state heat transfer through a liquid-cooled rocket chamber wall can be considered as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) series type with strong temperature gradient",
            "b) parallel type with weak temperature gradient",
            "c) series type with weak temperature gradient",
            "d) parallel type with strong temperature gradient"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The heat transfer through the liquid-cooled rocket chamber can be considered as a steady state series type process with strong temperature gradients. This involves a large temperature gradient across the thin gaseous film touching the wall, a temperature drop across the wall and a third temperature drop in the presence of the moving cooling fluid."
    },
    {
        "id": 374,
        "Question": "The whole process of heat transfer through the chamber wall is a combination of ________ through the chamber wall and ________ through the flowing fluids.",
        "Options": [
            "a) conduction; convection",
            "b) convection; radiation",
            "c) radiation; conduction",
            "d) conduction; conduction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Heat transfer through the chamber walls includes both the conduction through the chamber wall as well as convection through the flowing fluids. This problem is basically one that is associated with the heat and mass transport associated with through a wall."
    },
    {
        "id": 375,
        "Question": "For absolute chamber gas temperature Tg, absolute liquid temperature Tl, overall film coefficient h, gas film coefficient hg and liquid film coefficient hl, determine the expression for heat transferred per unit area q.",
        "Options": [
            "a) q = h/(hg hl) x (Tg – Tl)",
            "b) q = hg (Tg – Tl)",
            "c) q = hghl/h x (Tg – Tl)",
            "d) q = h (Tg – Tl)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: q = h(Tg – Tl) is the correct expression for heat transferred per unit area. This relation assumes that the heat flow is radial in direction."
    },
    {
        "id": 376,
        "Question": " For absolute chamber gas temperature Tg, absolute liquid temperature Tl, absolute wall temperature on the gas side of the wall Twg,  overall film coefficient h, gas film coefficient hg and liquid film coefficient hl, determine the expression for heat transferred per unit area q.",
        "Options": [
            "a) q = hl (To – Twg)",
            "b) q = h (To – Twg)",
            "c) q = hg (To – Twg)",
            "d) q = hg/h (Twg – To)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: q = hg (To – Twg) is the correct expression for heat transferred per unit area q. This is true for a regeneratively cooled thrust chamber. The strength of the material as well as its thermal properties are considered to be a function of temperature."
    },
    {
        "id": 377,
        "Question": "_____ largely determines the numerical heat transfer rate and __________ largely determines the value of wall temperatures.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gas film coefficient; liquid film coefficient",
            "b) Gas film coefficient; thermal conductivity",
            "c) Thermal conductivity; liquid film coefficient",
            "d) Liquid film coefficient; gas film coefficient"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gas film coefficient largely helps in the determination of numerical value of heat transfer rate. Liquid film coefficient largely helps in determining the value of wall temperatures."
    },
    {
        "id": 378,
        "Question": "Which of the following might simplify the determination of film coefficient?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Combustion oscillations",
            "b) Boundary layer behavior",
            "c) Uniform velocity profile",
            "d) Complex geometry"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Film coefficient calculation might be simplified for a uniform velocity profile. In reality, the determination of this coefficient is very difficult because of the presence of combustion oscillations, complex geometry, non-uniform velocity profile and presence of boundary layers."
    },
    {
        "id": 379,
        "Question": "The quantity hgD/k, where hg is the gas film coefficient, D is the diameter of the chamber and k denotes the gas conductivity is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bartz number",
            "b) Froude number",
            "c) Nusselt number",
            "d) Prandtl number"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: hgD/k is called as the Nusselt number. This is a parameter which comes into picture while dealing with heat transfer problems between a solid body and a moving fluid."
    },
    {
        "id": 380,
        "Question": "The quantity μCp/k, where μ is the absolute gas viscosity, Cp is the specific heat of gas at constant pressure and k is the thermal conductivity is called as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nusselt number",
            "b) Bartz number",
            "c) Prandtl number",
            "d) Froude number"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: μCp/k is the Prandtl number. It is the ratio of momentum diffusivity to thermal diffusivity."
    },
    {
        "id": 381,
        "Question": "Determine the Prandtl number for a liquid having thermal conductivity of 4.6 W/mK, Cp of 8 kJ/kgK. Assume the viscosity to be 1.25 Cp.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.59",
            "b) 7.21",
            "c) 5.91",
            "d) 2.17"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: 1 Cp = 10-3 Pa s\nPrandtl number Pr = μCp/K\n= 1.25 10-3 x 8 x 103 / 4.6 = 2.17."
    },
    {
        "id": 382,
        "Question": "Determine the propellant mass flow rate for a TSFC of 3200 kg/Ns and a total thrust of 50 kN.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 21.65 kg/s",
            "b) 12.56 kg/s",
            "c) 16.52 kg/s",
            "d) 15.62 kg/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Propellant flow rate ṁ = F/c, where F is the total thrust and c is the specific fuel consumption.\nThen ṁ = 50,000/3200 = 15.62 kg/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 383,
        "Question": "Find the fuel flow rate for a total propellant flow of 10 kg/s and a mixture ratio of 2.3.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4.71 kg/s",
            "b) 7.41 kg/s",
            "c) 1.47 kg/s",
            "d) 4.17 kg/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Fuel flow rate ṁf = ṁ/(r+1), where ṁ is the total propellant mass flow rate and r is the mixture ratio.\nSo ṁf = 10/2.4 = 4.17 kg/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 384,
        "Question": "Calculate the flow rate of LOX to the combustion chamber in a LOX-H2 rocket engine if the total propellant flow rate is 17 kg/s and mixture ratio is 3.2.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 11.33 kg/s",
            "b) 15.92 kg/s",
            "c) 12.95 kg/s",
            "d) 13.67 kg/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ṁo = ṁr/(r+1)\nSo ṁo = 17*3.2/4.2 = 12.95 kg/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 385,
        "Question": "Determine the nozzle throat area for a rocket engine producing a total thrust of 10 kN, chamber pressure of 5.2 MPa and thrust coefficient of 1.9.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10.12 cm2",
            "b) 12.10 cm2",
            "c) 11.20 cm2",
            "d) 21.10 cm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Nozzle throat area At = F/P1CF, where P1 is the chamber pressure, CF is the thrust coefficient and F is the total thrust provided by the rocket engine.\nThen At = 10000/(5.2 x 106 x 1.9)\n= 10.12 cm2."
    },
    {
        "id": 386,
        "Question": "If the semi-divergence angle of a conical nozzle is 15°, throat diameter is 8.326 cm and exit area is 0.54 m2, determine the nozzle length.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 139.2 cm",
            "b) 239.1 cm",
            "c) 312.9 cm",
            "d) 231.9 cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Nozzle length L = (D2 – D1) / 2tanλ, where D2 is the nozzle exit cross-section diameter, D1 is the nozzle inlet diameter and λ is the semi-divergence angle of the conical nozzle.\nExit diameter D2 = √(4*Ae/π), where Ae is the exit area.\nThen D2 = 82.92 cm\nSo, L = (82.92 – 8.326)/0.536 = 139.2 cm."
    },
    {
        "id": 387,
        "Question": "The pressure drop across injector is usually set between _________ of the chamber pressure.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 45 and 65%",
            "b) 30 and 45%",
            "c) 15 and 25%",
            "d) 5 and 15%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The pressure drop across the injector is set between 15 and 25% of the chamber pressure. This is done partly for obtaining high velocities of propellant injection. High velocities will help in easy atomization and droplet breakup which in turn helps in complete combustion."
    },
    {
        "id": 388,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a realistic value of the discharge coefficient?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5",
            "b) 1.5",
            "c) 5.5",
            "d) 10.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Velocity is maximum for a given pressure drop if the injector discharge coefficient is 1. For rounded and clean injection holes, discharge coefficients can be about 0.80."
    },
    {
        "id": 389,
        "Question": "In which of the following ignition techniques does the system use a solid propellant squib or grain of few seconds of burning duration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spark plug ignition",
            "b) Pyrotechnic ignition",
            "c) Ignition by electrically heated wires",
            "d) Precombustion chamber ignition"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In pyrotechnic ignition, a squib or grain of solid propellant of few seconds of burning duration is used for the sake of ignition. This is one of the common ways of ignition in a solid propellant rocket engine."
    },
    {
        "id": 390,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct expression for energy radiated by a body (Assume ε to be emissivity, A to be surface area, T to be temperature, f to be geometric factor)",
        "Options": [
            "a) E = (1/f)εσAT4",
            "b) E = fεσAT4",
            "c) E = (1/f)εσAT2",
            "d) E = fεσAT2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: E = fεσAT4 is the correct expression for energy radiated by a body. Here σ is the Stefan-Boltzmann constant and it has a value of 5.67 x 10-8 W/m2K4."
    },
    {
        "id": 391,
        "Question": "Which of the following gases show a strong emission band in the region of radiant heat transfer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ammonia",
            "b) Hydrogen",
            "c) Oxygen",
            "d) Nitrogen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gases with symmetrical molecules like hydrogen, oxygen and nitrogen typically doesn’t show a strong band in the region of radiant heat transfer. Heteropolar gases, on the other hand, shows strong activity in that band."
    },
    {
        "id": 392,
        "Question": "Which of the following zones is not a part of the thrust chamber?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Atomization zone",
            "b) Rapid-combustion zone",
            "c) Stream tube combustion zone",
            "d) Transonic flow zone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Atomization zone lies in front of the thrust chamber. Out of the remaining options, transonic flow zone lies in the nozzle while the rest of them are in the combustion chamber region."
    },
    {
        "id": 393,
        "Question": "The boundaries between the discrete combustion zones inside the combustion chamber is not ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) undulating",
            "b) immovable",
            "c) irregular",
            "d) local variations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The boundaries are not immovable. They are dynamically movable and subject to variations in temperature, locally intense radiation emissions etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 394,
        "Question": "Which of the following with regards to mixing and reaction in the combustion chamber is incorrect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Turbulent mixing",
            "b) Multiple chemical reactions",
            "c) Temperature rise increases densities",
            "d) Local mixture ratio variations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Temperature rise leads to reduced densities. The local mixture ratios, velocities, or reaction rates are non-uniform across the chamber. Turbulent mixing and multiple chemical reactions with major heat releases are common in this region."
    },
    {
        "id": 395,
        "Question": "In which of the zones does any remaining liquid droplets of the propellants get vaporized by convective heating?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rapid combustion zone",
            "b) Stream tube combustion zone",
            "c) Transonic-flow zone",
            "d) Supersonic expansion zone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Any remaining liquid droplets of propellants get vaporized by convective heating in the rapid combustion zone. In this zone, intensive chemical reactions take place at an increasingly higher temperature."
    },
    {
        "id": 396,
        "Question": "The mixing in rapid combustion zone is not aided by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) local turbulence",
            "b) diffusion of the gas species",
            "c) supersonic compression waves",
            "d) vaporization of the liquid propellants"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Local turbulence, diffusion of the gaseous species and vaporization of the liquid propellants all aid the mixing process in rapid combustion zone. The flow through the combustion chamber is subsonic in nature. So, supersonic compression waves cannot occur inside the combustion chamber."
    },
    {
        "id": 397,
        "Question": "Propellants injected through the injector orifices travel at velocities between _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0 and 22 m/s",
            "b) 7 and 60 m/s",
            "c) 23 and 98 m/s",
            "d) 105 and 320 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is because the rapid expansion of gases in the combustion zone increases the axial velocity by more than a factor of 100, so the gas flows quickly in this zone, while it is not so quick upstream."
    },
    {
        "id": 398,
        "Question": "Evaporation of the atomized droplets can happen due to heat transferred by ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) radiation from rapid combustion zone, but not by convection from moderately hot gases in the first zone",
            "b) radiation from rapid combustion zone and by convection from moderately hot gases in the first zone",
            "c) convection from moderately hot gases in the first zone, but not by radiation from rapid combustion zone",
            "d) neither radiation from rapid combustion zone nor by convection from moderately hot gases in the first zone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The propellant injection velocity typically lies between 7 and 60 m/s. It influences the combustion behavior and any small change in them can have a major effect on its instability."
    },
    {
        "id": 399,
        "Question": "The atomization region before the rapid combustion zone is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) homogenous",
            "b) heterogeneous",
            "c) isentropic",
            "d) isothermal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Radiation of heat from the high temperature rapid combustion zone and convection from moderately hot gases in the first zone will lead to the evaporation of the atomized droplets of the propellants."
    },
    {
        "id": 400,
        "Question": "Heat generation in the first zone of the atomization region is relatively low because of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) liquids and gases are relatively hot",
            "b) vaporization causing a cooling effect",
            "c) vaporization causing fuel-rich and fuel-lean regions",
            "d) low flow velocity in the injector zone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The atomization zone has both propellants – the fuel and the oxidizer. Some of them exist in liquid droplet form, while the others are in vaporized form. Their combination is hence heterogeneous."
    },
    {
        "id": 401,
        "Question": "Which of the following terms best describes the combustion when the pressure fluctuation during steady operation is 4% of the mean chamber pressure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Smooth combustion",
            "b) Rough combustion",
            "c) Combustion instability",
            "d) Complete combustion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the pressure fluctuations do not exceed 5% of the mean chamber pressure, the combustion is called as smooth combustion. Combustion in a liquid rocket engine in reality is never smooth."
    },
    {
        "id": 402,
        "Question": "Which of the following terms best describe the combustion when the pressure fluctuations during steady operation is 12% of the mean chamber pressure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Complete combustion",
            "b) Incomplete combustion",
            "c) Smooth combustion",
            "d) Rough combustion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If the pressure fluctuations exceed 5% of the mean chamber pressure, the combustion is called rough combustion. Normal liquid rocket engines in reality display rough combustion."
    },
    {
        "id": 403,
        "Question": "low-frequency combustion instability is called ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) chugging",
            "b) buzzing",
            "c) squealing",
            "d) screaming"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Chugging is the term used to denote combustion instabilities with low-frequency of occurrence of fairly large concentrations of vibratory energy. The frequency range for this instability is 10-400 Hz."
    },
    {
        "id": 404,
        "Question": "Intermediate frequency combustion instability is called ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) squealing",
            "b) chugging",
            "c) screaming",
            "d) buzzing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Buzzing is the term used to denote combustion instabilities with an intermediate frequency of occurrence of fairly large concentrations of vibratory energy. The frequency range for this instability is 400-1000 Hz."
    },
    {
        "id": 405,
        "Question": "high-frequency combustion instability is called ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) squealing",
            "b) buzzing",
            "c) chugging",
            "d) entropy waves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Squealing is the term used to denote combustion instabilities with high-frequency of occurrence of fairly large concentrations of vibratory energy. The frequency range lies above 1000 Hz. It is also called screaming."
    },
    {
        "id": 406,
        "Question": "Which of the following combustion instabilities occur due to propellant pump cavitation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Buzzing",
            "b) Chugging",
            "c) Pogo",
            "d) Screaming"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Chugging can occur in test facilities due to the propellant pump cavitation. It can also happen due to gas entrapment in propellant flow or due to tank pressurization control fluctuations."
    },
    {
        "id": 407,
        "Question": "Which of the following combustion instabilities happen due to propellant flow rate disturbances?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Screeching",
            "b) Entropy waves",
            "c) Screaming",
            "d) Pogo"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pogo instability is a longitudinal instability due to propellant flow rate disturbances. They are low-frequency waves, usually lying in the 10-50 Hz frequency zone."
    },
    {
        "id": 408,
        "Question": "Transverse mode of high-frequency instability propagation can be broken into ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) longitudinal and radial modes",
            "b) longitudinal and tangential modes",
            "c) radial, tangential and longitudinal modes",
            "d) tangential and radial modes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: High frequency (HF) instabilities are troublesome as they can lead to destructive results on the engine. Their destructive effect comes from the accelerated heat transfer as a result of these instabilities causing pressure fluctuations of the magnitude greater than about 20% of the mean combustion chamber pressure. Longitudinal and transverse modes are the two modes through which high-frequency instability occurs. The transverse modes can be further divided as radial and tangential modes."
    },
    {
        "id": 409,
        "Question": "Tangential mode of instability has the following modes ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) standing and travelling waves",
            "b) travelling and spinning waves",
            "c) travelling and longitudinal waves",
            "d) spinning and radial waves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Tangential mode can be considered as two waves: Standing wave and traveling wave. Traveling wave is also called as spinning wave. Standing wave remains fixed in position while the traveling tangential wave has a rotation of the whole vibratory system."
    },
    {
        "id": 410,
        "Question": "Acoustically stimulated variations in droplet mixing and/or vaporization can cause ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) screeching",
            "b) spinning wave",
            "c) traveling wave",
            "d) pogo"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Screeching (or squealing) can be caused by acoustically stimulated variations in droplet mixing and/or its vaporization. It can also be caused due to acoustic changes in combustion rates or due to local detonations."
    },
    {
        "id": 411,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the term used to denote a turbine with one or more pumps?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Turboshaft",
            "b) Turbopump",
            "c) Turboprop",
            "d) Turbojet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Turbopump is an arrangement with a turbine and one or more pumps. An alternative to turbopump would be the gas pressure feed system. Both of them have varying applications and are employed depending upon the scenario under consideration, e.g. a long-duration mission to the outer space or a missile within the earth’s atmosphere."
    },
    {
        "id": 412,
        "Question": "Main purpose of a turbopump is to ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) decrease the temperature of flowing propellant",
            "b) increase the temperature of flowing propellant",
            "c) decrease the pressure of flowing propellant",
            "d) increase the pressure of flowing propellant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A turbopump helps in the increase of pressure of the flowing propellants. To initiate the flow of propellants from their storage tanks to the combustion chamber, the propellants must traverse a path of favorable pressure gradient."
    },
    {
        "id": 413,
        "Question": "The propellant enters the pump through __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) duct",
            "b) pipe",
            "c) injector",
            "d) inducer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Inducer can be thought of as a special impeller where the pressure of the propellant is raised by a small amount, typically 5-10% of the total pressure rise. The propellants enter through this inducer to reach the impeller."
    },
    {
        "id": 414,
        "Question": "Majority of the kinetic energy imparted by the impeller to the flow is converted to ___________ in diffuser.",
        "Options": [
            "a) potential energy",
            "b) hydrostatic pressure",
            "c) frictional losses",
            "d) internal energy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is converted to hydrostatic pressure in the diffuser. Part of this conversion will also take place in the volute."
    },
    {
        "id": 415,
        "Question": "The bearings and shaft seals are cooled using ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) part of the propellant flow",
            "b) radiation cooling",
            "c) part of the Exhaust Flow from the nozzle",
            "d) lubricants"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Parts of the propellant flow is used for cooling of bearings and shaft seals. The heat absorbed by the propellants make it more energetic which can be later used during the combustion and expansion processes in the thrust chamber."
    },
    {
        "id": 416,
        "Question": "A geared turbopump has ___________ efficiency for the turbine and ____________ efficiency for the pump.",
        "Options": [
            "a) lower; lower",
            "b) lower; higher",
            "c) higher; lower",
            "d) higher; higher"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Because of the gear system, the two-stage turbine speed is higher than the shaft speed of the pumps and turbine is smaller. It will lead to higher turbine efficiency and higher pump efficiency."
    },
    {
        "id": 417,
        "Question": "Which of these will lead to lower reliability from design perspective of turbopumps?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lower efficiency and higher mass",
            "b) Higher efficiency and lower mass",
            "c) Higher efficiency and higher mass",
            "d) Lower efficiency and lower mass"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: From the design perspective, the reliability of a turbopump with higher efficiency and lower mass will be low. The reason is that by selecting such stringent criteria for efficiency and mass acts as restricted design margins."
    },
    {
        "id": 418,
        "Question": "The total propellant flow at the pump outlet is ____________ the flow in combustion chamber and the discharge pressure is __________ chamber pressure plus the other insignificant pressure losses in the system.",
        "Options": [
            "a) more than; less than",
            "b) more than; more than",
            "c) less than; more than",
            "d) equal to; equal to"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Mass flow rate remains constant. Hence the total propellant flow will be the same for the pump outlet as well as in the combustion chamber. Favorable pressure difference should be present for the flow to take place. The chamber pressure will be different from the nozzle pressure, but the discharge pressure is kept to be the same as the chamber pressure."
    },
    {
        "id": 419,
        "Question": "If the densities of the propellants are very different from one another, the pump head raise is ___________ for the lower-density propellant compared to higher-density propellant.",
        "Options": [
            "a) higher",
            "b) lower",
            "c) equal for both the propellants",
            "d) 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pump head refers to the difference between discharge and suction head of the pump. It is measured in meters or feet. It is much higher for the lower density propellant if the propellant combination used in an engine has a noticeable difference in their densities."
    },
    {
        "id": 420,
        "Question": "____________ is limited by the possibility of excessive cavitation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maximum shaft speed",
            "b) Minimum shaft speed",
            "c) Maximum pump gear ratio",
            "d) Minimum pump gear ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Maximum shaft speed is a key pump parameter. It is restricted by the need to avoid excessive cavitation."
    },
    {
        "id": 421,
        "Question": "For a rocket with an initial mass of 15,000 kg and carrying a payload of 1000 kg, determine the velocity change if it was ground launched and has an equivalent exhaust velocity of 3000 m/s. Assume the structural mass coefficient to be 0.24.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3533 m/s",
            "b) 3967 m/s",
            "c) 3706 m/s",
            "d) 4295 m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Payload ratio λ = 1000/(15000 – 1000) = 0.0714.\n∆V = Ueqln((1+λ)/(ε+λ))\n= 3000 x ln(1.0714/0.3114)\n= 3706 m/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 422,
        "Question": "If δ denotes inert mass fraction and λ denotes the payload fraction, what is the formula for parametric mass ratio (r)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) r = δ/λ",
            "b) r = λ/δ",
            "c) r = λ – δ",
            "d) r = λ + δ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Inert mass fraction is given by the formula δ = min/mo, where min denotes inert mass and mo denotes initial mass of the rocket. Payload mass fraction is λ = mpl/mo, where mpl is the payload mass. Parametric mass ratio is the sum of both the above ratios."
    },
    {
        "id": 423,
        "Question": "Overall engine specific impulse is influenced by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) nozzle area ratio and chamber pressure",
            "b) nozzle area ratio only",
            "c) chamber pressure only",
            "d) neither nozzle area ratio nor chamber pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In addition to the influence of nozzle area ratio and chamber pressure, the overall engine specific impulse also depends on the engine cycle and mixture ratio on a lesser extent."
    },
    {
        "id": 424,
        "Question": "Which of the following ranges describes the typical value of mixture ratio in the engines: SSME, RS-68, LE-5A and Vulcan?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4-7",
            "b) 12-15",
            "c) 1-4",
            "d) 15-20"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: All of the engines use LOX and LH propellants. Mixture ratio for SSME, RS-68, LE-5A and Vulcan are 6, 6, 5, 6 and 5.35 respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 425,
        "Question": "Which of the following engines were used in Ariane 5 vehicle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RS-68",
            "b) Vulcain",
            "c) HM7(A)",
            "d) RL 10-B2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Ariane 5 uses Vulcain engine. The engine makes use of a gas generator cycle. RS-68 (Rocket System 68) was used in the first stage of the Delta IV rocket. HM7 was used as an upper stage engine in Ariane 1. RL 10-B2 was used in Delta 3 and Delta IV launch vehicles."
    },
    {
        "id": 426,
        "Question": "YF 73 engine was used by which of these vehicles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Space Shuttle",
            "b) HII",
            "c) Long March",
            "d) Ariane 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: YF 73 was used by the Long March vehicle. LE-5A and LE-7 were used in HII and SSME was used for Space Shuttle."
    },
    {
        "id": 427,
        "Question": "Which of the following describes the typical range of specific impulse in vacuum produced by the major LOX and LH propellant driven engines?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 400-500 s",
            "b) 300-400 s",
            "c) 150-300 s",
            "d) 0-150 s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  a\nExplanation: Major LOX and LH propellant engines like SSME, RS68 and LE-5A produce specific impulses of 452.5s, 415s and 452s respectively. All of such engines are capable of producing specific impulse values above 400s."
    },
    {
        "id": 428,
        "Question": "LE-5A rocket engine and its derivatives were designed by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) France",
            "b) India",
            "c) China",
            "d) Japan"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: LE-5A and its derivatives were designed by Japan. It was designed to meet the upper stage requirements of H-I and H-II series of launch vehicles."
    },
    {
        "id": 429,
        "Question": "The kind of ignition system that allows multiple restarts for an engine is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) pyrotechnic igniter",
            "b) spark igniter",
            "c) hypergolic igniter",
            "d) pyrotechnic initiator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pyrotechnic igniter and pyrotechnic initiator are same. Spark igniter is capable of multiple restarts while the other two – hypergolic and pyrotechnic igniters are single use ignition systems."
    },
    {
        "id": 430,
        "Question": "Which of the following has metal oxide pyrotechnic composition?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ZPP",
            "b) Ni-Al laminate",
            "c) ZHPP",
            "d) HMTD"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: ZPP is Zirconium Potassium Perchlorate. It is one of the most common initiators and called NASA Standard Initiator. ZHPP is a metal hydride-oxidizer, HMTD is a highly explosive organic compound and Nickel-aluminum laminates are used in electrically initiated pyrotechnic igniters."
    },
    {
        "id": 431,
        "Question": "What is the typical amount of propellant (in percentage) used for a spacecraft propulsion system with a pressurized monopropellant feed system for contingency?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2-10% of the total load",
            "b) 0.5-2% of the total load",
            "c) 70-90% of the total load",
            "d) 5-15% of the total load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Other than increasing the vehicle velocity and producing thrust, they can also be used for other purposes. One such example is flight control function. Here a small amount of the propellants is used for reaction control thrusters to maintain flight stability."
    },
    {
        "id": 432,
        "Question": "How much amount of propellants is allowed in the propellant budget for off-nominal operations in a spacecraft propulsion system with a pressurized monopropellant feed system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5-1% of the total load",
            "b) 0.5% of the total load",
            "c) 0.5-2% of the total load",
            "d) 0.25-1% of the total load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: 2-10% of the total load is used for contingency. Total load Is the sum of propellant amount used for main thrust chamber, flight control function and mission margin. Contingency amount of propellant is reserved for a possible scenario that cannot be predicted with certainty."
    },
    {
        "id": 433,
        "Question": "For a spacecraft propulsion system using pressurized monopropellant feed system, what is the allocated amount of propellants to be used for the main thrust chamber?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 70-90%",
            "b) 10-50%",
            "c) 50-70%",
            "d) 95-99%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Allowance for off-nominal performance is 0.5-1% of the total load. But allowance for of-nominal operations is 0.25-1% of the total load."
    },
    {
        "id": 434,
        "Question": "In a turbopump system using a gas generator cycle, the flame temperature in the separate gas generator where a small portion of overall propellant is burned is _________ compared to the main gas generator and its mixture ratio is _________ compared to that of the main gas generator.",
        "Options": [
            "a) same, lower",
            "b) lower, different",
            "c) lower, higher",
            "d) higher, different"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Main thrust chamber uses the propellants in increasing the velocity of a stage or a vehicle. It is the most important constituent of propellant budget. Its contribution ranges from 70-90%. It is determined from mission analysis and system engineering."
    },
    {
        "id": 435,
        "Question": "The extra propellant required to compensate for the thrust decrease due to the operation of TVC’s component operating against the vehicle velocity direction is _________ of the amount of total propellants.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 to 4%",
            "b) 4 to 6%",
            "c) 0.8 to 10%",
            "d) 1 to 5%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The flame temperature in the smaller gas generator is lesser than the main gas generator. Its mixture ratio is different from that of the main gas generator. This factor contributes to the slight change in the overall mixture ratio of propellants flowing from the tanks."
    },
    {
        "id": 436,
        "Question": "What is the amount of propellants estimated to be that of the residual propellant that clings to the tank walls or remains trapped in valves, injector passages, pipes or cooling passages?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1-0.2% of the total load",
            "b) 0.25-0.5% of the total load",
            "c) 0.5-2% of the total load",
            "d) 5-10% of the total load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The amount of propellants required in this scenario is determined from the mission requirements and the TVC duty cycle. The amount of propellants required may range from 0.1 to 4% of the total propellant."
    },
    {
        "id": 437,
        "Question": "Which of the following occurs due to the variations in the manufacture of hardware from one engine to another?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thrust vectoring",
            "b) Loading uncertainty",
            "c) Off-nominal performance",
            "d) Operational factors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: 0.5-2% of the total propellant load is that of the residual propellant. At the period of thrust termination, it increases the vehicle mass and slightly reduces the flight vehicle velocity."
    },
    {
        "id": 438,
        "Question": "In order to meet a minimum total impulse requirement for a rocket engine displaying off-nominal performance and showing variations in mixture ratio, what has to be done?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Extra propellant to be used to allow for mixture ratio variations",
            "b) Suppress the required propellant injection and attempt the mixture ratio correction",
            "c) Halt the operation and replace the necessary component",
            "d) Change the mission trajectory accordingly"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Off-nominal performance is due to variations in hardware manufacturing and it varies from one engine to another. It can occur due to slightly different losses in a cooling jacket, in injectors and valves or due to different pump characteristics."
    },
    {
        "id": 439,
        "Question": "Which of the following comes under the category of operational factors in a propellant budget?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Variation in tank volume",
            "b) Attempting a complex maneuver",
            "c) Filling more propellant than needed into a tank",
            "d) Pressurizing cryogenic propellant tanks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Extra propellant needs to be tanked for allowing mixture ratio variations. It can even be as high as 2% of one of the propellants."
    },
    {
        "id": 440,
        "Question": "Which of the following studies usually result in a small improvement in vehicle performance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Optimization studies",
            "b) Mission analysis",
            "c) Trajectory design",
            "d) Launch site selection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Optimization studies lead to small improvements in vehicle performance. This process is sometimes completed even before identifying a suitable engine."
    },
    {
        "id": 441,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not optimized in the optimization studies?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mission duration",
            "b) Chamber pressure",
            "c) Nozzle area ratio",
            "d) Thrust"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Chamber pressure, nozzle area ratio, thrust, mixture ratio etc are optimized in the optimization studies. It results in small improvements in propellant fraction, engine volume, cost and vehicle performance."
    },
    {
        "id": 442,
        "Question": "Which of the following primarily involves obtaining data from prior similar engines?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Preliminary engine performance estimates",
            "b) Optimization studies",
            "c) Testing of full scale models",
            "d) Small scale modeling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Preliminary engine performance estimates involves obtaining data from existing similar models. When they are not readily available, then theoretical performance values calculated by incorporating correction factors, experimentation or simulation methods are adapted."
    },
    {
        "id": 443,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a recommended source for arriving at a tentative decision about the engine to be made?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mission requirements",
            "b) Customer preferences",
            "c) Past experiences",
            "d) Full-fledged simulations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Since the decisions to be made are tentative, a full-fledged simulation will most likely result in a waste of time and resources. Making logical decisions backed by mission requirements, customer preferences and past experiences is more sensible approach."
    },
    {
        "id": 444,
        "Question": "__________ generally do not take technical decisions on behalf of the rocket engine design.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Manufacturing experts",
            "b) Field service experts",
            "c) Stress analysis experts",
            "d) Consultancy experts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Experts from the fields of manufacturing, stress analysis, field service and safety are important in making appropriate decisions on behalf of the rocket engine design."
    },
    {
        "id": 445,
        "Question": "Key engine selection decisions are validated later in ___________ process by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) deployment; testing new components and engines",
            "b) development; testing new components and engines",
            "c) preliminary stage; proposing new components and engines based on existing knowledge",
            "d) mission analysis; proposing new components and engines based on existing knowledge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The engine selection decisions are validated in the development stage. In the development stage, new components and new engines are tested."
    },
    {
        "id": 446,
        "Question": "Which of the following are key parameters of interest for the vehicle designer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Both Inert mass and center of gravity",
            "b) Inert mass, but not center of gravity",
            "c) Center of gravity, but not inert mass",
            "d) Neither center of gravity nor inert mass"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Both inert mass of the engine and other mass properties like center of gravity or moment of inertia are key parameters to the customer as well as the vehicle designer. They are used both in the preliminary and final design."
    },
    {
        "id": 447,
        "Question": "_________ balances the pressure drops in fuel, oxidizer and pressurizing gas flow systems.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Performance balance program",
            "b) Engine balance program",
            "c) Optimization program",
            "d) Fuel balance program"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Engine balance program balances the pressure drops in oxidizer and fuel. It also balances pressurizing gas flow systems. It is a kind of computer program that specifically operates on a particular engine cycle."
    },
    {
        "id": 448,
        "Question": "_________ is not a type of engine by the degree of novelty.",
        "Options": [
            "a) New engine with new major components and new design",
            "b) New engine with major components from existing engines.",
            "c) Updated or improved version of a proven engine",
            "d) Reuse of a decommissioned engine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Reuse of a decommissioned engine isn’t part of the degree of novelty. It doesn’t involve any new design procedure and it is not recommended."
    },
    {
        "id": 449,
        "Question": "What is the simulation of the steady-state, internal conditions and functioning of the engine called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Power balance",
            "b) Optimization",
            "c) Engine balance",
            "d) Engine equilibrium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A power balance is a simulation of the steady-state, internal conditions and functioning of an engine. It may require varying levels of complexity to model a power balance, ranging from the use of a simple spreadsheet to the use of complicated computer programs."
    },
    {
        "id": 450,
        "Question": "The complexity of the control elements of the engine systems depend mostly on _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) capital",
            "b) launching site",
            "c) mission",
            "d) trajectory"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The mission determines how complex the engine system will be. If the mission is to reach Mars and deploy a rover, the level of complexity involved will be more compared to a mission to launch a rocket to intercept a missile above the atmosphere."
    },
    {
        "id": 451,
        "Question": "Single-shot devices are _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) devices with a single-engine",
            "b) devices which are deployed only once",
            "c) devices which can fire a single missile",
            "d) colloquial term for missiles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Single-shot devices are those which are deployed once. An example would be Rocketdyne’s X-1."
    },
    {
        "id": 452,
        "Question": "Valves, regulators and pressure switches come into picture while considering _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) solid rocket engines",
            "b) liquid rocket engines",
            "c) both solid and liquid rocket engines",
            "d) neither solid nor liquid rocket engines"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Valves, regulators and pressure switches are required for controlling and regulating the flow of liquid propellants in rocket engines which use them. The use of such equipment adds to the complexity of liquid propellant rocket engines compared to other types."
    },
    {
        "id": 453,
        "Question": "_________ are used to protect personnel and equipment in case of malfunction.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ejection seats",
            "b) Parachute system",
            "c) Rocket casing",
            "d) Safety controls"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Safety controls are maintained in a rocket with the special intention of protecting personnel and equipment in case of its malfunction. When a situation arises where we need to choose as to give weightage to safety or improve the performance and efficiency of a device, the preference will always be towards safety."
    },
    {
        "id": 454,
        "Question": "In which of the following cases does the electrical valves automatically return to their normal positions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nonhazardous shutdown",
            "b) Hazardous shutdown",
            "c) Cold start",
            "d) Warm start"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A failure in electrical power supply may lead to a nonhazardous shutdown in a rocket. In such a case, all the electrical valves return to their normal configuration."
    },
    {
        "id": 455,
        "Question": "_________ permits the simulation of operation of critical control components without the actual hot operation of the rocket unit.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Checkout controls",
            "b) Safety controls",
            "c) Thrust vectoring control",
            "d) Operating control"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In some rocket engines, there are provisions for actuation of principal valves without having propellant or pressure in the system. Check-out controls enables such a provision to be executed."
    },
    {
        "id": 456,
        "Question": "How is the stable operation of liquid propellant flows achieved?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By means of some kind of a pressure feed system",
            "b) By utilizing the gravitational force on the liquids to the rocket’s advantage",
            "c) By using suitable pipes and valves which can minimize vibrations",
            "d) Liquid flow system in general are inherently stable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The liquid flow systems used in liquid propellant rocket engines are inherently stable. This means that when there is a disturbance in the hydraulic system (like a sudden increase or decrease of flow), the system tries to reduce the effect of disturbance on its own."
    },
    {
        "id": 457,
        "Question": "Start delay includes the time taken to _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) close valves",
            "b) terminate combustion",
            "c) lower the flow",
            "d) raise chamber pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Start delay is the time required to do a number of operations. This involves the time to purge the system if required, open valves, initiate combustion, and raise the flow and chamber pressure to their rated values. "
    },
    {
        "id": 458,
        "Question": "Which of the following pressurization systems take more time to start for similar engines?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Turbopump system",
            "b) Gas pressure feed system",
            "c) Both requires the same time",
            "d) Start time is independent of such systems"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For the same kind of rocket engine, turbopump system will require more time to start. This is because of an additional time delay involved in such systems for starting the gas generator or preburner and for bringing the turbopumps up to speed."
    },
    {
        "id": 459,
        "Question": "How much time does it generally take to start a small thruster with a pressurized feed system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3-15 ms",
            "b) 1-5 s",
            "c) 3-15 s",
            "d) 1-5 ms"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It takes about 3-15 ms for starting small thrusters with a pressurized feed system. For a turbopump-fed system, this time can be about 1-5 s."
    },
    {
        "id": 460,
        "Question": "The calibration procedure for the turbopump system is ________ complex compared to gas pressure fed systems.",
        "Options": [
            "a) equally",
            "b) less",
            "c) more",
            "d) unrelated"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The calibration curves cannot be estimated readily without the use of good test data. Hence the calibration procedure for turbopump is more complex."
    },
    {
        "id": 461,
        "Question": "The process of balancing the pressure available to the engine against the pressure drop plus the chamber pressure is called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) chamber balance",
            "b) engine balance",
            "c) pressure balance",
            "d) overall balance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Pressure balance is the term used for denoting the balancing process. The pressure is supplied to the engine by pumps or pressurized tanks. This is an important part of engine calibration for it to operate at desired flow rate and mixture ratios."
    },
    {
        "id": 462,
        "Question": "Which of the following forces on a rocket engine is more significant than the rest of them?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Actuator forces",
            "b) Maneuver forces",
            "c) Vibration forces",
            "d) Thrust load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Thrust load is the most significant. The vehicle structure must be able to withstand this load for its successful operation. It is also called axial load and acts parallel to the vehicle’s longitudinal axis. With variable thrusters, this direction can also be manipulated."
    },
    {
        "id": 463,
        "Question": "Under ideal conditions, the ratio of the rated flows has to be _________ desired mixture ratio.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Equal to",
            "b) less than",
            "c) more than",
            "d) unrelated to"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The ratio of rated flows should be equal to the desired mixture ratio under ideal operating conditions. Ratio of the rated flows is given by ṁo/ṁf. One way of doing this is to add pressure drops with appropriately placed orifices, or changing valve positions or regulator setting."
    },
    {
        "id": 464,
        "Question": "The operating mixture ratio is usually ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) fuel-rich",
            "b) fuel-lean",
            "c) oxidizer-rich",
            "d) doesn’t matter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Operating mixture ratio is usually fuel-rich and the value is determined by optimum specific impulse. This is done because fuel-rich mixtures typically have lower molecular weight. It might also help in afterburning which can improve the overall rocket performance."
    },
    {
        "id": 465,
        "Question": "The calibration procedure for turbopump system is ___________ complex compared to gas pressure fed systems.",
        "Options": [
            "a) equally",
            "b) less",
            "c) more",
            "d) unrelated"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The calibration curves cannot be estimated readily without the use of good test data. Hence the calibration procedure for turbopump is more complex."
    },
    {
        "id": 466,
        "Question": "In a pressurized feed system, the pressurizing gas is supplied from its high-pressure tank through ____ for the pressurization of both fuel and oxidizer.",
        "Options": [
            "a) regulator",
            "b) passage valves",
            "c) expansion joints",
            "d) combustion chamber"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The pressurizing gases first passes through a regulator for pressurization of both the fuel and the oxidizer. Regulators in general, can be used for both liquid and gases and may contain its own restrictor or pressure sensor."
    },
    {
        "id": 467,
        "Question": "The gas pressure in the propellant tank is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) unregulated pressure",
            "b) sea level pressure",
            "c) ambient pressure",
            "d) regulated pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The gas pressure in the propellant tank is regulated pressure Pgas. It is diminished by the pressure losses in the gas line denoted by ∆Pgas. This gas pressure is augmented by the static head of the liquid."
    },
    {
        "id": 468,
        "Question": "Precise control of engine performance parameters via the use of an automatic feedback system employing a digital computer for control purposes is _________ compared to static calibration of the engine design.",
        "Options": [
            "a) simpler",
            "b) complex",
            "c) equally difficult",
            "d) unachievable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The use of an automatic feedback system employing a digital computer is complex compared to static calibration. The error in static calibration indicates a deviation from a linear response of the system. Dynamic measurements may incur appreciable errors because of the nonlinear response."
    },
    {
        "id": 469,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a method of achieving a variable thrust?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Injecting liquid into the gas streams before injection",
            "b) Varying injection element area",
            "c) Varying the nozzle throat area",
            "d) Varying feed system pressure drops"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Injecting gas into liquid streams before the injection is a method for achieving a variable thrust but not vice versa. Varying injection element area can be done via selectable manifolds and movable injector elements."
    },
    {
        "id": 470,
        "Question": "Which of the following can’t happen if a chemical rocket engine were to use gelled propellants?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase in specific impulse",
            "b) Increase in density impulse",
            "c) Possibility of short-duration pulsing",
            "d) Much less likely to have explosions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Depending upon the gelling agent, specific impulse might change. Because of the dilution of the propellants with a gelling agent, there is generally a small decrease in specific impulse. It will also lead to less efficient atomization or combustion. "
    },
    {
        "id": 471,
        "Question": "Which of the following will not happen if small aluminum particles are suspended in the fuel or if small inert solid particles are suspended in the oxidizer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase in propellant density",
            "b) Reduction in tank and vehicle size",
            "c) Decrease in density impulse",
            "d) Increase in speed and range of atmospheric rockets or missiles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Density impulse is the specific impulse of the propellants multiplied by its density. Addition of small inert solid particles will increase the density of the propellant and hence lead to improved impulse density. This also means that the volume required to store the propellants is lesser and the rocket size becomes smaller. It will lead to drag reduction (since the surface area is lesser) under atmospheric operating conditions and improve speed and range of the vehicle."
    },
    {
        "id": 472,
        "Question": "Propellants that are thick or viscous under static conditions, but flow through valves, injectors, pipes or pumps when adequate shear stress is applied are called __________ propellants.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thixotropic",
            "b) Dilatant",
            "c) Newtonian fluid",
            "d) Non-Newtonian fluid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Thixotropic fluids become thinner (or less viscous) over time when adequate shear stresses are applied on it. A dilatant material has increasing viscosity with the rate of shear strain. A Newtonian fluid is a fluid in which the viscous stresses arising from its flow is linearly proportional to the local strain rate. Non-Newtonian fluids are those fluids that doesn’t obey Newton’s law of viscosity (which states that the shear stress between two adjacent fluid layers is proportional to the negative value of velocity gradient between those two layers)."
    },
    {
        "id": 473,
        "Question": "For a missile weighing 60 kg cruising with constant velocity 110 m/s, with lift-to-drag ratio of 8 and Isp of 200, determine the range if the final mass of the missile is 25 kg.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 119 km",
            "b) 132 km",
            "c) 154 km",
            "d) 198 km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: From Breguet’s range equation, R = u Isp (L/D) ln(Wi/Wf), which gives\nR = 110 x 200 x 8 x ln(60/25)\n= 154 km."
    },
    {
        "id": 474,
        "Question": "A tactical missile is not used for _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) attacking ground troops",
            "b) defending ground troops",
            "c) attacking military aircrafts",
            "d) decoy flare"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Decoy flare is an infrared countermeasure taken by airborne vehicles against homing infrared missiles to divert its attention from its target. It is not a kind of tactical missile."
    },
    {
        "id": 475,
        "Question": "Military missiles generally use ___________ rocket engines.",
        "Options": [
            "a) ion-electric",
            "b) chemical",
            "c) nuclear",
            "d) solar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Because of the simplicity in logistics and its ability to be launched quickly, military missiles are typically chemical rocket engines. Most of the time, they employ solid rocket propellants for similar reasons."
    },
    {
        "id": 476,
        "Question": "Verification of initial burning or ignition is done via ________ for visual detection and ________ for heat detection in some rocket engines.",
        "Options": [
            "a) photocell; pyrometer",
            "b) pyrometer; photocell",
            "c) bolometer; pyrometer",
            "d) load cell; pyrometer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bolometer is used for measuring radiant energy, whereas load cells act as transducers which converts force into measurable electrical output. Photocell is used for visual detection, while pyrometer for heat detection."
    },
    {
        "id": 477,
        "Question": "Which of the following doesn’t happen if the starting controls are improperly designed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Accumulation of unburned propellants in the combustion chamber",
            "b) Explosion upon ignition",
            "c) Eventual damage to rocket engine",
            "d) Increase in dripping flow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Improper starting control design may or may not lead to an increase in dripping flow. But it can lead to the accumulation of unburned propellants in the combustion chamber, chances of explosion upon ignition and eventual damage to a rocket engine."
    }
]